Importing Modules by Name String

The module name in an import or from statement is a hardcoded variable name. Sometimes, though, your program will get the name of a module to be imported as a string at runtime (e.g., if a user selects a module name from within a GUI). Unfortunately, you can’t use import statements directly to load a module given its name as a string—Python expects a variable name, not a string. For instance:

>>> import "string"
  File "<stdin>", line 1
    import "string"
                  ^
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

It also won’t work to simply assign the string to a variable name:

x = "string"
import x

Here, Python will try to import a file x.py, not the string module—the name in an import statement both becomes a variable assigned to the loaded module and identifies the external file literally.

To get around this, you need to use special tools to load a module dynamically from a string that is generated at runtime. The most general approach is to construct an import statement as a string of Python code and pass it to the exec built-in function to run (exec is a statement in Python 2.6, but it can be used exactly as shown here—the parentheses are simply ignored):

>>> modname = "string"
>>> exec("import " + modname)      # Run a string of code
>>> string                         # Imported in this namespace
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python30\lib\string.py'>

The exec function (and its cousin for expressions, eval) compiles a string of code and passes it to the Python interpreter to be executed. In Python, the byte code compiler is available at runtime, so you can write programs that construct and run other programs like this. By default, exec runs the code in the current scope, but you can get more specific by passing in optional namespace dictionaries.

The only real drawback to exec is that it must compile the import statement each time it runs; if it runs many times, your code may run quicker if it uses the built-in __import__ function to load from a name string instead. The effect is similar, but __import__ returns the module object, so assign it to a name here to keep it:

>>> modname = "string"
>>> string = __import__(modname)
>>> string
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python30\lib\string.py'>

Module Gotchas

In this section, we’ll take a look at the usual collection of boundary cases that make life interesting for Python beginners. Some are so obscure that it was hard to come up with examples, but most illustrate something important about the language.

Statement Order Matters in Top-Level Code

When a module is first imported (or reloaded), Python executes its statements one by one, from the top of the file to the bottom. This has a few subtle implications regarding forward references that are worth underscoring here:

Code at the top level of a module file (not nested in a function) runs as soon as Python reaches it during an import; because of that, it can’t reference names assigned lower in the file.

Code inside a function body doesn’t run until the function is called; because names in a function aren’t resolved until the function actually runs, they can usually reference names anywhere in the file.

Generally, forward references are only a concern in top-level module code that executes immediately; functions can reference names arbitrarily. Here’s an example that illustrates forward reference:

func1()                           # Error: "func1" not yet assigned

def func1():
    print(func2())                # Okay: "func2" looked up later

func1()                           # Error: "func2" not yet assigned

def func2():
    return "Hello"

func1()                           # Okay: "func1" and "func2" assigned

When this file is imported (or run as a standalone program), Python executes its statements from top to bottom. The first call to func1 fails because the func1 def hasn’t run yet. The call to func2 inside func1 works as long as func2’s def has been reached by the time func1 is called (it hasn’t when the second top-level func1 call is run). The last call to func1 at the bottom of the file works because func1 and func2 have both been assigned.

Mixing defs with top-level code is not only hard to read, it’s dependent on statement ordering. As a rule of thumb, if you need to mix immediate code with defs, put your defs at the top of the file and your top-level code at the bottom. That way, your functions are guaranteed to be defined and assigned by the time code that uses them runs.

from Copies Names but Doesn’t Link

Although it’s commonly used, the from statement is the source of a variety of potential gotchas in Python. The from statement is really an assignment to names in the importer’s scope—a name-copy operation, not a name aliasing. The implications of this are the same as for all assignments in Python, but they’re subtle, especially given that the code that shares the objects lives in different files. For instance, suppose we define the following module, nested1.py:

# nested1.py
X = 99
def printer(): print(X)

If we import its two names using from in another module, nested2.py, we get copies of those names, not links to them. Changing a name in the importer resets only the binding of the local version of that name, not the name in nested1.py:

# nested2.py
from nested1 import X, printer    # Copy names out
X = 88                            # Changes my "X" only!
printer()                         # nested1's X is still 99

% python nested2.py
99

If we use import to get the whole module and then assign to a qualified name, however, we change the name in nested1.py. Qualification directs Python to a name in the module object, rather than a name in the importer, nested3.py:

# nested3.py
import nested1                    # Get module as a whole
nested1.X = 88                    # OK: change nested1's X
nested1.printer()

% python nested3.py
88

from * Can Obscure the Meaning of Variables

I mentioned this earlier but saved the details for here. Because you don’t list the variables you want when using the from module import * statement form, it can accidentally overwrite names you’re already using in your scope. Worse, it can make it difficult to determine where a variable comes from. This is especially true if the from * form is used on more than one imported file.

For example, if you use from * on three modules, you’ll have no way of knowing what a raw function call really means, short of searching all three external module files (all of which may be in other directories):

>>> from module1 import *          # Bad: may overwrite my names silently
>>> from module2 import *          # Worse: no way to tell what we get!
>>> from module3 import *
>>> . . .

>>> func()                         # Huh???

The solution again is not to do this: try to explicitly list the attributes you want in your from statements, and restrict the from * form to at most one imported module per file. That way, any undefined names must by deduction be in the module named in the single from *. You can avoid the issue altogether if you always use import instead of from, but that advice is too harsh; like much else in programming, from is a convenient tool if used wisely. Even this example isn’t an absolute evil—it’s OK for a program to use this technique to collect names in a single space for convenience, as long as it’s well known.

reload May Not Impact from Imports

Here’s another from-related gotcha: as discussed previously, because from copies (assigns) names when run, there’s no link back to the modules where the names came from. Names imported with from simply become references to objects, which happen to have been referenced by the same names in the importee when the from ran.

Because of this behavior, reloading the importee has no effect on clients that import its names using from. That is, the client’s names will still reference the original objects fetched with from, even if the names in the original module are later reset:

from module import X          # X may not reflect any module reloads!
 . . .
from imp import reload
reload(module)                # Changes module, but not my names
X                             # Still references old object

To make reloads more effective, use import and name qualification instead of from. Because qualifications always go back to the module, they will find the new bindings of module names after reloading:

import module                 # Get module, not names
 . . .
from imp import reload
reload(module)                # Changes module in-place
module.X                      # Get current X: reflects module reloads

reload, from, and Interactive Testing

In fact, the prior gotcha is even more subtle than it appears. Chapter 3 warned that it’s usually better not to launch programs with imports and reloads because of the complexities involved. Things get even worse when from is brought into the mix. Python beginners often stumble onto its issues in scenarios like the one outlined next. Say that after opening a module file in a text edit window, you launch an interactive session to load and test your module with from:

from module import function
function(1, 2, 3)

Finding a bug, you jump back to the edit window, make a change, and try to reload the module this way:

from imp import reload
reload(module)

This doesn’t work, because the from statement assigned the name function, not module. To refer to the module in a reload, you have to first load it with an import statement at least once:

from imp import reload
import module
reload(module)
function(1, 2, 3)

However, this doesn’t quite work either—reload updates the module object, but as discussed in the preceding section, names like function that were copied out of the module in the past still refer to the old objects (in this instance, the original version of the function). To really get the new function, you must refer to it as module.function after the reload, or rerun the from:

from imp import reload
import module
reload(module)
from module import function        # Or give up and use module.function()
function(1, 2, 3)

Now, the new version of the function will finally run.

As you can see, there are problems inherent in using reload with from: not only do you have to remember to reload after imports, but you also have to remember to rerun your from statements after reloads. This is complex enough to trip up even an expert once in a while. (In fact, the situation has gotten even worse in Python 3.0, because you must also remember to import reload itself!)

The short story is that you should not expect reload and from to play together nicely. The best policy is not to combine them at all—use reload with import, or launch your programs other ways, as suggested in Chapter 3: using the Run→Run Module menu option in IDLE, file icon clicks, system command lines, or the exec built-in function.

Recursive from Imports May Not Work

I saved the most bizarre (and, thankfully, obscure) gotcha for last. Because imports execute a file’s statements from top to bottom, you need to be careful when using modules that import each other (known as recursive imports). Because the statements in a module may not all have been run when it imports another module, some of its names may not yet exist.

If you use import to fetch the module as a whole, this may or may not matter; the module’s names won’t be accessed until you later use qualification to fetch their values. But if you use from to fetch specific names, you must bear in mind that you will only have access to names in that module that have already been assigned.

For instance, take the following modules, recur1 and recur2. recur1 assigns a name X, and then imports recur2 before assigning the name Y. At this point, recur2 can fetch recur1 as a whole with an import (it already exists in Python’s internal modules table), but if it uses from, it will be able to see only the name X; the name Y, which is assigned below the import in recur1, doesn’t yet exist, so you get an error:

# recur1.py
X = 1
import recur2                             # Run recur2 now if it doesn't exist
Y = 2

# recur2.py
from recur1 import X                      # OK: "X" already assigned
from recur1 import Y                      # Error: "Y" not yet assigned

C:\misc> C:\Python30\python
>>> import recur1
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
  File "recur1.py", line 2, in <module>
    import recur2
  File "recur2.py", line 2, in <module>
    from recur1 import Y
ImportError: cannot import name Y

Python avoids rerunning recur1’s statements when they are imported recursively from recur2 (otherwise the imports would send the script into an infinite loop), but recur1’s namespace is incomplete when it’s imported by recur2.

The solution? Don’t use from in recursive imports (no, really!). Python won’t get stuck in a cycle if you do, but your programs will once again be dependent on the order of the statements in the modules.

There are two ways out of this gotcha:

You can usually eliminate import cycles like this by careful design—maximizing cohesion and minimizing coupling are good first steps.

If you can’t break the cycles completely, postpone module name accesses by using import and qualification (instead of from), or by running your froms either inside functions (instead of at the top level of the module), or near the bottom of your file to defer their execution.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Variables at the top level of a module whose names begin with a single underscore are not copied out to the importing scope when the from * statement form is used. They can still be accessed by an import or the normal from statement form, though.

If a module’s __name__ variable is the string "__main__", it means that the file is being executed as a top-level script instead of being imported from another file in the program. That is, the file is being used as a program, not a library.

User input usually comes into a script as a string; to import the referenced module given its string name, you can build and run an import statement with exec, or pass the string name in a call to the __import__ function.

Changing sys.path only affects one running program, and is temporary—the change goes away when the program ends. PYTHONPATH settings live in the operating system—they are picked up globally by all programs on a machine, and changes to these settings endure after programs exit.

No, we can’t import from the past in Python. We can install (or stubbornly use) an older version of the language, but the latest Python is generally the best Python.

Test Your Knowledge: Part V Exercises

See Part V, Modules in Appendix B for the solutions.

Import basics. Write a program that counts the lines and characters in a file (similar in spirit to wc on Unix). With your text editor, code a Python module called mymod.py that exports three top-level names:

A countLines(name) function that reads an input file and counts the number of lines in it (hint: file.readlines does most of the work for you, and len does the rest).

A countChars(name) function that reads an input file and counts the number of characters in it (hint: file.read returns a single string).

A test(name) function that calls both counting functions with a given input filename. Such a filename generally might be passed in, hardcoded, input with the input built-in function, or pulled from a command line via the sys.argv list shown in this chapter’s formats.py example; for now, you can assume it’s a passed-in function argument.

All three mymod functions should expect a filename string to be passed in. If you type more than two or three lines per function, you’re working much too hard—use the hints I just gave!

Next, test your module interactively, using import and attribute references to fetch your exports. Does your PYTHONPATH need to include the directory where you created mymod.py? Try running your module on itself: e.g., test("mymod.py"). Note that test opens the file twice; if you’re feeling ambitious, you may be able to improve this by passing an open file object into the two count functions (hint: file.seek(0) is a file rewind).

from/from *. Test your mymod module from exercise 1 interactively by using from to load the exports directly, first by name, then using the from * variant to fetch everything.

__main__. Add a line in your mymod module that calls the test function automatically only when the module is run as a script, not when it is imported. The line you add will probably test the value of __name__ for the string "__main__", as shown in this chapter. Try running your module from the system command line; then, import the module and test its functions interactively. Does it still work in both modes?

Nested imports. Write a second module, myclient.py, that imports mymod and tests its functions; then run myclient from the system command line. If myclient uses from to fetch from mymod, will mymod’s functions be accessible from the top level of myclient? What if it imports with import instead? Try coding both variations in myclient and test interactively by importing myclient and inspecting its __dict__ attribute.

Package imports. Import your file from a package. Create a subdirectory called mypkg nested in a directory on your module import search path, move the mymod.py module file you created in exercise 1 or 3 into the new directory, and try to import it with a package import of the form import mypkg.mymod.

You’ll need to add an __init__.py file in the directory your module was moved to make this go, but it should work on all major Python platforms (that’s part of the reason Python uses “.” as a path separator). The package directory you create can be simply a subdirectory of the one you’re working in; if it is, it will be found via the home directory component of the search path, and you won’t have to configure your path. Add some code to your __init__.py, and see if it runs on each import.

Reloads. Experiment with module reloads: perform the tests in Chapter 22’s changer.py example, changing the called function’s message and/or behavior repeatedly, without stopping the Python interpreter. Depending on your system, you might be able to edit changer in another window, or suspend the Python interpreter and edit in the same window (on Unix, a Ctrl-Z key combination usually suspends the current process, and an fg command later resumes it).

Circular imports.[56] In the section on recursive import gotchas, importing recur1 raised an error. But if you restart Python and import recur2 interactively, the error doesn’t occur—test this and see for yourself. Why do you think it works to import recur2, but not recur1? (Hint: Python stores new modules in the built-in sys.modules table—a dictionary—before running their code; later imports fetch the module from this table first, whether the module is “complete” yet or not.) Now, try running recur1 as a top-level script file: python recur1.py. Do you get the same error that occurs when recur1 is imported interactively? Why? (Hint: when modules are run as programs, they aren’t imported, so this case has the same effect as importing recur2 interactively; recur2 is the first module imported.) What happens when you run recur2 as a script?

[54] As we saw in Chapter 17, because a function can access its enclosing module by going through the sys.modules table like this, it’s possible to emulate the effect of the global statement. For instance, the effect of global X; X=0 can be simulated (albeit with much more typing!) by saying this inside a function: import sys; glob=sys.modules[__name__]; glob.X=0. Remember, each module gets a __name__ attribute for free; it’s visible as a global name inside the functions within the module. This trick provides another way to change both local and global variables of the same name inside a function.

[55] Tools such as mydir.listing can be preloaded into the interactive namespace by importing them in the file referenced by the PYTHONSTARTUP environment variable. Because code in the startup file runs in the interactive namespace (module __main__), importing common tools in the startup file can save you some typing. See Appendix A for more details.

[56] Note that circular imports are extremely rare in practice. On the other hand, if you can understand why they are a potential problem, you know a lot about Python’s import semantics.

Chapter 25. OOP: The Big Picture

So far in this book, we’ve been using the term “object” generically. Really, the code written up to this point has been object-based—we’ve passed objects around our scripts, used them in expressions, called their methods, and so on. For our code to qualify as being truly object-oriented (OO), though, our objects will generally need to also participate in something called an inheritance hierarchy.

This chapter begins our exploration of the Python class—a device used to implement new kinds of objects in Python that support inheritance. Classes are Python’s main object-oriented programming (OOP) tool, so we’ll also look at OOP basics along the way in this part of the book. OOP offers a different and often more effective way of looking at programming, in which we factor code to minimize redundancy, and write new programs by customizing existing code instead of changing it in-place.

In Python, classes are created with a new statement: the class statement. As you’ll see, the objects defined with classes can look a lot like the built-in types we studied earlier in the book. In fact, classes really just apply and extend the ideas we’ve already covered; roughly, they are packages of functions that use and process built-in object types. Classes, though, are designed to create and manage new objects, and they also support inheritance—a mechanism of code customization and reuse above and beyond anything we’ve seen so far.

One note up front: in Python, OOP is entirely optional, and you don’t need to use classes just to get started. In fact, you can get plenty of work done with simpler constructs such as functions, or even simple top-level script code. Because using classes well requires some up-front planning, they tend to be of more interest to people who work in strategic mode (doing long-term product development) than to people who work in tactical mode (where time is in very short supply).

Still, as you’ll see in this part of the book, classes turn out to be one of the most useful tools Python provides. When used well, classes can actually cut development time radically. They’re also employed in popular Python tools like the tkinter GUI API, so most Python programmers will usually find at least a working knowledge of class basics helpful.

Why Use Classes?

Remember when I told you that programs “do things with stuff”? In simple terms, classes are just a way to define new sorts of stuff, reflecting real objects in a program’s domain. For instance, suppose we decide to implement that hypothetical pizza-making robot we used as an example in Chapter 16. If we implement it using classes, we can model more of its real-world structure and relationships. Two aspects of OOP prove useful here:

Inheritance

Pizza-making robots are kinds of robots, so they possess the usual robot-y properties. In OOP terms, we say they “inherit” properties from the general category of all robots. These common properties need to be implemented only once for the general case and can be reused by all types of robots we may build in the future.

Composition

Pizza-making robots are really collections of components that work together as a team. For instance, for our robot to be successful, it might need arms to roll dough, motors to maneuver to the oven, and so on. In OOP parlance, our robot is an example of composition; it contains other objects that it activates to do its bidding. Each component might be coded as a class, which defines its own behavior and relationships.

General OOP ideas like inheritance and composition apply to any application that can be decomposed into a set of objects. For example, in typical GUI systems, interfaces are written as collections of widgets—buttons, labels, and so on—which are all drawn when their container is drawn (composition). Moreover, we may be able to write our own custom widgets—buttons with unique fonts, labels with new color schemes, and the like—which are specialized versions of more general interface devices (inheritance).

From a more concrete programming perspective, classes are Python program units, just like functions and modules: they are another compartment for packaging logic and data. In fact, classes also define new namespaces, much like modules. But, compared to other program units we’ve already seen, classes have three critical distinctions that make them more useful when it comes to building new objects:

Multiple instances

Classes are essentially factories for generating one or more objects. Every time we call a class, we generate a new object with a distinct namespace. Each object generated from a class has access to the class’s attributes and gets a namespace of its own for data that varies per object.

Customization via inheritance

Classes also support the OOP notion of inheritance; we can extend a class by redefining its attributes outside the class itself. More generally, classes can build up namespace hierarchies, which define names to be used by objects created from classes in the hierarchy.

Operator overloading

By providing special protocol methods, classes can define objects that respond to the sorts of operations we saw at work on built-in types. For instance, objects made with classes can be sliced, concatenated, indexed, and so on. Python provides hooks that classes can use to intercept and implement any built-in type operation.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

OOP is about code reuse—you factor code to minimize redundancy and program by customizing what already exists instead of changing code in-place or starting from scratch.

An inheritance search looks for an attribute first in the instance object, then in the class the instance was created from, then in all higher superclasses, progressing from the bottom to the top of the object tree, and from left to right (by default). The search stops at the first place the attribute is found. Because the lowest version of a name found along the way wins, class hierarchies naturally support customization by extension.

Both class and instance objects are namespaces (packages of variables that appear as attributes). The main difference between them is that classes are a kind of factory for creating multiple instances. Classes also support operator overloading methods, which instances inherit, and treat any functions nested within them as special methods for processing instances.

The first argument in a class method function is special because it always receives the instance object that is the implied subject of the method call. It’s usually called self by convention. Because method functions always have this implied subject object context by default, we say they are “object-oriented”—i.e., designed to process or change objects.

If the __init__ method is coded or inherited in a class, Python calls it automatically each time an instance of that class is created. It’s known as the constructor method; it is passed the new instance implicitly, as well as any arguments passed explicitly to the class name. It’s also the most commonly used operator overloading method. If no __init__ method is present, instances simply begin life as empty namespaces.

You create a class instance by calling the class name as though it were a function; any arguments passed into the class name show up as arguments two and beyond in the __init__ constructor method. The new instance remembers the class it was created from for inheritance purposes.

You create a class by running a class statement; like function definitions, these statements normally run when the enclosing module file is imported (more on this in the next chapter).

You specify a class’s superclasses by listing them in parentheses in the class statement, after the new class’s name. The left-to-right order in which the classes are listed in the parentheses gives the left-to-right inheritance search order in the class tree.

[57] In other literature, you may also occasionally see the terms base classes and derived classes used to describe superclasses and subclasses, respectively.

[58] If you’ve ever used C++ or Java, you’ll recognize that Python’s self is the same as the this pointer, but self is always explicit in Python to make attribute accesses more obvious.

[59] Note that the company list in this example could be stored in a file with Python object pickling, introduced in Chapter 9 when we met files, to yield a persistent employee database. Python also comes with a module named shelve, which would allow you to store the pickled representation of the class instances in an access-by-key filesystem; the third-party open source ZODB system does the same but has better support for production-quality object-oriented databases.

Chapter 26. Class Coding Basics

Now that we’ve talked about OOP in the abstract, it’s time to see how this translates to actual code. This chapter begins to fill in the syntax details behind the class model in Python.

If you’ve never been exposed to OOP in the past, classes can seem somewhat complicated if taken in a single dose. To make class coding easier to absorb, we’ll begin our detailed exploration of OOP by taking a first look at some basic classes in action in this chapter. We’ll expand on the details introduced here in later chapters of this part of the book, but in their basic form, Python classes are easy to understand.

In fact, classes have just three primary distinctions. At a base level, they are mostly just namespaces, much like the modules we studied in Part V. Unlike modules, though, classes also have support for generating multiple objects, for namespace inheritance, and for operator overloading. Let’s begin our class statement tour by exploring each of these three distinctions in turn.

The World’s Simplest Python Class

We’ve begun studying class statement syntax in detail in this chapter, but I’d again like to remind you that the basic inheritance model that classes produce is very simple—all it really involves is searching for attributes in trees of linked objects. In fact, we can create a class with nothing in it at all. The following statement makes a class with no attributes attached (an empty namespace object):

>>> class rec: pass              # Empty namespace object

We need the no-operation pass statement (discussed in Chapter 13) here because we don’t have any methods to code. After we make the class by running this statement interactively, we can start attaching attributes to the class by assigning names to it completely outside of the original class statement:

>>> rec.name = 'Bob'             # Just objects with attributes
>>> rec.age  = 40

And, after we’ve created these attributes by assignment, we can fetch them with the usual syntax. When used this way, a class is roughly similar to a “struct” in C, or a “record” in Pascal. It’s basically an object with field names attached to it (we can do similar work with dictionary keys, but it requires extra characters):

>>> print(rec.name)              # Like a C struct or a record
Bob

Notice that this works even though there are no instances of the class yet; classes are objects in their own right, even without instances. In fact, they are just self-contained namespaces, so as long as we have a reference to a class, we can set or change its attributes anytime we wish. Watch what happens when we do create two instances, though:

>>> x = rec()                    # Instances inherit class names
>>> y = rec()

These instances begin their lives as completely empty namespace objects. Because they remember the class from which they were made, though, they will obtain the attributes we attached to the class by inheritance:

>>> x.name, y.name               # name is stored on the class only
('Bob', 'Bob')

Really, these instances have no attributes of their own; they simply fetch the name attribute from the class object where it is stored. If we do assign an attribute to an instance, though, it creates (or changes) the attribute in that object, and no other—attribute references kick off inheritance searches, but attribute assignments affect only the objects in which the assignments are made. Here, x gets its own name, but y still inherits the name attached to the class above it:

>>> x.name = 'Sue'               # But assignment changes x only
>>> rec.name, x.name, y.name
('Bob', 'Sue', 'Bob')

In fact, as we’ll explore in more detail in Chapter 28, the attributes of a namespace object are usually implemented as dictionaries, and class inheritance trees are (generally speaking) just dictionaries with links to other dictionaries. If you know where to look, you can see this explicitly.

For example, the __dict__ attribute is the namespace dictionary for most class-based objects (some classes may also define attributes in __slots__, an advanced and seldom-used feature that we’ll study in Chapters 30 and 31). The following was run in Python 3.0; the order of names and set of __X__ internal names present can vary from release to release, but the names we assigned are present in all:

>>> rec.__dict__.keys()
['__module__', 'name', 'age', '__dict__', '__weakref__', '__doc__']

>>> list(x.__dict__.keys())
['name']

>>> list(y.__dict__.keys())                # list() not required in Python 2.6
[]

Here, the class’s namespace dictionary shows the name and age attributes we assigned to it, x has its own name, and y is still empty. Each instance has a link to its class for inheritance, though—it’s called __class__, if you want to inspect it:

>>> x.__class__
<class '__main__.rec'>

Classes also have a __bases__ attribute, which is a tuple of their superclasses:

>>> rec.__bases__                          # () empty tuple in Python 2.6
(<class 'object'>,)

These two attributes are how class trees are literally represented in memory by Python.

The main point to take away from this look under the hood is that Python’s class model is extremely dynamic. Classes and instances are just namespace objects, with attributes created on the fly by assignment. Those assignments usually happen within the class statements you code, but they can occur anywhere you have a reference to one of the objects in the tree.

Even methods, normally created by a def nested in a class, can be created completely independently of any class object. The following, for example, defines a simple function outside of any class that takes one argument:

>>> def upperName(self):
...     return self.name.upper()    # Still needs a self

There is nothing about a class here yet—it’s a simple function, and it can be called as such at this point, provided we pass in an object with a name attribute (the name self does not make this special in any way):

>>> upperName(x)                    # Call as a simple function
'SUE'

If we assign this simple function to an attribute of our class, though, it becomes a method, callable through any instance (as well as through the class name itself, as long as we pass in an instance manually):[61]

>>> rec.method = upperName

>>> x.method()                              # Run  method to process x
'SUE'

>>> y.method()                              # Same, but pass y to self
'BOB'

>>> rec.method(x)                           # Can call through instance or class
'SUE'

Normally, classes are filled out by class statements, and instance attributes are created by assignments to self attributes in method functions. The point again, though, is that they don’t have to be; OOP in Python really is mostly about looking up attributes in linked namespace objects.

Classes Versus Dictionaries

Although the simple classes of the prior section are meant to illustrate class model basics, the techniques they employ can also be used for real work. For example, Chapter 8 showed how to use dictionaries to record properties of entities in our programs. It turns out that classes can serve this role, too—they package information like dictionaries, but can also bundle processing logic in the form of methods. For reference, here is the example for dictionary-based records we used earlier in the book:

>>> rec = {}
>>> rec['name'] = 'mel'                     # Dictionary-based record
>>> rec['age']  = 45
>>> rec['job']  = 'trainer/writer'
>>>
>>> print(rec['name'])
mel

This code emulates tools like records in other languages. As we just saw, though, there are also multiple ways to do the same with classes. Perhaps the simplest is this—trading keys for attributes:

>>> class rec: pass
...
>>> rec.name = 'mel'                        # Class-based record
>>> rec.age  = 45
>>> rec.job  = 'trainer/writer'
>>>
>>> print(rec.age)
45

This code has substantially less syntax than the dictionary equivalent. It uses an empty class statement to generate an empty namespace object. Once we make the empty class, we fill it out by assigning class attributes over time, as before.

This works, but a new class statement will be required for each distinct record we will need. Perhaps more typically, we can instead generate instances of an empty class to represent each distinct entity:

>>> class rec: pass
...
>>> pers1 = rec()                           # Instance-based records
>>> pers1.name = 'mel'
>>> pers1.job  = 'trainer'
>>> pers1.age   = 40
>>>
>>> pers2 = rec()
>>> pers2.name = 'vls'
>>> pers2.job  = 'developer'
>>>
>>> pers1.name, pers2.name
('mel', 'vls')

Here, we make two records from the same class. Instances start out life empty, just like classes. We then fill in the records by assigning to attributes. This time, though, there are two separate objects, and hence two separate name attributes. In fact, instances of the same class don’t even have to have the same set of attribute names; in this example, one has a unique age name. Instances really are distinct namespaces, so each has a distinct attribute dictionary. Although they are normally filled out consistently by class methods, they are more flexible than you might expect.

Finally, we might instead code a more full-blown class to implement the record and its processing:

>>> class Person:
...     def __init__(self, name, job):      # Class = Data + Logic
...         self.name = name
...         self.job  = job
...     def info(self):
...         return (self.name, self.job)
...
>>> rec1 = Person('mel', 'trainer')
>>> rec2 = Person('vls', 'developer')
>>>
>>> rec1.job, rec2.info()
('trainer', ('vls', 'developer'))

This scheme also makes multiple instances, but the class is not empty this time: we’ve added logic (methods) to initialize instances at construction time and collect attributes into a tuple. The constructor imposes some consistency on instances here by always setting the name and job attributes. Together, the class’s methods and instance attributes create a package, which combines both data and logic.

We could further extend this code by adding logic to compute salaries, parse names, and so on. Ultimately, we might link the class into a larger hierarchy to inherit an existing set of methods via the automatic attribute search of classes, or perhaps even store instances of the class in a file with Python object pickling to make them persistent. In fact, we will—in the next chapter, we’ll expand on this analogy between classes and records with a more realistic running example that demonstrates class basics in action.

In the end, although types like dictionaries are flexible, classes allow us to add behavior to objects in ways that built-in types and simple functions do not directly support. Although we can store functions in dictionaries, too, using them to process implied instances is nowhere near as natural as it is in classes.

Chapter 27. A More Realistic Example

We’ll dig into more class syntax details in the next chapter. Before we do, though, I’d like to show you a more realistic example of classes in action that’s more practical than what we’ve seen so far. In this chapter, we’re going to build a set of classes that do something more concrete—recording and processing information about people. As you’ll see, what we call instances and classes in Python programming can often serve the same roles as records and programs in more traditional terms.

Specifically, in this chapter we’re going to code two classes:

Person—a class that creates and processes information about people

Manager—a customization of Person that modifies inherited behavior

Along the way, we’ll make instances of both classes and test out their functionality. When we’re done, I’ll show you a nice example use case for classes—we’ll store our instances in a shelve object-oriented database, to make them permanent. That way, you can use this code as a template for fleshing out a full-blown personal database written entirely in Python.

Besides actual utility, though, our aim here is also educational: this chapter provides a tutorial on object-oriented programming in Python. Often, people grasp the last chapter’s class syntax on paper, but have trouble seeing how to get started when confronted with having to code a new class from scratch. Toward this end, we’ll take it one step at a time here, to help you learn the basics; we’ll build up the classes gradually, so you can see how their features come together in complete programs.

In the end, our classes will still be relatively small in terms of code, but they will demonstrate all of the main ideas in Python’s OOP model. Despite its syntax details, Python’s class system really is largely just a matter of searching for an attribute in a tree of objects, along with a special first argument for functions.

Step 1: Making Instances

OK, so much for the design phase—let’s move on to implementation. Our first task is to start coding the main class, Person. In your favorite text editor, open a new file for the code we’ll be writing. It’s a fairly strong convention in Python to begin module names with a lowercase letter and class names with an uppercase letter; like the name of self arguments in methods, this is not required by the language, but it’s so common that deviating might be confusing to people who later read your code. To conform, we’ll call our new module file person.py and our class within it Person, like this:

# File person.py (start)

class Person:

All our work will be done in this file until later in this chapter. We can code any number of functions and classes in a single module file in Python, and this one’s person.py name might not make much sense if we add unrelated components to it later. For now, we’ll assume everything in it will be Person-related. It probably should be anyhow—as we’ve learned, modules tend to work best when they have a single, cohesive purpose.

Coding Constructors

Now, the first thing we want to do with our Person class is record basic information about people—to fill out record fields, if you will. Of course, these are known as instance object attributes in Python-speak, and they generally are created by assignment to self attributes in class method functions. The normal way to give instance attributes their first values is to assign them to self in the __init__ constructor method, which contains code run automatically by Python each time an instance is created. Let’s add one to our class:

# Add record field initialization

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job, pay):      # Constructor takes 3 arguments
        self.name = name                     # Fill out fields when created
        self.job  = job                      # self is the new instance object
        self.pay  = pay

This is a very common coding pattern: we pass in the data to be attached to an instance as arguments to the constructor method and assign them to self to retain them permanently. In OO terms, self is the newly created instance object, and name, job, and pay become state information—descriptive data saved on an object for later use. Although other techniques (such as enclosing scope references) can save details, too, instance attributes make this very explicit and easy to understand.

Notice that the argument names appear twice here. This code might seem a bit redundant at first, but it’s not. The job argument, for example, is a local variable in the scope of the __init__ function, but self.job is an attribute of the instance that’s the implied subject of the method call. They are two different variables, which happen to have the same name. By assigning the job local to the self.job attribute with self.job=job, we save the passed-in job on the instance for later use. As usual in Python, where a name is assigned (or what object it is assigned to) determines what it means.

Speaking of arguments, there’s really nothing magical about __init__, apart from the fact that it’s called automatically when an instance is made and has a special first argument. Despite its weird name, it’s a normal function and supports all the features of functions we’ve already covered. We can, for example, provide defaults for some of its arguments, so they need not be provided in cases where their values aren’t available or useful.

To demonstrate, let’s make the job argument optional—it will default to None, meaning the person being created is not (currently) employed. If job defaults to None, we’ll probably want to default pay to 0, too, for consistency (unless some of the people you know manage to get paid without having jobs!). In fact, we have to specify a default for pay because according to Python’s syntax rules, any arguments in a function’s header after the first default must all have defaults, too:

# Add defaults for constructor arguments

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):         # Normal function args
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay

What this code means is that we’ll need to pass in a name when making Persons, but job and pay are now optional; they’ll default to None and 0 if omitted. The self argument, as usual, is filled in by Python automatically to refer to the instance object—assigning values to attributes of self attaches them to the new instance.

Testing As You Go

This class doesn’t do much yet—it essentially just fills out the fields of a new record—but it’s a real working class. At this point we could add more code to it for more features, but we won’t do that yet. As you’ve probably begun to appreciate already, programming in Python is really a matter of incremental prototyping—you write some code, test it, write more code, test again, and so on. Because Python provides both an interactive session and nearly immediate turnaround after code changes, it’s more natural to test as you go than to write a huge amount of code to test all at once.

Before adding more features, then, let’s test what we’ve got so far by making a few instances of our class and displaying their attributes as created by the constructor. We could do this interactively, but as you’ve also probably surmised by now, interactive testing has its limits—it gets tedious to have to reimport modules and retype test cases each time you start a new testing session. More commonly, Python programmers use the interactive prompt for simple one-off tests but do more substantial testing by writing code at the bottom of the file that contains the objects to be tested, like this:

# Add incremental self-test code

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay

bob = Person('Bob Smith')                         # Test the class
sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)  # Runs __init__ automatically
print(bob.name, bob.pay)                          # Fetch attached attributes
print(sue.name, sue.pay)                          # sue's and bob's attrs differ

Notice here that the bob object accepts the defaults for job and pay, but sue provides values explicitly. Also note how we use keyword arguments when making sue; we could pass by position instead, but the keywords may help remind us later what the data is (and they allow us to pass the arguments in any left-to-right order we like). Again, despite its unusual name, __init__ is a normal function, supporting everything you already know about functions—including both defaults and pass-by-name keyword arguments.

When this file runs as a script, the test code at the bottom makes two instances of our class and prints two attributes of each (name and pay):

C:\misc> person.py
Bob Smith 0
Sue Jones 100000

You can also type this file’s test code at Python’s interactive prompt (assuming you import the Person class there first), but coding canned tests inside the module file like this makes it much easier to rerun them in the future.

Although this is fairly simple code, it’s already demonstrating something important. Notice that bob’s name is not sue’s, and sue’s pay is not bob’s. Each is an independent record of information. Technically, bob and sue are both namespace objects—like all class instances, they each have their own independent copy of the state information created by the class. Because each instance of a class has its own set of self attributes, classes are a natural for recording information for multiple objects this way; just like built-in types, classes serve as a sort of object factory. Other Python program structures, such as functions and modules, have no such concept.

Using Code Two Ways

As is, the test code at the bottom of the file works, but there’s a big catch—its top-level print statements run both when the file is run as a script and when it is imported as a module. This means if we ever decide to import the class in this file in order to use it somewhere else (and we will later in this chapter), we’ll see the output of its test code every time the file is imported. That’s not very good software citizenship, though: client programs probably don’t care about our internal tests and won’t want to see our output mixed in with their own.

Although we could split the test code off into a separate file, it’s often more convenient to code tests in the same file as the items to be tested. It would be better to arrange to run the test statements at the bottom only when the file is run for testing, not when the file is imported. That’s exactly what the module __name__ check is designed for, as you learned in the preceding part of this book. Here’s what this addition looks like:

# Allow this file to be imported as well as run/tested

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay

if __name__ == '__main__':                  # When run for testing only
    # self-test code
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob.name, bob.pay)
    print(sue.name, sue.pay)

Now, we get exactly the behavior we’re after—running the file as a top-level script tests it because its __name__ is __main__, but importing it as a library of classes later does not:

C:\misc> person.py
Bob Smith 0
Sue Jones 100000

c:\misc> python
Python 3.0.1 (r301:69561, Feb 13 2009, 20:04:18) ...
>>> import person
>>>

When imported, the file now defines the class, but does not use it. When run directly, this file creates two instances of our class as before, and prints two attributes of each; again, because each instance is an independent namespace object, the values of their attributes differ.

Version Portability Note

I’m running all the code in this chapter under Python 3.0, and using the 3.0 print function call syntax. If you run under 2.6 the code will work as-is, but you’ll notice parentheses around some output lines because the extra parentheses in prints turn multiple items into a tuple:

c:\misc> c:\python26\python person.py
('Bob Smith', 0)
('Sue Jones', 100000)

If this difference is the sort of detail that might keep you awake at nights, simply remove the parentheses to use 2.6 print statements. You can also avoid the extra parentheses portably by using formatting to yield a single object to print. Either of the following works in both 2.6 and 3.0, though the method form is newer:

print('{0} {1}'.format(bob.name, bob.pay))    # New format method
print('%s %s' % (bob.name, bob.pay))          # Format expression

Step 2: Adding Behavior Methods

Everything looks good so far—at this point, our class is essentially a record factory; it creates and fills out fields of records (attributes of instances, in more Pythonic terms). Even as limited as it is, though, we can still run some operations on its objects. Although classes add an extra layer of structure, they ultimately do most of their work by embedding and processing basic core data types like lists and strings. In other words, if you already know how to use Python’s simple core types, you already know much of the Python class story; classes are really just a minor structural extension.

For example, the name field of our objects is a simple string, so we can extract last names from our objects by splitting on spaces and indexing. These are all core data type operations, which work whether their subjects are embedded in class instances or not:

>>> name = 'Bob Smith'      # Simple string, outside class
>>> name.split()            # Extract last name
['Bob', 'Smith']
>>> name.split()[-1]        # Or [1], if always just two parts
'Smith'

Similarly, we can give an object a pay raise by updating its pay field—that is, by changing its state information in-place with an assignment. This task also involves basic operations that work on Python’s core objects, regardless of whether they are standalone or embedded in a class structure:

>>> pay = 100000            # Simple variable, outside class
>>> pay *= 1.10             # Give a 10% raise
>>> print(pay)              # Or: pay = pay * 1.10, if you like to type
110000.0                    # Or: pay = pay + (pay * .10), if you _really_ do!

To apply these operations to the Person objects created by our script, simply do to bob.name and sue.pay what we just did to name and pay. The operations are the same, but the subject objects are attached to attributes in our class structure:

# Process embedded built-in types: strings, mutability

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay

if __name__ == '__main__':
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob.name, bob.pay)
    print(sue.name, sue.pay)
    print(bob.name.split()[-1])            # Extract object's last name
    sue.pay *= 1.10                        # Give this object a raise
    print(sue.pay)

We’ve added the last three lines here; when they’re run, we extract bob’s last name by using basic string and list operations and give sue a pay raise by modifying her pay attribute in-place with basic number operations. In a sense, sue is also a mutable object—her state changes in-place just like a list after an append call:

Bob Smith 0
Sue Jones 100000
Smith
110000.0

The preceding code works as planned, but if you show it to a veteran software developer he’ll probably tell you that its general approach is not a great idea in practice. Hardcoding operations like these outside of the class can lead to maintenance problems in the future.

For example, what if you’ve hardcoded the last-name-extraction formula at many different places in your program? If you ever need to change the way it works (to support a new name structure, for instance), you’ll need to hunt down and update every occurrence. Similarly, if the pay-raise code ever changes (e.g., to require approval or database updates), you may have multiple copies to modify. Just finding all the appearances of such code may be problematic in larger programs—they may be scattered across many files, split into individual steps, and so on.

Coding Methods

What we really want to do here is employ a software design concept known as encapsulation. The idea with encapsulation is to wrap up operation logic behind interfaces, such that each operation is coded only once in our program. That way, if our needs change in the future, there is just one copy to update. Moreover, we’re free to change the single copy’s internals almost arbitrarily, without breaking the code that uses it.

In Python terms, we want to code operations on objects in class methods, instead of littering them throughout our program. In fact, this is one of the things that classes are very good at—factoring code to remove redundancy and thus optimize maintainability. As an added bonus, turning operations into methods enables them to be applied to any instance of the class, not just those that they’ve been hardcoded to process.

This is all simpler in code than it may sound in theory. The following achieves encapsulation by moving the two operations from code outside the class into class methods. While we’re at it, let’s change our self-test code at the bottom to use the new methods we’re creating, instead of hardcoding operations:

# Add methods to encapsulate operations for maintainability

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay
    def lastName(self):                               # Behavior methods
        return self.name.split()[-1]                  # self is implied subject
    def giveRaise(self, percent):
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent))      # Must change here only

if __name__ == '__main__':
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob.name, bob.pay)
    print(sue.name, sue.pay)
    print(bob.lastName(), sue.lastName())             # Use the new methods
    sue.giveRaise(.10)                                # instead of hardcoding
    print(sue.pay)

As we’ve learned, methods are simply normal functions that are attached to classes and designed to process instances of those classes. The instance is the subject of the method call and is passed to the method’s self argument automatically.

The transformation to the methods in this version is straightforward. The new lastName method, for example, simply does to self what the previous version hardcoded for bob, because self is the implied subject when the method is called. lastName also returns the result, because this operation is a called function now; it computes a value for its caller to use, even if it is just to be printed. Similarly, the new giveRaise method just does to self what we did to sue before.

When run now, our file’s output is similar to before—we’ve mostly just refactored the code to allow for easier changes in the future, not altered its behavior:

Bob Smith 0
Sue Jones 100000
Smith Jones
110000

A few coding details are worth pointing out here. First, notice that sue’s pay is now still an integer after a pay raise—we convert the math result back to an integer by calling the int built-in within the method. Changing the value to either int or float is probably not a significant concern for most purposes (integer and floating-point objects have the same interfaces and can be mixed within expressions), but we may need to address rounding issues in a real system (money probably matters to Persons!).

As we learned in Chapter 5, we might handle this by using the round(N, 2) built-in to round and retain cents, using the decimal type to fix precision, or storing monetary values as full floating-point numbers and displaying them with a %.2f or {0:.2f} formatting string to show cents. For this example, we’ll simply truncate any cents with int. (For another idea, also see the money function in the formats.py module of Chapter 24; you can import this tool to show pay with commas, cents, and dollar signs.)

Second, notice that we’re also printing sue’s last name this time—because the last-name logic has been encapsulated in a method, we get to use it on any instance of the class. As we’ve seen, Python tells a method which instance to process by automatically passing it in to the first argument, usually called self. Specifically:

In the first call, bob.lastName(), bob is the implied subject passed to self.

In the second call, sue.lastName(), sue goes to self instead.

Trace through these calls to see how the instance winds up in self. The net effect is that the method fetches the name of the implied subject each time. The same happens for giveRaise. We could, for example, give bob a raise by calling giveRaise for both instances this way, too; but unfortunately, bob’s zero pay will prevent him from getting a raise as the program is currently coded (something we may want to address in a future 2.0 release of our software).

Finally, notice that the giveRaise method assumes that percent is passed in as a floating-point number between zero and one. That may be too radical an assumption in the real world (a 1000% raise would probably be a bug for most of us!); we’ll let it pass for this prototype, but we might want to test or at least document this in a future iteration of this code. Stay tuned for a rehash of this idea in a later chapter in this book, where we’ll code something called function decorators and explore Python’s assert statement—alternatives that can do the validity test for us automatically during development.

Step 3: Operator Overloading

At this point, we have a fairly full-featured class that generates and initializes instances, along with two new bits of behavior for processing instances (in the form of methods). So far, so good.

As it stands, though, testing is still a bit less convenient than it needs to be—to trace our objects, we have to manually fetch and print individual attributes (e.g., bob.name, sue.pay). It would be nice if displaying an instance all at once actually gave us some useful information. Unfortunately, the default display format for an instance object isn’t very good—it displays the object’s class name, and its address in memory (which is essentially useless in Python, except as a unique identifier).

To see this, change the last line in the script to print(sue) so it displays the object as a whole. Here’s what you’ll get (the output says that sue is an “object” in 3.0 and an “instance” in 2.6):

Bob Smith 0
Sue Jones 100000
Smith Jones
<__main__.Person object at 0x02614430>

Providing Print Displays

Fortunately, it’s easy to do better by employing operator overloading—coding methods in a class that intercept and process built-in operations when run on the class’s instances. Specifically, we can make use of what is probably the second most commonly used operator overloading method in Python, after __init__: the __str__ method introduced in the preceding chapter. __str__ is run automatically every time an instance is converted to its print string. Because that’s what printing an object does, the net transitive effect is that printing an object displays whatever is returned by the object’s __str__ method, if it either defines one itself or inherits one from a superclass (double-underscored names are inherited just like any other).

Technically speaking, the __init__ constructor method we’ve already coded is operator overloading too—it is run automatically at construction time to initialize a newly created instance. Constructors are so common, though, that they almost seem like a special case. More focused methods like __str__ allow us to tap into specific operations and provide specialized behavior when our objects are used in those contexts.

Let’s put this into code. The following extends our class to give a custom display that lists attributes when our class’s instances are displayed as a whole, instead of relying on the less useful default display:

# Add __str__ overload method for printing objects

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay
    def lastName(self):
        return self.name.split()[-1]
    def giveRaise(self, percent):
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent))
    def __str__(self):                                         # Added method
        return '[Person: %s, %s]' % (self.name, self.pay)      # String to print

if __name__ == '__main__':
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob)
    print(sue)
    print(bob.lastName(), sue.lastName())
    sue.giveRaise(.10)
    print(sue)

Notice that we’re doing string % formatting to build the display string in __str__ here; at the bottom, classes use built-in type objects and operations like these to get their work done. Again, everything you’ve already learned about both built-in types and functions applies to class-based code. Classes largely just add an additional layer of structure that packages functions and data together and supports extensions.

We’ve also changed our self-test code to print objects directly, instead of printing individual attributes. When run, the output is more coherent and meaningful now; the “[...]” lines are returned by our new __str__, run automatically by print operations:

[Person: Bob Smith, 0]
[Person: Sue Jones, 100000]
Smith Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]

Here’s a subtle point: as we’ll learn in the next chapter, a related overloading method, __repr__, provides an as-code low-level display of an object when present. Sometimes classes provide both a __str__ for user-friendly displays and a __repr__ with extra details for developers to view. Because printing runs __str__ and the interactive prompt echoes results with __repr__, this can provide both target audiences with an appropriate display. Since we’re not interested in displaying an as-code format, __str__ is sufficient for our class.

Step 4: Customizing Behavior by Subclassing

At this point, our class captures much of the OOP machinery in Python: it makes instances, provides behavior in methods, and even does a bit of operator overloading now to intercept print operations in __str__. It effectively packages our data and logic together into a single, self-contained software component, making it easy to locate code and straightforward to change it in the future. By allowing us to encapsulate behavior, it also allows us to factor that code to avoid redundancy and its associated maintenance headaches.

The only major OOP concept it does not yet capture is customization by inheritance. In some sense, we’re already doing inheritance, because instances inherit methods from their classes. To demonstrate the real power of OOP, though, we need to define a superclass/subclass relationship that allows us to extend our software and replace bits of inherited behavior. That’s the main idea behind OOP, after all; by fostering a coding model based upon customization of work already done, it can dramatically cut development time.

Coding Subclasses

As a next step, then, let’s put OOP’s methodology to use and customize our Person class by extending our software hierarchy. For the purpose of this tutorial, we’ll define a subclass of Person called Manager that replaces the inherited giveRaise method with a more specialized version. Our new class begins as follows:

class Manager(Person):                          # Define a subclass of Person

This code means that we’re defining a new class named Manager, which inherits from and may add customizations to the superclass Person. In plain terms, a Manager is almost like a Person (admittedly, a very long journey for a very small joke...), but Manager has a custom way to give raises.

For the sake of argument, let’s assume that when a Manager gets a raise, it receives the passed-in percentage as usual, but also gets an extra bonus that defaults to 10%. For instance, if a Manager’s raise is specified as 10%, it will really get 20%. (Any relation to Persons living or dead is, of course, strictly coincidental.) Our new method begins as follows; because this redefinition of giveRaise will be closer in the class tree to Manager instances than the original version in Person, it effectively replaces, and thereby customizes, the operation. Recall that according to the inheritance search rules, the lowest version of the name wins:

class Manager(Person):                          # Inherit Person attrs
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):    # Redefine to customize

Augmenting Methods: The Bad Way

Now, there are two ways we might code this Manager customization: a good way and a bad way. Let’s start with the bad way, since it might be a bit easier to understand. The bad way is to cut and paste the code of giveRaise in Person and modify it for Manager, like this:

class Manager(Person):
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent + bonus))   # Bad: cut-and-paste

This works as advertised—when we later call the giveRaise method of a Manager instance, it will run this custom version, which tacks on the extra bonus. So what’s wrong with something that runs correctly?

The problem here is a very general one: any time you copy code with cut and paste, you essentially double your maintenance effort in the future. Think about it: because we copied the original version, if we ever have to change the way raises are given (and we probably will), we’ll have to change the code in two places, not one. Although this is a small and artificial example, it’s also representative of a universal issue—any time you’re tempted to program by copying code this way, you probably want to look for a better approach.

Augmenting Methods: The Good Way

What we really want to do here is somehow augment the original giveRaise, instead of replacing it altogether. The good way to do that in Python is by calling to the original version directly, with augmented arguments, like this:

class Manager(Person):
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        Person.giveRaise(self, percent + bonus)            # Good: augment original

This code leverages the fact that a class method can always be called either through an instance (the usual way, where Python sends the instance to the self argument automatically) or through the class (the less common scheme, where you must pass the instance manually). In more symbolic terms, recall that a normal method call of this form:

instance.method(args...)

is automatically translated by Python into this equivalent form:

class.method(instance, args...)

where the class containing the method to be run is determined by the inheritance search rule applied to the method’s name. You can code either form in your script, but there is a slight asymmetry between the two—you must remember to pass along the instance manually if you call through the class directly. The method always needs a subject instance one way or another, and Python provides it automatically only for calls made through an instance. For calls through the class name, you need to send an instance to self yourself; for code inside a method like giveRaise, self already is the subject of the call, and hence the instance to pass along.

Calling through the class directly effectively subverts inheritance and kicks the call higher up the class tree to run a specific version. In our case, we can use this technique to invoke the default giveRaise in Person, even though it’s been redefined at the Manager level. In some sense, we must call through Person this way, because a self.giveRaise() inside Manager’s giveRaise code would loop—since self already is a Manager, self.giveRaise() would resolve again to Manager.giveRaise, and so on and so forth until available memory is exhausted.

This “good” version may seem like a small difference in code, but it can make a huge difference for future code maintenance—because the giveRaise logic lives in just one place now (Person’s method), we have only one version to change in the future as needs evolve. And really, this form captures our intent more directly anyhow—we want to perform the standard giveRaise operation, but simply tack on an extra bonus. Here’s our entire module file with this step applied:

# Add customization of one behavior in a subclass

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay
    def lastName(self):
        return self.name.split()[-1]
    def giveRaise(self, percent):
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent))
    def __str__(self):
        return '[Person: %s, %s]' % (self.name, self.pay)

class Manager(Person):
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):           # Redefine at this level
        Person.giveRaise(self, percent + bonus)        # Call Person's version

if __name__ == '__main__':
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob)
    print(sue)
    print(bob.lastName(), sue.lastName())
    sue.giveRaise(.10)
    print(sue)
    tom = Manager('Tom Jones', 'mgr', 50000)           # Make a Manager: __init__
    tom.giveRaise(.10)                                 # Runs custom version
    print(tom.lastName())                              # Runs inherited method
    print(tom)                                         # Runs inherited __str__

To test our Manager subclass customization, we’ve also added self-test code that makes a Manager, calls its methods, and prints it. Here’s the new version’s output:

[Person: Bob Smith, 0]
[Person: Sue Jones, 100000]
Smith Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
Jones
[Person: Tom Jones, 60000]

Everything looks good here: bob and sue are as before, and when tom the Manager is given a 10% raise, he really gets 20% (his pay goes from $50K to $60K), because the customized giveRaise in Manager is run for him only. Also notice how printing tom as a whole at the end of the test code displays the nice format defined in Person’s __str__: Manager objects get this, lastName, and the __init__ constructor method’s code “for free” from Person, by inheritance.

Polymorphism in Action

To make this acquisition of inherited behavior even more striking, we can add the following code at the end of our file:

if __name__ == '__main__':
    ...
    print('--All three--')
    for object in (bob, sue, tom):            # Process objects generically
        object.giveRaise(.10)                 # Run this object's giveRaise
        print(object)                         # Run the common __str__

Here’s the resulting output:

[Person: Bob Smith, 0]
[Person: Sue Jones, 100000]
Smith Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
Jones
[Person: Tom Jones, 60000]
--All three--
[Person: Bob Smith, 0]
[Person: Sue Jones, 121000]
[Person: Tom Jones, 72000]

In the added code, object is either a Person or a Manager, and Python runs the appropriate giveRaise automatically—our original version in Person for bob and sue, and our customized version in Manager for tom. Trace the method calls yourself to see how Python selects the right giveRaise method for each object.

This is just Python’s notion of polymorphism, which we met earlier in the book, at work again—what giveRaise does depends on what you do it to. Here, it’s made all the more obvious when it selects from code we’ve written ourselves in classes. The practical effect in this code is that sue gets another 10% but tom gets another 20%, because giveRaise is dispatched based upon the object’s type. As we’ve learned, polymorphism is at the heart of Python’s flexibility. Passing any of our three objects to a function that calls a giveRaise method, for example, would have the same effect: the appropriate version would be run automatically, depending on which type of object was passed.

On the other hand, printing runs the same __str__ for all three objects, because it’s coded just once in Person. Manager both specializes and applies the code we originally wrote in Person. Although this example is small, it’s already leveraging OOP’s talent for code customization and reuse; with classes, this almost seems automatic at times.

Inherit, Customize, and Extend

In fact, classes can be even more flexible than our example implies. In general, classes can inherit, customize, or extend existing code in superclasses. For example, although we’re focused on customization here, we can also add unique methods to Manager that are not present in Person, if Managers require something completely different (Python namesake reference intended). The following snippet illustrates. Here, giveRaise redefines a superclass method to customize it, but someThingElse defines something new to extend:

class Person:
    def lastName(self): ...
    def giveRaise(self): ...
    def __str__(self): ...

class Manager(Person):                        # Inherit
    def giveRaise(self, ...): ...             # Customize
    def someThingElse(self, ...): ...         # Extend

tom = Manager()
tom.lastName()                                # Inherited verbatim
tom.giveRaise()                               # Customized version
tom.someThingElse()                           # Extension here
print(tom)                                    # Inherited overload method

Extra methods like this code’s someThingElse extend the existing software and are available on Manager objects only, not on Persons. For the purposes of this tutorial, however, we’ll limit our scope to customizing some of Person’s behavior by redefining it, not adding to it.

OOP: The Big Idea

As is, our code may be small, but it’s fairly functional. And really, it already illustrates the main point behind OOP in general: in OOP, we program by customizing what has already been done, rather than copying or changing existing code. This isn’t always an obvious win to newcomers at first glance, especially given the extra coding requirements of classes. But overall, the programming style implied by classes can cut development time radically compared to other approaches.

For instance, in our example we could theoretically have implemented a custom giveRaise operation without subclassing, but none of the other options yield code as optimal as ours:

Although we could have simply coded Manager from scratch as new, independent code, we would have had to reimplement all the behaviors in Person that are the same for Managers.

Although we could have simply changed the existing Person class in-place for the requirements of Manager’s giveRaise, doing so would probably break the places where we still need the original Person behavior.

Although we could have simply copied the Person class in its entirety, renamed the copy to Manager, and changed its giveRaise, doing so would introduce code redundancy that would double our work in the future—changes made to Person in the future would not be picked up automatically, but would have to be manually propagated to Manager’s code. As usual, the cut-and-paste approach may seem quick now, but it doubles your work in the future.

The customizable hierarchies we can build with classes provide a much better solution for software that will evolve over time. No other tools in Python support this development mode. Because we can tailor and extend our prior work by coding new subclasses, we can leverage what we’ve already done, rather than starting from scratch each time, breaking what already works, or introducing multiple copies of code that may all have to be updated in the future. When done right, OOP is a powerful programmer’s ally.

Step 5: Customizing Constructors, Too

Our code works as it is, but if you study the current version closely, you may be struck by something a bit odd—it seems pointless to have to provide a mgr job name for Manager objects when we create them: this is already implied by the class itself. It would be better if we could somehow fill in this value automatically when a Manager is made.

The trick we need to improve on this turns out to be the same as the one we employed in the prior section: we want to customize the constructor logic for Managers in such a way as to provide a job name automatically. In terms of code, we want to redefine an __init__ method in Manager that provides the mgr string for us. And like with the giveRaise customization, we also want to run the original __init__ in Person by calling through the class name, so it still initializes our objects’ state information attributes.

The following extension will do the job—we’ve coded the new Manager constructor and changed the call that creates tom to not pass in the mgr job name:

# Add customization of constructor in a subclass

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay
    def lastName(self):
        return self.name.split()[-1]
    def giveRaise(self, percent):
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent))
    def __str__(self):
        return '[Person: %s, %s]' % (self.name, self.pay)

class Manager(Person):
    def __init__(self, name, pay):                     # Redefine constructor
        Person.__init__(self, name, 'mgr', pay)        # Run original with 'mgr'
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        Person.giveRaise(self, percent + bonus)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob)
    print(sue)
    print(bob.lastName(), sue.lastName())
    sue.giveRaise(.10)
    print(sue)
    tom = Manager('Tom Jones', 50000)                   # Job name not needed:
    tom.giveRaise(.10)                                  # Implied/set by class
    print(tom.lastName())
    print(tom)

Again, we’re using the same technique to augment the __init__ constructor here that we used for giveRaise earlier—running the superclass version by calling through the class name directly and passing the self instance along explicitly. Although the constructor has a strange name, the effect is identical. Because we need Person’s construction logic to run too (to initialize instance attributes), we really have to call it this way; otherwise, instances would not have any attributes attached.

Calling superclass constructors from redefinitions this way turns out to be a very common coding pattern in Python. By itself, Python uses inheritance to look for and call only one __init__ method at construction time—the lowest one in the class tree. If you need higher __init__ methods to be run at construction time (and you usually do), you must call them manually through the superclass’s name. The upside to this is that you can be explicit about which argument to pass up to the superclass’s constructor and can choose to not call it at all: not calling the superclass constructor allows you to replace its logic altogether, rather than augmenting it.

The output of this file’s self-test code is the same as before—we haven’t changed what it does, we’ve simply restructured to get rid of some logical redundancy:

[Person: Bob Smith, 0]
[Person: Sue Jones, 100000]
Smith Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
Jones
[Person: Tom Jones, 60000]

OOP Is Simpler Than You May Think

In this complete form, despite their sizes, our classes capture nearly all the important concepts in Python’s OOP machinery:

Instance creation—filling out instance attributes

Behavior methods—encapsulating logic in class methods

Operator overloading—providing behavior for built-in operations like printing

Customizing behavior—redefining methods in subclasses to specialize them

Customizing constructors—adding initialization logic to superclass steps

Most of these concepts are based upon just three simple ideas: the inheritance search for attributes in object trees, the special self argument in methods, and operator overloading’s automatic dispatch to methods.

Along the way, we’ve also made our code easy to change in the future, by harnessing the class’s propensity for factoring code to reduce redundancy. For example, we wrapped up logic in methods and called back to superclass methods from extensions to avoid having multiple copies of the same code. Most of these steps were a natural outgrowth of the structuring power of classes.

By and large, that’s all there is to OOP in Python. Classes certainly can become larger than this, and there are some more advanced class concepts, such as decorators and metaclasses, which we will meet in later chapters. In terms of the basics, though, our classes already do it all. In fact, if you’ve grasped the workings of the classes we’ve written, most OOP Python code should now be within your reach.

Other Ways to Combine Classes

Having said that, I should also tell you that although the basic mechanics of OOP are simple in Python, some of the art in larger programs lies in the way that classes are put together. We’re focusing on inheritance in this tutorial because that’s the mechanism the Python language provides, but programmers sometimes combine classes in other ways, too. For example, a common coding pattern involves nesting objects inside each other to build up composites. We’ll explore this pattern in more detail in Chapter 30, which is really more about design than about Python; as a quick example, though, we could use this composition idea to code our Manager extension by embedding a Person, instead of inheriting from it.

The following alternative does so by using the __getattr__ operator overloading method we will meet in Chapter 29 to intercept undefined attribute fetches and delegate them to the embedded object with the getattr built-in. The giveRaise method here still achieves customization, by changing the argument passed along to the embedded object. In effect, Manager becomes a controller layer that passes calls down to the embedded object, rather than up to superclass methods:

# Embedding-based Manager alternative

class Person:
    ...same...

class Manager:
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.person = Person(name, 'mgr', pay)      # Embed a Person object
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        self.person.giveRaise(percent + bonus)      # Intercept and delegate
    def __getattr__(self, attr):
        return getattr(self.person, attr)           # Delegate all other attrs
    def __str__(self):
        return str(self.person)                     # Must overload again (in 3.0)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    ...same...

In fact, this Manager alternative is representative of a general coding pattern usually known as delegation—a composite-based structure that manages a wrapped object and propagates method calls to it. This pattern works in our example, but it requires about twice as much code and is less well suited than inheritance to the kinds of direct customizations we meant to express (in fact, no reasonable Python programmer would code this example this way in practice, except perhaps those writing general tutorials). Manager isn’t really a Person here, so we need extra code to manually dispatch method calls to the embedded object; operator overloading methods like __str__ must be redefined (in 3.0, at least, as noted in the upcoming sidebar Catching Built-in Attributes in 3.0), and adding new Manager behavior is less straightforward since state information is one level removed.

Still, object embedding, and design patterns based upon it, can be a very good fit when embedded objects require more limited interaction with the container than direct customization implies. A controller layer like this alternative Manager, for example, might come in handy if we want to trace or validate calls to another object’s methods (indeed, we will use a nearly identical coding pattern when we study class decorators later in the book). Moreover, a hypothetical Department class like the following could aggregate other objects in order to treat them as a set. Add this to the bottom of the person.py file to try this on your own:

# Aggregate embedded objects into a composite

...
bob = Person(...)
sue = Person(...)
tom = Manager(...)

class Department:
    def __init__(self, *args):
        self.members = list(args)
    def addMember(self, person):
        self.members.append(person)
    def giveRaises(self, percent):
        for person in self.members:
            person.giveRaise(percent)
    def showAll(self):
        for person in self.members:
            print(person)

development = Department(bob, sue)          # Embed objects in a composite
development.addMember(tom)
development.giveRaises(.10)                 # Runs embedded objects' giveRaise
development.showAll()                       # Runs embedded objects' __str__s

Interestingly, this code uses both inheritance and composition—Department is a composite that embeds and controls other objects to aggregate, but the embedded Person and Manager objects themselves use inheritance to customize. As another example, a GUI might similarly use inheritance to customize the behavior or appearance of labels and buttons, but also composition to build up larger packages of embedded widgets, such as input forms, calculators, and text editors. The class structure to use depends on the objects you are trying to model.

Design issues like composition are explored in Chapter 30, so we’ll postpone further investigations for now. But again, in terms of the basic mechanics of OOP in Python, our Person and Manager classes already tell the entire story. Having mastered the basics of OOP, though, developing general tools for applying it more easily in your scripts is often a natural next step—and the topic of the next section.

Catching Built-in Attributes in 3.0

In Python 3.0 (and 2.6 if new-style classes are used), the alternative delegation-based Manager class we just coded will not be able to intercept and delegate operator overloading method attributes like __str__ without redefining them. Although we know that __str__ is the only such name used in our specific example, this a general issue for delegation-based classes.

Recall that built-in operations like printing and indexing implicitly invoke operator overloading methods such as __str__ and __getitem__. In 3.0, built-in operations like these do not route their implicit attribute fetches through generic attribute managers: neither __getattr__ (run for undefined attributes) nor its cousin __getattribute__ (run for all attributes) is invoked. This is why we have to redefine __str__ redundantly in the alternative Manager, in order to ensure that printing is routed to the embedded Person object when run in Python 3.0.

Technically, this happens because classic classes normally look up operator overloading names in instances at runtime, but new-style classes do not—they skip the instance entirely and look up such methods in classes. In 2.6 classic classes, built-ins do route attributes generically—printing, for example, routes __str__ through __getattr__. New-style classes also inherit a default for __str__ that would foil __getattr__, but __getattribute__ doesn’t intercept the name in 3.0 either.

This is a change, but isn’t a show-stopper—delegation-based classes can generally redefine operator overloading methods to delegate them to wrapped objects in 3.0, either manually or via tools or superclasses. This topic is too advanced to explore further in this tutorial, though, so don’t sweat the details too much here. Watch for it to be revisited in the attribute management coverage of Chapter 37, and again in the context of Private class decorators in Chapter 38.

Step 6: Using Introspection Tools

Let’s make one final tweak before we throw our objects onto a database. As they are, our classes are complete and demonstrate most of the basics of OOP in Python. They still have two remaining issues we probably should iron out, though, before we go live with them:

First, if you look at the display of the objects as they are right now, you’ll notice that when you print tom the Manager labels him as a Person. That’s not technically incorrect, since Manager is a kind of customized and specialized Person. Still, it would be more accurate to display objects with the most specific (that is, lowest) classes possible.

Second, and perhaps more importantly, the current display format shows only the attributes we include in our __str__, and that might not account for future goals. For example, we can’t yet verify that tom’s job name has been set to mgr correctly by Manager’s constructor, because the __str__ we coded for Person does not print this field. Worse, if we ever expand or otherwise change the set of attributes assigned to our objects in __init__, we’ll have to remember to also update __str__ for new names to be displayed, or it will become out of sync over time.

The last point means that, yet again, we’ve made potential extra work for ourselves in the future by introducing redundancy in our code. Because any disparity in __str__ will be reflected in the program’s output, this redundancy may be more obvious than the other forms we addressed earlier; still, avoiding extra work in the future is generally a good thing.

Special Class Attributes

We can address both issues with Python’s introspection tools—special attributes and functions that give us access to some of the internals of objects’ implementations. These tools are somewhat advanced and generally used more by people writing tools for other programmers to use than by programmers developing applications. Even so, a basic knowledge of some of these tools is useful because they allow us to write code that processes classes in generic ways. In our code, for example, there are two hooks that can help us out, both of which were introduced near the end of the preceding chapter:

The built-in instance.__class__ attribute provides a link from an instance to the class from which it was created. Classes in turn have a __name__, just like modules, and a __bases__ sequence that provides access to superclasses. We can use these here to print the name of the class from which an instance is made rather than one we’ve hardcoded.

The built-in object.__dict__ attribute provides a dictionary with one key/value pair for every attribute attached to a namespace object (including modules, classes, and instances). Because it is a dictionary, we can fetch its keys list, index by key, iterate over its keys, and so on, to process all attributes generically. We can use this here to print every attribute in any instance, not just those we hardcode in custom displays.

Here’s what these tools look like in action at Python’s interactive prompt. Notice how we load Person at the interactive prompt with a from statement here—class names live in and are imported from modules, exactly like function names and other variables:

>>> from person import Person
>>> bob = Person('Bob Smith')
>>> print(bob)                                 # Show bob's __str__
[Person: Bob Smith, 0]

>>> bob.__class__                              # Show bob's class and its name
<class 'person.Person'>
>>> bob.__class__.__name__
'Person'

>>> list(bob.__dict__.keys())                  # Attributes are really dict keys
['pay', 'job', 'name']                         # Use list to force list in 3.0

>>> for key in bob.__dict__:
        print(key, '=>', bob.__dict__[key])    # Index manually

pay => 0
job => None
name => Bob Smith

>>> for key in bob.__dict__:
        print(key, '=>', getattr(bob, key))    # obj.attr, but attr is a var

pay => 0
job => None
name => Bob Smith

As noted briefly in the prior chapter, some attributes accessible from an instance might not be stored in the __dict__ dictionary if the instance’s class defines __slots__, an optional and relatively obscure feature of new-style classes (and all classes in Python 3.0) that stores attributes in an array and that we’ll discuss in Chapters 30 and 31. Since slots really belong to classes instead of instances, and since they are very rarely used in any event, we can safely ignore them here and focus on the normal __dict__.

A Generic Display Tool

We can put these interfaces to work in a superclass that displays accurate class names and formats all attributes of an instance of any class. Open a new file in your text editor to code the following—it’s a new, independent module named classtools.py that implements just such a class. Because its __str__ print overload uses generic introspection tools, it will work on any instance, regardless of its attributes set. And because this is a class, it automatically becomes a general formatting tool: thanks to inheritance, it can be mixed into any class that wishes to use its display format. As an added bonus, if we ever want to change how instances are displayed we need only change this class, as every class that inherits its __str__ will automatically pick up the new format when it’s next run:

# File classtools.py (new)
"Assorted class utilities and tools"

class AttrDisplay:
    """
    Provides an inheritable print overload method that displays
    instances with their class names and a name=value pair for
    each attribute stored on the instance itself (but not attrs
    inherited from its classes). Can be mixed into any class,
    and will work on any instance.
    """
    def gatherAttrs(self):
        attrs = []
        for key in sorted(self.__dict__):
            attrs.append('%s=%s' % (key, getattr(self, key)))
        return ', '.join(attrs)
    def __str__(self):
        return '[%s: %s]' % (self.__class__.__name__, self.gatherAttrs())


if __name__ == '__main__':
    class TopTest(AttrDisplay):
        count = 0
        def __init__(self):
            self.attr1 = TopTest.count
            self.attr2 = TopTest.count+1
            TopTest.count += 2

    class SubTest(TopTest):
        pass

    X, Y = TopTest(), SubTest()
    print(X)                         # Show all instance attrs
    print(Y)                         # Show lowest class name

Notice the docstrings here—as a general-purpose tool, we want to add some functional documentation for potential users to read. As we saw in Chapter 15, docstrings can be placed at the top of simple functions and modules, and also at the start of classes and their methods; the help function and the PyDoc tool extracts and displays these automatically (we’ll look at docstrings again in Chapter 28).

When run directly, this module’s self-test makes two instances and prints them; the __str__ defined here shows the instance’s class, and all its attributes names and values, in sorted attribute name order:

C:\misc> classtools.py
[TopTest: attr1=0, attr2=1]
[SubTest: attr1=2, attr2=3]

Instance Versus Class Attributes

If you study the classtools module’s self-test code long enough, you’ll notice that its class displays only instance attributes, attached to the self object at the bottom of the inheritance tree; that’s what self’s __dict__ contains. As an intended consequence, we don’t see attributes inherited by the instance from classes above it in the tree (e.g., count in this file’s self-test code). Inherited class attributes are attached to the class only, not copied down to instances.

If you ever do wish to include inherited attributes too, you can climb the __class__ link to the instance’s class, use the __dict__ there to fetch class attributes, and then iterate through the class’s __bases__ attribute to climb to even higher superclasses (repeating as necessary). If you’re a fan of simple code, running a built-in dir call on the instance instead of using __dict__ and climbing would have much the same effect, since dir results include inherited names in the sorted results list:

>>> from person import Person
>>> bob = Person('Bob Smith')

# In Python 2.6:

>>> bob.__dict__.keys()                 # Instance attrs only
['pay', 'job', 'name']

>>> dir(bob)                            # + inherited attrs in classes
['__doc__', '__init__', '__module__', '__str__', 'giveRaise', 'job',
'lastName', 'name', 'pay']

# In Python 3.0:

>>> list(bob.__dict__.keys())           # 3.0 keys is a view, not a list
['pay', 'job', 'name']

>>> dir(bob)                            # 3.0 includes class type methods
['__class__', '__delattr__', '__dict__', '__doc__', '__eq__', '__format__',
'__ge__', '__getattribute__', '__gt__', '__hash__', '__init__', '__le__',
...more lines omitted...
'__setattr__', '__sizeof__', '__str__', '__subclasshook__', '__weakref__',
'giveRaise', 'job', 'lastName', 'name', 'pay']

The output here varies between Python 2.6 and 3.0, because 3.0’s dict.keys is not a list, and 3.0’s dir returns extra class-type implementation attributes. Technically, dir returns more in 3.0 because classes are all “new style” and inherit a large set of operator overloading names from the class type. In fact, you’ll probably want to filter out most of the __X__ names in the 3.0 dir result, since they are internal implementation details and not something you’d normally want to display.

In the interest of space, we’ll leave optional display of inherited class attributes with either tree climbs or dir as suggested experiments for now. For more hints on this front, though, watch for the classtree.py inheritance tree climber we will write in Chapter 28, and the lister.py attribute listers and climbers we’ll code in Chapter 30.

Name Considerations in Tool Classes

One last subtlety here: because our AttrDisplay class in the classtools module is a general tool designed to be mixed into other arbitrary classes, we have to be aware of the potential for unintended name collisions with client classes. As is, I’ve assumed that client subclasses may want to use both its __str__ and gatherAttrs, but the latter of these may be more than a subclass expects—if a subclass innocently defines a gatherAttrs name of its own, it will likely break our class, because the lower version in the subclass will be used instead of ours.

To see this for yourself, add a gatherAttrs to TopTest in the file’s self-test code; unless the new method is identical, or intentionally customizes the original, our tool class will no longer work as planned:

    class TopTest(AttrDisplay):
        ....
        def gatherAttrs(self):         # Replaces method in AttrDisplay!
            return 'Spam'

This isn’t necessarily bad—sometimes we want other methods to be available to subclasses, either for direct calls or for customization. If we really meant to provide a __str__ only, though, this is less than ideal.

To minimize the chances of name collisions like this, Python programmers often prefix methods not meant for external use with a single underscore: _gatherAttrs in our case. This isn’t foolproof (what if another class defines _gatherAttrs, too?), but it’s usually sufficient, and it’s a common Python naming convention for methods internal to a class.

A better and less commonly used solution would be to use two underscores at the front of the method name only: __gatherAttrs for us. Python automatically expands such names to include the enclosing class’s name, which makes them truly unique. This is a feature usually called pseudoprivate class attributes, which we’ll expand on in Chapter 30. For now, we’ll make both our methods available.

Our Classes’ Final Form

Now, to use this generic tool in our classes, all we need to do is import it from its module, mix it in by inheritance in our top-level class, and get rid of the more specific __str__ we coded before. The new print overload method will be inherited by instances of Person, as well as Manager; Manager gets __str__ from Person, which now obtains it from the AttrDisplay coded in another module. Here is the final version of our person.py file with these changes applied:

# File person.py (final)

from classtools import AttrDisplay                  # Use generic display tool

class Person(AttrDisplay):
    """
    Create and process person records
    """
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay
    def lastName(self):                             # Assumes last is last
        return self.name.split()[-1]
    def giveRaise(self, percent):                   # Percent must be 0..1
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent))

class Manager(Person):
    """
    A customized Person with special requirements
    """
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        Person.__init__(self, name, 'mgr', pay)
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        Person.giveRaise(self, percent + bonus)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    bob = Person('Bob Smith')
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(bob)
    print(sue)
    print(bob.lastName(), sue.lastName())
    sue.giveRaise(.10)
    print(sue)
    tom = Manager('Tom Jones', 50000)
    tom.giveRaise(.10)
    print(tom.lastName())
    print(tom)

As this is the final revision, we’ve added a few comments here to document our work—docstrings for functional descriptions and # for smaller notes, per best-practice conventions. When we run this code now, we see all the attributes of our objects, not just the ones we hardcoded in the original __str__. And our final issue is resolved: because AttrDisplay takes class names off the self instance directly, each object is shown with the name of its closest (lowest) class—tom displays as a Manager now, not a Person, and we can finally verify that his job name has been correctly filled in by the Manager constructor:

C:\misc> person.py
[Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]
[Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=100000]
Smith Jones
[Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=110000]
Jones
[Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=60000]

This is the more useful display we were after. From a larger perspective, though, our attribute display class has become a general tool, which we can mix into any class by inheritance to leverage the display format it defines. Further, all its clients will automatically pick up future changes in our tool. Later in the book, we’ll meet even more powerful class tool concepts, such as decorators and metaclasses; along with Python’s introspection tools, they allow us to write code that augments and manages classes in structured and maintainable ways.

Step 7 (Final): Storing Objects in a Database

At this point, our work is almost complete. We now have a two-module system that not only implements our original design goals for representing people, but also provides a general attribute display tool we can use in other programs in the future. By coding functions and classes in module files, we’ve ensured that they naturally support reuse. And by coding our software as classes, we’ve ensured that it naturally supports extension.

Although our classes work as planned, though, the objects they create are not real database records. That is, if we kill Python, our instances will disappear—they’re transient objects in memory and are not stored in a more permanent medium like a file, so they won’t be available in future program runs. It turns out that it’s easy to make instance objects more permanent, with a Python feature called object persistence—making objects live on after the program that creates them exits. As a final step in this tutorial, let’s make our objects permanent.

Pickles and Shelves

Object persistence is implemented by three standard library modules, available in every Python:

pickle

Serializes arbitrary Python objects to and from a string of bytes

dbm (named anydbm in Python 2.6)

Implements an access-by-key filesystem for storing strings

shelve

Uses the other two modules to store Python objects on a file by key

We met these modules very briefly in Chapter 9 when we studied file basics. They provide powerful data storage options. Although we can’t do them complete justice in this tutorial or book, they are simple enough that a brief introduction is enough to get you started.

The pickle module is a sort of super-general object formatting and deformatting tool: given a nearly arbitrary Python object in memory, it’s clever enough to convert the object to a string of bytes, which it can use later to reconstruct the original object in memory. The pickle module can handle almost any object you can create—lists, dictionaries, nested combinations thereof, and class instances. The latter are especially useful things to pickle, because they provide both data (attributes) and behavior (methods); in fact, the combination is roughly equivalent to “records” and “programs.” Because pickle is so general, it can replace extra code you might otherwise write to create and parse custom text file representations for your objects. By storing an object’s pickle string on a file, you effectively make it permanent and persistent: simply load and unpickle it later to re-create the original object.

Although it’s easy to use pickle by itself to store objects in simple flat files and load them from there later, the shelve module provides an extra layer of structure that allows you to store pickled objects by key. shelve translates an object to its pickled string with pickle and stores that string under a key in a dbm file; when later loading, shelve fetches the pickled string by key and re-creates the original object in memory with pickle. This is all quite a trick, but to your script a shelve[62] of pickled objects looks just like a dictionary—you index by key to fetch, assign to keys to store, and use dictionary tools such as len, in, and dict.keys to get information. Shelves automatically map dictionary operations to objects stored in a file.

In fact, to your script the only coding difference between a shelve and a normal dictionary is that you must open shelves initially and must close them after making changes. The net effect is that a shelve provides a simple database for storing and fetching native Python objects by keys, and thus makes them persistent across program runs. It does not support query tools such as SQL, and it lacks some advanced features found in enterprise-level databases (such as true transaction processing), but native Python objects stored on a shelve may be processed with the full power of the Python language once they are fetched back by key.

Storing Objects on a Shelve Database

Pickling and shelves are somewhat advanced topics, and we won’t go into all their details here; you can read more about them in the standard library manuals, as well as application-focused books such as Programming Python. This is all simpler in Python than in English, though, so let’s jump into some code.

Let’s write a new script that throws objects of our classes onto a shelve. In your text editor, open a new file we’ll call makedb.py. Since this is a new file, we’ll need to import our classes in order to create a few instances to store. We used from to load a class at the interactive prompt earlier, but really, as with functions and other variables, there are two ways to load a class from a file (class names are variables like any other, and not at all magic in this context):

import person                                   # Load class with import
bob = person.Person(...)                        # Go through module name

from person import Person                       # Load class with from
bob = Person(...)                               # Use name directly

We’ll use from to load in our script, just because it’s a bit less to type. Copy or retype this code to make instances of our classes in the new script, so we have something to store (this is a simple demo, so we won’t worry about the test-code redundancy here). Once we have some instances, it’s almost trivial to store them on a shelve. We simply import the shelve module, open a new shelve with an external filename, assign the objects to keys in the shelve, and close the shelve when we’re done because we’ve made changes:

# File makedb.py: store Person objects on a shelve database

from person import Person, Manager              # Load our classes
bob = Person('Bob Smith')                       # Re-create objects to be stored
sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
tom = Manager('Tom Jones', 50000)

import shelve
db = shelve.open('persondb')                    # Filename where objects are stored
for object in (bob, sue, tom):                  # Use object's name attr as key
    db[object.name] = object                    # Store object on shelve by key
db.close()                                      # Close after making changes

Notice how we assign objects to the shelve using their own names as keys. This is just for convenience; in a shelve, the key can be any string, including one we might create to be unique using tools such as process IDs and timestamps (available in the os and time standard library modules). The only rule is that the keys must be strings and should be unique, since we can store just one object per key (though that object can be a list or dictionary containing many objects). The values we store under keys, though, can be Python objects of almost any sort: built-in types like strings, lists, and dictionaries, as well as user-defined class instances, and nested combinations of all of these.

That’s all there is to it—if this script has no output when run, it means it probably worked; we’re not printing anything, just creating and storing objects:

C:\misc> makedb.py

Exploring Shelves Interactively

At this point, there are one or more real files in the current directory whose names all start with “persondb”. The actual files created can vary per platform, and just like in the built-in open function, the filename in shelve.open() is relative to the current working directory unless it includes a directory path. Wherever they are stored, these files implement a keyed-access file that contains the pickled representation of our three Python objects. Don’t delete these files—they are your database, and are what you’ll need to copy or transfer when you back up or move your storage.

You can look at the shelve’s files if you want to, either from Windows Explorer or the Python shell, but they are binary hash files, and most of their content makes little sense outside the context of the shelve module. With Python 3.0 and no extra software installed, our database is stored in three files (in 2.6, it’s just one file, persondb, because the bsddb extension module is preinstalled with Python for shelves; in 3.0, bsddb is a third-party open source add-on):

# Directory listing module: verify files are present

>>> import glob
>>> glob.glob('person*')
['person.py', 'person.pyc', 'persondb.bak', 'persondb.dat', 'persondb.dir']

# Type the file: text mode for string, binary mode for bytes

>>> print(open('persondb.dir').read())
'Tom Jones', (1024, 91)
...more omitted...

>>> print(open('persondb.dat', 'rb').read())
b'\x80\x03cperson\nPerson\nq\x00)\x81q\x01}q\x02(X\x03\x00\x00\x00payq\x03K...
...more omitted...

This content isn’t impossible to decipher, but it can vary on different platforms and doesn’t exactly qualify as a user-friendly database interface! To verify our work better, we can write another script, or poke around our shelve at the interactive prompt. Because shelves are Python objects containing Python objects, we can process them with normal Python syntax and development modes. Here, the interactive prompt effectively becomes a database client:

>>> import shelve
>>> db = shelve.open('persondb')                # Reopen the shelve

>>> len(db)                                     # Three 'records' stored
3
>>> list(db.keys())                             # keys is the index
['Tom Jones', 'Sue Jones', 'Bob Smith']         # list to make a list in 3.0

>>> bob = db['Bob Smith']                       # Fetch bob by key
>>> print(bob)                                  # Runs __str__ from AttrDisplay
[Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]

>>> bob.lastName()                              # Runs lastName from Person
'Smith'

>>> for key in db:                              # Iterate, fetch, print
        print(key, '=>', db[key])

Tom Jones => [Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=50000]
Sue Jones => [Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=100000]
Bob Smith => [Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]

>>> for key in sorted(db):
        print(key, '=>', db[key])               # Iterate by sorted keys

Bob Smith => [Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]
Sue Jones => [Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=100000]
Tom Jones => [Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=50000]

Notice that we don’t have to import our Person or Manager classes here in order to load or use our stored objects. For example, we can call bob’s lastName method freely, and get his custom print display format automatically, even though we don’t have his Person class in our scope here. This works because when Python pickles a class instance, it records its self instance attributes, along with the name of the class it was created from and the module where the class lives. When bob is later fetched from the shelve and unpickled, Python will automatically reimport the class and link bob to it.

The upshot of this scheme is that class instances automatically acquire all their class behavior when they are loaded in the future. We have to import our classes only to make new instances, not to process existing ones. Although a deliberate feature, this scheme has somewhat mixed consequences:

The downside is that classes and their module’s files must be importable when an instance is later loaded. More formally, pickleable classes must be coded at the top level of a module file accessible from a directory listed on the sys.path module search path (and shouldn’t live in the most script files’ module __main__ unless they’re always in that module when used). Because of this external module file requirement, some applications choose to pickle simpler objects such as dictionaries or lists, especially if they are to be transferred across the Internet.

The upside is that changes in a class’s source code file are automatically picked up when instances of the class are loaded again; there is often no need to update stored objects themselves, since updating their class’s code changes their behavior.

Shelves also have well-known limitations (the database suggestions at the end of this chapter mention a few of these). For simple object storage, though, shelves and pickles are remarkably easy-to-use tools.

Updating Objects on a Shelve

Now for one last script: let’s write a program that updates an instance (record) each time it runs, to prove the point that our objects really are persistent (i.e., that their current values are available every time a Python program runs). The following file, updatedb.py, prints the database and gives a raise to one of our stored objects each time. If you trace through what’s going on here, you’ll notice that we’re getting a lot of utility “for free”—printing our objects automatically employs the general __str__ overloading method, and we give raises by calling the giveRaise method we wrote earlier. This all “just works” for objects based on OOP’s inheritance model, even when they live in a file:

# File updatedb.py: update Person object on database

import shelve
db = shelve.open('persondb')               # Reopen shelve with same filename

for key in sorted(db):                     # Iterate to display database objects
    print(key, '\t=>', db[key])            # Prints with custom format

sue = db['Sue Jones']                      # Index by key to fetch
sue.giveRaise(.10)                         # Update in memory using class method
db['Sue Jones'] = sue                      # Assign to key to update in shelve
db.close()                                 # Close after making changes

Because this script prints the database when it starts up, we have to run it a few times to see our objects change. Here it is in action, displaying all records and increasing sue’s pay each time it’s run (it’s a pretty good script for sue...):

c:\misc> updatedb.py
Bob Smith       => [Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]
Sue Jones       => [Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=100000]
Tom Jones       => [Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=50000]

c:\misc> updatedb.py
Bob Smith       => [Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]
Sue Jones       => [Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=110000]
Tom Jones       => [Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=50000]

c:\misc> updatedb.py
Bob Smith       => [Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]
Sue Jones       => [Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=121000]
Tom Jones       => [Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=50000]

c:\misc> updatedb.py
Bob Smith       => [Person: job=None, name=Bob Smith, pay=0]
Sue Jones       => [Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=133100]
Tom Jones       => [Manager: job=mgr, name=Tom Jones, pay=50000]

Again, what we see here is a product of the shelve and pickle tools we get from Python, and of the behavior we coded in our classes ourselves. And once again, we can verify our script’s work at the interactive prompt (the shelve’s equivalent of a database client):

c:\misc> python
>>> import shelve
>>> db = shelve.open('persondb')             # Reopen database
>>> rec = db['Sue Jones']                    # Fetch object by key
>>> print(rec)
[Person: job=dev, name=Sue Jones, pay=146410]
>>> rec.lastName()
'Jones'
>>> rec.pay
146410

For another example of object persistence in this book, see the sidebar in Chapter 30 titled Why You Will Care: Classes and Persistence. It stores a somewhat larger composite object in a flat file with pickle instead of shelve, but the effect is similar. For more details on both pickles and shelves, see other books or Python’s manuals.

Future Directions

And that’s a wrap for this tutorial. At this point, you’ve seen all the basics of Python’s OOP machinery in action, and you’ve learned ways to avoid redundancy and its associated maintenance issues in your code. You’ve built full-featured classes that do real work. As an added bonus, you’ve made them real database records by storing them in a Python shelve, so their information lives on persistently.

There is much more we could explore here, of course. For example, we could extend our classes to make them more realistic, add new kinds of behavior to them, and so on. Giving a raise, for instance, should in practice verify that pay increase rates are between zero and one—an extension we’ll add when we meet decorators later in this book. You might also mutate this example into a personal contacts database, by changing the state information stored on objects, as well as the class methods used to process it. We’ll leave this a suggested exercise open to your imagination.

We could also expand our scope to use tools that either come with Python or are freely available in the open source world:

GUIs

As is, we can only process our database with the interactive prompt’s command-based interface, and scripts. We could also work on expanding our object database’s usability by adding a graphical user interface for browsing and updating its records. GUIs can be built portably with either Python’s tkinter (Tkinter in 2.6) standard library support, or third-party toolkits such as WxPython and PyQt. tkinter ships with Python, lets you build simple GUIs quickly, and is ideal for learning GUI programming techniques; WxPython and PyQt tend to be more complex to use but often produce higher-grade GUIs in the end.

Websites

Although GUIs are convenient and fast, the Web is hard to beat in terms of accessibility. We might also implement a website for browsing and updating records, instead of or in addition to GUIs and the interactive prompt. Websites can be constructed with either basic CGI scripting tools that come with Python, or full-featured third-party web frameworks such as Django, TurboGears, Pylons, web2Py, Zope, or Google’s App Engine. On the Web, your data can still be stored in a shelve, pickle file, or other Python-based medium; the scripts that process it are simply run automatically on a server in response to requests from web browsers and other clients, and they produce HTML to interact with a user, either directly or by interfacing with Framework APIs.

Web services

Although web clients can often parse information in the replies from websites (a technique colorfully known as “screen scraping”), we might go further and provide a more direct way to fetch records on the Web via a web services interface such as SOAP or XML-RPC calls—APIs supported by either Python itself or the third-party open source domain. Such APIs return data in a more direct form, rather than embedded in the HTML of a reply page.

Databases

If our database becomes higher-volume or critical, we might eventually move it from shelves to a more full-featured storage mechanism such as the open source ZODB object-oriented database system (OODB), or a more traditional SQL-based relational database system such as MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, or SQLite. Python itself comes with the in-process SQLite database system built-in, but other open source options are freely available on the Web. ZODB, for example, is similar to Python’s shelve but addresses many of its limitations, supporting larger databases, concurrent updates, transaction processing, and automatic write-through on in-memory changes. SQL-based systems like MySQL offer enterprise-level tools for database storage and may be directly used from a within a Python script.

ORMs

If we do migrate to a relational database system for storage, we don’t have to sacrifice Python’s OOP tools. Object-relational mappers (ORMs) like SQLObject and SQLAlchemy can automatically map relational tables and rows to and from Python classes and instances, such that we can process the stored data using normal Python class syntax. This approach provides an alternative to OODBs like shelve and ZODB and leverages the power of both relational databases and Python’s class model.

While I hope this introduction whets your appetite for future exploration, all of these topics are of course far beyond the scope of this tutorial and this book at large. If you want to explore any of them on your own, see the Web, Python’s standard library manuals, and application-focused books such as Programming Python. In the latter I pick up this example where we’ve stopped here, showing how to add both a GUI and a website on top of the database to allow for browsing and updating instance records. I hope to see you there eventually, but first, let’s return to class fundamentals and finish up the rest of the core Python language story.

Chapter Summary

In this chapter, we explored all the fundamentals of Python classes and OOP in action, by building upon a simple but real example, step by step. We added constructors, methods, operator overloading, customization with subclasses, and introspection tools, and we met other concepts (such as composition, delegation, and polymorphism) along the way.

In the end, we took objects created by our classes and made them persistent by storing them on a shelve object database—an easy-to-use system for saving and retrieving native Python objects by key. While exploring class basics, we also encountered multiple ways to factor our code to reduce redundancy and minimize future maintenance costs. Finally, we briefly previewed ways to extend our code with application-programming tools such as GUIs and databases, covered in follow-up books.

In the next chapters of this part of the book we’ll return to our study of the details behind Python’s class model and investigate its application to some of the design concepts used to combine classes in larger programs. Before we move ahead, though, let’s work through this chapter’s quiz to review what we covered here. Since we’ve already done a lot of hands-on work in this chapter, we’ll close with a set of mostly theory-oriented questions designed to make you trace through some of the code and ponder some of the bigger ideas behind it.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

In the final version of our classes, Manager ultimately inherits its __str__ printing method from AttrDisplay in the separate classtools module. Manager doesn’t have one itself, so the inheritance search climbs to its Person superclass; because there is no __str__ there either, the search climbs higher and finds it in AttrDisplay. The class names listed in parentheses in a class statement’s header line provide the links to higher superclasses.

Shelves (really, the pickle module they use) automatically relink an instance to the class it was created from when that instance is later loaded back into memory. Python reimports the class from its module internally, creates an instance with its stored attributes, and sets the instance’s __class__ link to point to its original class. This way, loaded instances automatically obtain all their original methods (like lastName, giveRaise, and __str__), even if we have not imported the instance’s class into our scope.

It’s important to move processing into methods so that there is only one copy to change in the future, and so that the methods can be run on any instance. This is Python’s notion of encapsulation—wrapping up logic behind interfaces, to better support future code maintenance. If you don’t do so, you create code redundancy that can multiply your work effort as the code evolves in the future.

Customizing with subclasses reduces development effort. In OOP, we code by customizing what has already been done, rather than copying or changing existing code. This is the real “big idea” in OOP—because we can easily extend our prior work by coding new subclasses, we can leverage what we’ve already done. This is much better than either starting from scratch each time, or introducing multiple redundant copies of code that may all have to be updated in the future.

Copying and modifying code doubles your potential work effort in the future, regardless of the context. If a subclass needs to perform default actions coded in a superclass method, it’s much better to call back to the original through the superclass’s name than to copy its code. This also holds true for superclass constructors. Again, copying code creates redundancy, which is a major issue as code evolves.

Generic tools can avoid hardcoded solutions that must be kept in sync with the rest of the class as it evolves over time. A generic __str__ print method, for example, need not be updated each time a new attribute is added to instances in an __init__ constructor. In addition, a generic print method inherited by all classes only appears, and need only be modified, in one place—changes in the generic version are picked up by all classes that inherit from the generic class. Again, eliminating code redundancy cuts future development effort; that’s one of the primary assets classes bring to the table.

Inheritance is best at coding extensions based on direct customization (like our Manager specialization of Person). Composition is well suited to scenarios where multiple objects are aggregated into a whole and directed by a controller layer class. Inheritance passes calls up to reuse, and composition passes down to delegate. Inheritance and composition are not mutually exclusive; often, the objects embedded in a controller are themselves customizations based upon inheritance.

The classes in this chapter could be used as boilerplate “template” code to implement a variety of types of databases. Essentially, you can repurpose them by modifying the constructors to record different attributes and providing whatever methods are appropriate for the target application. For instance, you might use attributes such as name, address, birthday, phone, email, and so on for a contacts database, and methods appropriate for this purpose. A method named sendmail, for example, might use Python’s standard library smtplib module to send an email to one of the contacts automatically when called (see Python’s manuals or application-level books for more details on such tools). The AttrDisplay tool we wrote here could be used verbatim to print your objects, because it is intentionally generic. Most of the shelve database code here can be used to store your objects, too, with minor changes.

[62] Yes, we use “shelve” as a noun in Python, much to the chagrin of a variety of editors I’ve worked with over the years, both electronic and human.

The class Statement

Although the Python class statement may seem similar to tools in other OOP languages on the surface, on closer inspection, it is quite different from what some programmers are used to. For example, as in C++, the class statement is Python’s main OOP tool, but unlike in C++, Python’s class is not a declaration. Like a def, a class statement is an object builder, and an implicit assignment—when run, it generates a class object and stores a reference to it in the name used in the header. Also like a def, a class statement is true executable code—your class doesn’t exist until Python reaches and runs the class statement that defines it (typically while importing the module it is coded in, but not before).

General Form

class is a compound statement, with a body of indented statements typically appearing under the header. In the header, superclasses are listed in parentheses after the class name, separated by commas. Listing more than one superclass leads to multiple inheritance (which we’ll discuss more formally in Chapter 30). Here is the statement’s general form:

class <name>(superclass,...):         # Assign to name
    data = value                      # Shared class data
    def method(self,...):             # Methods
        self.member = value           # Per-instance data

Within the class statement, any assignments generate class attributes, and specially named methods overload operators; for instance, a function called __init__ is called at instance object construction time, if defined.

Example

As we’ve seen, classes are mostly just namespaces—that is, tools for defining names (i.e., attributes) that export data and logic to clients. So, how do you get from the class statement to a namespace?

Here’s how. Just like in a module file, the statements nested in a class statement body create its attributes. When Python executes a class statement (not a call to a class), it runs all the statements in its body, from top to bottom. Assignments that happen during this process create names in the class’s local scope, which become attributes in the associated class object. Because of this, classes resemble both modules and functions:

Like functions, class statements are local scopes where names created by nested assignments live.

Like names in a module, names assigned in a class statement become attributes in a class object.

The main distinction for classes is that their namespaces are also the basis of inheritance in Python; reference attributes that are not found in a class or instance object are fetched from other classes.

Because class is a compound statement, any sort of statement can be nested inside its body—print, =, if, def, and so on. All the statements inside the class statement run when the class statement itself runs (not when the class is later called to make an instance). Assigning names inside the class statement makes class attributes, and nested defs make class methods, but other assignments make attributes, too.

For example, assignments of simple nonfunction objects to class attributes produce data attributes, shared by all instances:

>>> class SharedData:
...     spam = 42          # Generates a class data attribute
...
>>> x = SharedData()       # Make two instances
>>> y = SharedData()
>>> x.spam, y.spam         # They inherit and share 'spam'
(42, 42)

Here, because the name spam is assigned at the top level of a class statement, it is attached to the class and so will be shared by all instances. We can change it by going through the class name, and we can refer to it through either instances or the class.[63]

>>> SharedData.spam = 99
>>> x.spam, y.spam, SharedData.spam
(99, 99, 99)

Such class attributes can be used to manage information that spans all the instances—a counter of the number of instances generated, for example (we’ll expand on this idea by example in Chapter 31). Now, watch what happens if we assign the name spam through an instance instead of the class:

>>> x.spam = 88
>>> x.spam, y.spam, SharedData.spam
(88, 99, 99)

Assignments to instance attributes create or change the names in the instance, rather than in the shared class. More generally, inheritance searches occur only on attribute references, not on assignment: assigning to an object’s attribute always changes that object, and no other.[64] For example, y.spam is looked up in the class by inheritance, but the assignment to x.spam attaches a name to x itself.

Here’s a more comprehensive example of this behavior that stores the same name in two places. Suppose we run the following class:

class MixedNames:                            # Define class
    data = 'spam'                            # Assign class attr
    def __init__(self, value):               # Assign method name
        self.data = value                    # Assign instance attr
    def display(self):
        print(self.data, MixedNames.data)    # Instance attr, class attr

This class contains two defs, which bind class attributes to method functions. It also contains an = assignment statement; because this assignment assigns the name data inside the class, it lives in the class’s local scope and becomes an attribute of the class object. Like all class attributes, this data is inherited and shared by all instances of the class that don’t have data attributes of their own.

When we make instances of this class, the name data is attached to those instances by the assignment to self.data in the constructor method:

>>> x = MixedNames(1)          # Make two instance objects
>>> y = MixedNames(2)          # Each has its own data
>>> x.display(); y.display()   # self.data differs, MixedNames.data is the same
1 spam
2 spam

The net result is that data lives in two places: in the instance objects (created by the self.data assignment in __init__), and in the class from which they inherit names (created by the data assignment in the class). The class’s display method prints both versions, by first qualifying the self instance, and then the class.

By using these techniques to store attributes in different objects, we determine their scope of visibility. When attached to classes, names are shared; in instances, names record per-instance data, not shared behavior or data. Although inheritance searches look up names for us, we can always get to an attribute anywhere in a tree by accessing the desired object directly.

In the preceding example, for instance, specifying x.data or self.data will return an instance name, which normally hides the same name in the class; however, MixedNames.data grabs the class name explicitly. We’ll see various roles for such coding patterns later; the next section describes one of the most common.

Methods

Because you already know about functions, you also know about methods in classes. Methods are just function objects created by def statements nested in a class statement’s body. From an abstract perspective, methods provide behavior for instance objects to inherit. From a programming perspective, methods work in exactly the same way as simple functions, with one crucial exception: a method’s first argument always receives the instance object that is the implied subject of the method call.

In other words, Python automatically maps instance method calls to class method functions as follows. Method calls made through an instance, like this:

instance.method(args...)

are automatically translated to class method function calls of this form:

class.method(instance, args...)

where the class is determined by locating the method name using Python’s inheritance search procedure. In fact, both call forms are valid in Python.

Besides the normal inheritance of method attribute names, the special first argument is the only real magic behind method calls. In a class method, the first argument is usually called self by convention (technically, only its position is significant, not its name). This argument provides methods with a hook back to the instance that is the subject of the call—because classes generate many instance objects, they need to use this argument to manage data that varies per instance.

C++ programmers may recognize Python’s self argument as being similar to C++’s this pointer. In Python, though, self is always explicit in your code: methods must always go through self to fetch or change attributes of the instance being processed by the current method call. This explicit nature of self is by design—the presence of this name makes it obvious that you are using instance attribute names in your script, not names in the local or global scope.

Method Example

To clarify these concepts, let’s turn to an example. Suppose we define the following class:

class NextClass:                            # Define class
    def printer(self, text):                # Define method
        self.message = text                 # Change instance
        print(self.message)                 # Access instance

The name printer references a function object; because it’s assigned in the class statement’s scope, it becomes a class object attribute and is inherited by every instance made from the class. Normally, because methods like printer are designed to process instances, we call them through instances:

>>> x = NextClass()                         # Make instance

>>> x.printer('instance call')              # Call its method
instance call

>>> x.message                               # Instance changed
'instance call'

When we call the method by qualifying an instance like this, printer is first located by inheritance, and then its self argument is automatically assigned the instance object (x); the text argument gets the string passed at the call ('instance call'). Notice that because Python automatically passes the first argument to self for us, we only actually have to pass in one argument. Inside printer, the name self is used to access or set per-instance data because it refers back to the instance currently being processed.

Methods may be called in one of two ways—through an instance, or through the class itself. For example, we can also call printer by going through the class name, provided we pass an instance to the self argument explicitly:

>>> NextClass.printer(x, 'class call')      # Direct class call
class call

>>> x.message                               # Instance changed again
'class call'

Calls routed through the instance and the class have the exact same effect, as long as we pass the same instance object ourselves in the class form. By default, in fact, you get an error message if you try to call a method without any instance:

>>> NextClass.printer('bad call')
TypeError: unbound method printer() must be called with NextClass instance...

Calling Superclass Constructors

Methods are normally called through instances. Calls to methods through a class, though, do show up in a variety of special roles. One common scenario involves the constructor method. The __init__ method, like all attributes, is looked up by inheritance. This means that at construction time, Python locates and calls just one __init__. If subclass constructors need to guarantee that superclass construction-time logic runs, too, they generally must call the superclass’s __init__ method explicitly through the class:

class Super:
    def __init__(self, x):
        ...default code...

class Sub(Super):
    def __init__(self, x, y):
        Super.__init__(self, x)             # Run superclass __init__
        ...custom code...                   # Do my init actions

I = Sub(1, 2)

This is one of the few contexts in which your code is likely to call an operator overloading method directly. Naturally, you should only call the superclass constructor this way if you really want it to run—without the call, the subclass replaces it completely. For a more realistic illustration of this technique in action, see the Manager class example in the prior chapter’s tutorial.[65]

Other Method Call Possibilities

This pattern of calling methods through a class is the general basis of extending (instead of completely replacing) inherited method behavior. In Chapter 31, we’ll also meet a new option added in Python 2.2, static methods, that allow you to code methods that do not expect instance objects in their first arguments. Such methods can act like simple instanceless functions, with names that are local to the classes in which they are coded, and may be used to manage class data. A related concept, the class method, receives a class when called instead of an instance and can be used to manage per-class data. These are advanced and optional extensions, though; normally, you must always pass an instance to a method, whether it is called through an instance or a class.

Namespaces: The Whole Story

Now that we’ve examined class and instance objects, the Python namespace story is complete. For reference, I’ll quickly summarize all the rules used to resolve names here. The first things you need to remember are that qualified and unqualified names are treated differently, and that some scopes serve to initialize object namespaces:

Unqualified names (e.g., X) deal with scopes.

Qualified attribute names (e.g., object.X) use object namespaces.

Some scopes initialize object namespaces (for modules and classes).

Simple Names: Global Unless Assigned

Unqualified simple names follow the LEGB lexical scoping rule outlined for functions in Chapter 17:

Assignment (X = value)

Makes names local: creates or changes the name X in the current local scope, unless declared global.

Reference (X)

Looks for the name X in the current local scope, then any and all enclosing functions, then the current global scope, then the built-in scope.

Attribute Names: Object Namespaces

Qualified attribute names refer to attributes of specific objects and obey the rules for modules and classes. For class and instance objects, the reference rules are augmented to include the inheritance search procedure:

Assignment (object.X = value)

Creates or alters the attribute name X in the namespace of the object being qualified, and none other. Inheritance-tree climbing happens only on attribute reference, not on attribute assignment.

Reference (object.X)

For class-based objects, searches for the attribute name X in object, then in all accessible classes above it, using the inheritance search procedure. For nonclass objects such as modules, fetches X from object directly.

The “Zen” of Python Namespaces: Assignments Classify Names

With distinct search procedures for qualified and unqualified names, and multiple lookup layers for both, it can sometimes be difficult to tell where a name will wind up going. In Python, the place where you assign a name is crucial—it fully determines the scope or object in which a name will reside. The file manynames.py illustrates how this principle translates to code and summarizes the namespace ideas we have seen throughout this book:

# manynames.py

X = 11                       # Global (module) name/attribute (X, or manynames.X)

def f():
    print(X)                 # Access global X (11)

def g():
    X = 22                   # Local (function) variable (X, hides module X)
    print(X)

class C:
    X = 33                   # Class attribute (C.X)
    def m(self):
        X = 44               # Local variable in method (X)
        self.X = 55          # Instance attribute (instance.X)

This file assigns the same name, X, five times. Because this name is assigned in five different locations, though, all five Xs in this program are completely different variables. From top to bottom, the assignments to X here generate: a module attribute (11), a local variable in a function (22), a class attribute (33), a local variable in a method (44), and an instance attribute (55). Although all five are named X, the fact that they are all assigned at different places in the source code or to different objects makes all of these unique variables.

You should take the time to study this example carefully because it collects ideas we’ve been exploring throughout the last few parts of this book. When it makes sense to you, you will have achieved a sort of Python namespace nirvana. Of course, an alternative route to nirvana is to simply run the program and see what happens. Here’s the remainder of this source file, which makes an instance and prints all the Xs that it can fetch:

# manynames.py, continued

if __name__ == '__main__':
    print(X)                 # 11: module (a.k.a. manynames.X outside file)
    f()                      # 11: global
    g()                      # 22: local
    print(X)                 # 11: module name unchanged

    obj = C()                # Make instance
    print(obj.X)             # 33: class name inherited by instance

    obj.m()                  # Attach attribute name X to instance now
    print(obj.X)             # 55: instance
    print(C.X)               # 33: class (a.k.a. obj.X if no X in instance)

    #print(C.m.X)            # FAILS: only visible in method
    #print(g.X)              # FAILS: only visible in function

The outputs that are printed when the file is run are noted in the comments in the code; trace through them to see which variable named X is being accessed each time. Notice in particular that we can go through the class to fetch its attribute (C.X), but we can never fetch local variables in functions or methods from outside their def statements. Locals are visible only to other code within the def, and in fact only live in memory while a call to the function or method is executing.

Some of the names defined by this file are visible outside the file to other modules, but recall that we must always import before we can access names in another file—that is the main point of modules, after all:

# otherfile.py

import manynames

X = 66
print(X)                     # 66: the global here
print(manynames.X)           # 11: globals become attributes after imports

manynames.f()                # 11: manynames's X, not the one here!
manynames.g()                # 22: local in other file's function

print(manynames.C.X)         # 33: attribute of class in other module
I = manynames.C()
print(I.X)                   # 33: still from class here
I.m()
print(I.X)                   # 55: now from instance!

Notice here how manynames.f() prints the X in manynames, not the X assigned in this file—scopes are always determined by the position of assignments in your source code (i.e., lexically) and are never influenced by what imports what or who imports whom. Also, notice that the instance’s own X is not created until we call I.m()—attributes, like all variables, spring into existence when assigned, and not before. Normally we create instance attributes by assigning them in class __init__ constructor methods, but this isn’t the only option.

Finally, as we learned in Chapter 17, it’s also possible for a function to change names outside itself, with global and (in Python 3.0) nonlocal statements—these statements provide write access, but also modify assignment’s namespace binding rules:

X = 11                       # Global in module

def g1():
    print(X)                 # Reference global in module

def g2():
    global X
    X = 22                   # Change global in module

def h1():
    X = 33                   # Local in function
    def nested():
        print(X)             # Reference local in enclosing scope

def h2():
    X = 33                   # Local in function
    def nested():
        nonlocal X           # Python 3.0 statement
        X = 44               # Change local in enclosing scope

Of course, you generally shouldn’t use the same name for every variable in your script—but as this example demonstrates, even if you do, Python’s namespaces will work to keep names used in one context from accidentally clashing with those used in another.

Namespace Dictionaries

In Chapter 22, we learned that module namespaces are actually implemented as dictionaries and exposed with the built-in __dict__ attribute. The same holds for class and instance objects: attribute qualification is really a dictionary indexing operation internally, and attribute inheritance is just a matter of searching linked dictionaries. In fact, instance and class objects are mostly just dictionaries with links inside Python. Python exposes these dictionaries, as well as the links between them, for use in advanced roles (e.g., for coding tools).

To help you understand how attributes work internally, let’s work through an interactive session that traces the way namespace dictionaries grow when classes are involved. We saw a simpler version of this type of code in Chapter 26, but now that we know more about methods and superclasses, let’s embellish it here. First, let’s define a superclass and a subclass with methods that will store data in their instances:

>>> class super:
...     def hello(self):
...         self.data1 = 'spam'
...
>>> class sub(super):
...     def hola(self):
...         self.data2 = 'eggs'
...

When we make an instance of the subclass, the instance starts out with an empty namespace dictionary, but it has links back to the class for the inheritance search to follow. In fact, the inheritance tree is explicitly available in special attributes, which you can inspect. Instances have a __class__ attribute that links to their class, and classes have a __bases__ attribute that is a tuple containing links to higher superclasses (I’m running this on Python 3.0; name formats and some internal attributes vary slightly in 2.6):

>>> X = sub()
>>> X.__dict__                            # Instance namespace dict
{}

>>> X.__class__                           # Class of instance
<class '__main__.sub'>

>>> sub.__bases__                         # Superclasses of class
(<class '__main__.super'>,)

>>> super.__bases__                       # () empty tuple in Python 2.6
(<class 'object'>,)

As classes assign to self attributes, they populate the instance objects—that is, attributes wind up in the instances’ attribute namespace dictionaries, not in the classes’. An instance object’s namespace records data that can vary from instance to instance, and self is a hook into that namespace:

>>> Y = sub()

>>> X.hello()
>>> X.__dict__
{'data1': 'spam'}

>>> X.hola()
>>> X.__dict__
{'data1': 'spam', 'data2': 'eggs'}

>>> sub.__dict__.keys()
['__module__', '__doc__', 'hola']

>>> super.__dict__.keys()
['__dict__', '__module__', '__weakref__', 'hello', '__doc__']

>>> Y.__dict__
{}

Notice the extra underscore names in the class dictionaries; Python sets these automatically. Most are not used in typical programs, but there are tools that use some of them (e.g., __doc__ holds the docstrings discussed in Chapter 15).

Also, observe that Y, a second instance made at the start of this series, still has an empty namespace dictionary at the end, even though X’s dictionary has been populated by assignments in methods. Again, each instance has an independent namespace dictionary, which starts out empty and can record completely different attributes than those recorded by the namespace dictionaries of other instances of the same class.

Because attributes are actually dictionary keys inside Python, there are really two ways to fetch and assign their values—by qualification, or by key indexing:

>>> X.data1, X.__dict__['data1']
('spam', 'spam')

>>> X.data3 = 'toast'
>>> X.__dict__
{'data1': 'spam', 'data3': 'toast', 'data2': 'eggs'}

>>> X.__dict__['data3'] = 'ham'
>>> X.data3
'ham'

This equivalence applies only to attributes actually attached to the instance, though. Because attribute fetch qualification also performs an inheritance search, it can access attributes that namespace dictionary indexing cannot. The inherited attribute X.hello, for instance, cannot be accessed by X.__dict__['hello'].

Finally, here is the built-in dir function we met in Chapters 4 and 15 at work on class and instance objects. This function works on anything with attributes: dir(object) is similar to an object.__dict__.keys() call. Notice, though, that dir sorts its list and includes some system attributes. As of Python 2.2, dir also collects inherited attributes automatically, and in 3.0 it includes names inherited from the object class that is an implied superclass of all classes:[67]

>>> X.__dict__, Y.__dict__
({'data1': 'spam', 'data3': 'ham', 'data2': 'eggs'}, {})
>>> list(X.__dict__.keys())                                  # Need list in 3.0
['data1', 'data3', 'data2']

# In Python 2.6:

>>>> dir(X)
['__doc__', '__module__', 'data1', 'data2', 'data3', 'hello', 'hola']
>>> dir(sub)
['__doc__', '__module__', 'hello', 'hola']
>>> dir(super)
['__doc__', '__module__', 'hello']

# In Python 3.0:

>>> dir(X)
['__class__', '__delattr__', '__dict__', '__doc__', '__eq__', '__format__',
...more omitted...
'data1', 'data2', 'data3', 'hello', 'hola']

>>> dir(sub)
['__class__', '__delattr__', '__dict__', '__doc__', '__eq__', '__format__',
...more omitted...
'hello', 'hola']

>>> dir(super)
['__class__', '__delattr__', '__dict__', '__doc__', '__eq__', '__format__',
...more omitted...
'hello'
]

Experiment with these special attributes on your own to get a better feel for how namespaces actually do their attribute business. Even if you will never use these in the kinds of programs you write, seeing that they are just normal dictionaries will help demystify the notion of namespaces in general.

Namespace Links

The prior section introduced the special __class__ and __bases__ instance and class attributes, without really explaining why you might care about them. In short, these attributes allow you to inspect inheritance hierarchies within your own code. For example, they can be used to display a class tree, as in the following example:

# classtree.py

"""
Climb inheritance trees using namespace links,
displaying higher superclasses with indentation
"""

def classtree(cls, indent):
    print('.' * indent + cls.__name__)    # Print class name here
    for supercls in cls.__bases__:        # Recur to all superclasses
        classtree(supercls, indent+3)     # May visit super > once

def instancetree(inst):
    print('Tree of %s' % inst)            # Show instance
    classtree(inst.__class__, 3)          # Climb to its class

def selftest():
    class A:      pass
    class B(A):   pass
    class C(A):   pass
    class D(B,C): pass
    class E:      pass
    class F(D,E): pass
    instancetree(B())
    instancetree(F())

if __name__ == '__main__': selftest()

The classtree function in this script is recursive—it prints a class’s name using __name__, then climbs up to the superclasses by calling itself. This allows the function to traverse arbitrarily shaped class trees; the recursion climbs to the top, and stops at root superclasses that have empty __bases__ attributes. When using recursion, each active level of a function gets its own copy of the local scope; here, this means that cls and indent are different at each classtree level.

Most of this file is self-test code. When run standalone in Python 3.0, it builds an empty class tree, makes two instances from it, and prints their class tree structures:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python classtree.py
Tree of <__main__.B instance at 0x02557328>
...B
......A
Tree of <__main__.F instance at 0x02557328>
...F
......D
.........B
............A
.........C
............A
......E

When run under Python 3.0, the tree includes the implied object superclasses that are automatically added above standalone classes, because all classes are “new style” in 3.0 (more on this change in Chapter 31):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python classtree.py
Tree of <__main__.B object at 0x02810650>
...B
......A
.........object
Tree of <__main__.F object at 0x02810650>
...F
......D
.........B
............A
...............object
.........C
............A
...............object
......E
.........object

Here, indentation marked by periods is used to denote class tree height. Of course, we could improve on this output format, and perhaps even sketch it in a GUI display. Even as is, though, we can import these functions anywhere we want a quick class tree display:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> class Emp: pass
...
>>> class Person(Emp): pass
>>> bob = Person()

>>> import classtree
>>> classtree.instancetree(bob)
Tree of <__main__.Person object at 0x028203B0>
...Person
......Emp
.........object

Regardless of whether you will ever code or use such tools, this example demonstrates one of the many ways that you can make use of special attributes that expose interpreter internals. You’ll see another when we code the lister.py general-purpose class display tools in the section Multiple Inheritance: “Mix-in” Classes—there, we will extend this technique to also display attributes in each object in a class tree. And in the last part of this book, we’ll revisit such tools in the context of Python tool building at large, to code tools that implement attribute privacy, argument validation, and more. While not for every Python programmer, access to internals enables powerful development tools.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

An abstract superclass is a class that calls a method, but does not inherit or define it—it expects the method to be filled in by a subclass. This is often used as a way to generalize classes when behavior cannot be predicted until a more specific subclass is coded. OOP frameworks also use this as a way to dispatch to client-defined, customizable operations.

When a simple assignment statement (X = Y) appears at the top level of a class statement, it attaches a data attribute to the class (Class.X). Like all class attributes, this will be shared by all instances; data attributes are not callable method functions, though.

A class must manually call the __init__ method in a superclass if it defines an __init__ constructor of its own and still wants the superclass’s construction code to run. Python itself automatically runs just one constructor—the lowest one in the tree. Superclass constructors are called through the class name, passing in the self instance manually: Superclass.__init__(self, ...).

To augment instead of completely replacing an inherited method, redefine it in a subclass, but call back to the superclass’s version of the method manually from the new version of the method in the subclass. That is, pass the self instance to the superclass’s version of the method manually: Superclass.method(self, ...).

Ashur (or Qalat Sherqat), Calah (or Nimrud), the short-lived Dur Sharrukin (or Khorsabad), and finally Nineveh.

[63] If you’ve used C++ you may recognize this as similar to the notion of C++’s “static” data members—members that are stored in the class, independent of instances. In Python, it’s nothing special: all class attributes are just names assigned in the class statement, whether they happen to reference functions (C++’s “methods”) or something else (C++’s “members”). In Chapter 31, we’ll also meet Python static methods (akin to those in C++), which are just self-less functions that usually process class attributes.

[64] Unless the class has redefined the attribute assignment operation to do something unique with the __setattr__ operator overloading method (discussed in Chapter 29).

[65] On a somewhat related note, you can also code multiple __init__ methods within the same class, but only the last definition will be used; see Chapter 30 for more details on multiple method definitions.

[66] This description isn’t 100% complete, because we can also create instance and class attributes by assigning to objects outside class statements—but that’s a much less common and sometimes more error-prone approach (changes aren’t isolated to class statements). In Python, all attributes are always accessible by default. We’ll talk more about attribute name privacy in Chapter 29 when we study __setattr__, in Chapter 30 when we meet __X names, and again in Chapter 38, where we’ll implement it with a class decorator.

[67] As you can see, the contents of attribute dictionaries and dir call results may change over time. For example, because Python now allows built-in types to be subclassed like classes, the contents of dir results for built-in types have expanded to include operator overloading methods, just like our dir results here for user-defined classes under Python 3.0. In general, attribute names with leading and trailing double underscores are interpreter-specific. Type subclasses will be discussed further in Chapter 31.

Iterator Objects: __iter__ and __next__

Although the __getitem__ technique of the prior section works, it’s really just a fallback for iteration. Today, all iteration contexts in Python will try the __iter__ method first, before trying __getitem__. That is, they prefer the iteration protocol we learned about in Chapter 14 to repeatedly indexing an object; only if the object does not support the iteration protocol is indexing attempted instead. Generally speaking, you should prefer __iter__ too—it supports general iteration contexts better than __getitem__ can.

Technically, iteration contexts work by calling the iter built-in function to try to find an __iter__ method, which is expected to return an iterator object. If it’s provided, Python then repeatedly calls this iterator object’s __next__ method to produce items until a StopIteration exception is raised. If no such __iter__ method is found, Python falls back on the __getitem__ scheme and repeatedly indexes by offsets as before, until an IndexError exception is raised. A next built-in function is also available as a convenience for manual iterations: next(I) is the same as I.__next__().

Note

Version skew note: As described in Chapter 14, if you are using Python 2.6, the I.__next__() method just described is named I.next() in your Python, and the next(I) built-in is present for portability: it calls I.next() in 2.6 and I.__next__() in 3.0. Iteration works the same in 2.6 in all other respects.

User-Defined Iterators

In the __iter__ scheme, classes implement user-defined iterators by simply implementing the iteration protocol introduced in Chapters 14 and 20 (refer back to those chapters for more background details on iterators). For example, the following file, iters.py, defines a user-defined iterator class that generates squares:

class Squares:
    def __init__(self, start, stop):    # Save state when created
        self.value = start - 1
        self.stop  = stop
    def __iter__(self):                 # Get iterator object on iter
        return self
    def __next__(self):                 # Return a square on each iteration
        if self.value == self.stop:     # Also called by next built-in
            raise StopIteration
        self.value += 1
        return self.value ** 2

% python
>>> from iters import Squares
>>> for i in Squares(1, 5):             # for calls iter, which calls __iter__
...     print(i, end=' ')               # Each iteration calls __next__
...
1 4 9 16 25

Here, the iterator object is simply the instance self, because the __next__ method is part of this class. In more complex scenarios, the iterator object may be defined as a separate class and object with its own state information to support multiple active iterations over the same data (we’ll see an example of this in a moment). The end of the iteration is signaled with a Python raise statement (more on raising exceptions in the next part of this book). Manual iterations work as for built-in types as well:

>>> X = Squares(1, 5)                   # Iterate manually: what loops do
>>> I = iter(X)                         # iter calls __iter__
>>> next(I)                             # next calls __next__
1
>>> next(I)
4
...more omitted...
>>> next(I)
25
>>> next(I)                             # Can catch this in try statement
StopIteration

An equivalent coding of this iterator with __getitem__ might be less natural, because the for would then iterate through all offsets zero and higher; the offsets passed in would be only indirectly related to the range of values produced (0..N would need to map to start..stop). Because __iter__ objects retain explicitly managed state between next calls, they can be more general than __getitem__.

On the other hand, using iterators based on __iter__ can sometimes be more complex and less convenient than using __getitem__. They are really designed for iteration, not random indexing—in fact, they don’t overload the indexing expression at all:

>>> X = Squares(1, 5)
>>> X[1]
AttributeError: Squares instance has no attribute '__getitem__'

The __iter__ scheme is also the implementation for all the other iteration contexts we saw in action for __getitem__ (membership tests, type constructors, sequence assignment, and so on). However, unlike our prior __getitem__ example, we also need to be aware that a class’s __iter__ may be designed for a single traversal, not many. For example, the Squares class is a one-shot iteration; once you’ve iterated over an instance of that class, it’s empty. You need to make a new iterator object for each new iteration:

>>> X = Squares(1, 5)
>>> [n for n in X]                      # Exhausts items
[1, 4, 9, 16, 25]
>>> [n for n in X]                      # Now it's empty
[]
>>> [n for n in Squares(1, 5)]          # Make a new iterator object
[1, 4, 9, 16, 25]
>>> list(Squares(1, 3))
[1, 4, 9]

Notice that this example would probably be simpler if it were coded with generator functions or expressions (topics introduced in Chapter 20 and related to iterators):

>>> def gsquares(start, stop):
...     for i in range(start, stop+1):
...         yield i ** 2
...
>>> for i in gsquares(1, 5):                      # or: (x ** 2 for x in range(1, 5))
...     print(i, end=' ')
...
1 4 9 16 25

Unlike the class, the function automatically saves its state between iterations. Of course, for this artificial example, you could in fact skip both techniques and simply use a for loop, map, or a list comprehension to build the list all at once. The best and fastest way to accomplish a task in Python is often also the simplest:

>>> [x ** 2 for x in range(1, 6)]
[1, 4, 9, 16, 25]

However, classes may be better at modeling more complex iterations, especially when they can benefit from state information and inheritance hierarchies. The next section explores one such use case.

Multiple Iterators on One Object

Earlier, I mentioned that the iterator object may be defined as a separate class with its own state information to support multiple active iterations over the same data. Consider what happens when we step across a built-in type like a string:

>>> S = 'ace'
>>> for x in S:
...     for y in S:
...         print(x + y, end=' ')
...
aa ac ae ca cc ce ea ec ee

Here, the outer loop grabs an iterator from the string by calling iter, and each nested loop does the same to get an independent iterator. Because each active iterator has its own state information, each loop can maintain its own position in the string, regardless of any other active loops.

We saw related examples earlier, in Chapters 14 and 20. For instance, generator functions and expressions, as well as built-ins like map and zip, proved to be single-iterator objects; by contrast, the range built-in and other built-in types, like lists, support multiple active iterators with independent positions.

When we code user-defined iterators with classes, it’s up to us to decide whether we will support a single active iteration or many. To achieve the multiple-iterator effect, __iter__ simply needs to define a new stateful object for the iterator, instead of returning self.

The following, for example, defines an iterator class that skips every other item on iterations. Because the iterator object is created anew for each iteration, it supports multiple active loops:

class SkipIterator:
    def __init__(self, wrapped):
        self.wrapped = wrapped                    # Iterator state information
        self.offset  = 0
    def __next__(self):
        if self.offset >= len(self.wrapped):      # Terminate iterations
            raise StopIteration
        else:
            item = self.wrapped[self.offset]      # else return and skip
            self.offset += 2
            return item

class SkipObject:
    def __init__(self, wrapped):                  # Save item to be used
        self.wrapped = wrapped
    def __iter__(self):
        return SkipIterator(self.wrapped)         # New iterator each time

if __name__ == '__main__':
    alpha = 'abcdef'
    skipper = SkipObject(alpha)                   # Make container object
    I = iter(skipper)                             # Make an iterator on it
    print(next(I), next(I), next(I))              # Visit offsets 0, 2, 4

    for x in skipper:               # for calls __iter__ automatically
        for y in skipper:           # Nested fors call __iter__ again each time
            print(x + y, end=' ')   # Each iterator has its own state, offset

When run, this example works like the nested loops with built-in strings. Each active loop has its own position in the string because each obtains an independent iterator object that records its own state information:

% python skipper.py
a c e
aa ac ae ca cc ce ea ec ee

By contrast, our earlier Squares example supports just one active iteration, unless we call Squares again in nested loops to obtain new objects. Here, there is just one SkipObject, with multiple iterator objects created from it.

As before, we could achieve similar results with built-in tools—for example, slicing with a third bound to skip items:

>>> S = 'abcdef'
>>> for x in S[::2]:
...     for y in S[::2]:            # New objects on each iteration
...         print(x + y, end=' ')
...
aa ac ae ca cc ce ea ec ee

This isn’t quite the same, though, for two reasons. First, each slice expression here will physically store the result list all at once in memory; iterators, on the other hand, produce just one value at a time, which can save substantial space for large result lists. Second, slices produce new objects, so we’re not really iterating over the same object in multiple places here. To be closer to the class, we would need to make a single object to step across by slicing ahead of time:

>>> S = 'abcdef'
>>> S = S[::2]
>>> S
'ace'
>>> for x in S:
...     for y in S:                 # Same object, new iterators
...         print(x + y, end=' ')
...
aa ac ae ca cc ce ea ec ee

This is more similar to our class-based solution, but it still stores the slice result in memory all at once (there is no generator form of built-in slicing today), and it’s only equivalent for this particular case of skipping every other item.

Because iterators can do anything a class can do, they are much more general than this example may imply. Regardless of whether our applications require such generality, user-defined iterators are a powerful tool—they allow us to make arbitrary objects look and feel like the other sequences and iterables we have met in this book. We could use this technique with a database object, for example, to support iterations over database fetches, with multiple cursors into the same query result.

Attribute Reference: __getattr__ and __setattr__

The __getattr__ method intercepts attribute qualifications. More specifically, it’s called with the attribute name as a string whenever you try to qualify an instance with an undefined (nonexistent) attribute name. It is not called if Python can find the attribute using its inheritance tree search procedure. Because of its behavior, __getattr__ is useful as a hook for responding to attribute requests in a generic fashion. For example:

>>> class empty:
...     def __getattr__(self, attrname):
...         if attrname == "age":
...             return 40
...         else:
...             raise AttributeError(attrname)
...
>>> X = empty()
>>> X.age
40
>>> X.name
...error text omitted...
AttributeError: name

Here, the empty class and its instance X have no real attributes of their own, so the access to X.age gets routed to the __getattr__ method; self is assigned the instance (X), and attrname is assigned the undefined attribute name string ("age"). The class makes age look like a real attribute by returning a real value as the result of the X.age qualification expression (40). In effect, age becomes a dynamically computed attribute.

For attributes that the class doesn’t know how to handle, __getattr__ raises the built-in AttributeError exception to tell Python that these are bona fide undefined names; asking for X.name triggers the error. You’ll see __getattr__ again when we see delegation and properties at work in the next two chapters, and I’ll say more about exceptions in Part VII.

A related overloading method, __setattr__, intercepts all attribute assignments. If this method is defined, self.attr = value becomes self.__setattr__('attr', value). This is a bit trickier to use because assigning to any self attributes within __setattr__ calls __setattr__ again, causing an infinite recursion loop (and eventually, a stack overflow exception!). If you want to use this method, be sure that it assigns any instance attributes by indexing the attribute dictionary, discussed in the next section. That is, use self.__dict__['name'] = x, not self.name = x:

>>> class accesscontrol:
...     def __setattr__(self, attr, value):
...         if attr == 'age':
...             self.__dict__[attr] = value
...         else:
...             raise AttributeError(attr + ' not allowed')
...
>>> X = accesscontrol()
>>> X.age = 40                                  # Calls __setattr__
>>> X.age
40
>>> X.name = 'mel'
...text omitted...
AttributeError: name not allowed

These two attribute-access overloading methods allow you to control or specialize access to attributes in your objects. They tend to play highly specialized roles, some of which we’ll explore later in this book.

Other Attribute Management Tools

For future reference, also note that there are other ways to manage attribute access in Python:

The __getattribute__ method intercepts all attribute fetches, not just those that are undefined, but when using it you must be more cautious than with __getattr__ to avoid loops.

The property built-in function allows us to associate methods with fetch and set operations on a specific class attribute.

Descriptors provide a protocol for associating __get__ and __set__ methods of a class with accesses to a specific class attribute.

Because these are somewhat advanced tools not of interest to every Python programmer, we’ll defer a look at properties until Chapter 31 and detailed coverage of all the attribute management techniques until Chapter 37.

Emulating Privacy for Instance Attributes: Part 1

The following code generalizes the previous example, to allow each subclass to have its own list of private names that cannot be assigned to its instances:

class PrivateExc(Exception): pass                   # More on exceptions later

class Privacy:
    def __setattr__(self, attrname, value):         # On self.attrname = value
        if attrname in self.privates:
            raise PrivateExc(attrname, self)
        else:
            self.__dict__[attrname] = value         # self.attrname = value loops!

class Test1(Privacy):
    privates = ['age']

class Test2(Privacy):
    privates = ['name', 'pay']
    def __init__(self):
        self.__dict__['name'] = 'Tom'

x = Test1()
y = Test2()

x.name = 'Bob'
y.name = 'Sue'                                      # Fails

y.age  = 30
x.age  = 40                                         # Fails

In fact, this is a first-cut solution for an implementation of attribute privacy in Python (i.e., disallowing changes to attribute names outside a class). Although Python doesn’t support private declarations per se, techniques like this can emulate much of their purpose. This is a partial solution, though; to make it more effective, it must be augmented to allow subclasses to set private attributes more naturally, too, and to use __getattr__ and a wrapper (sometimes called a proxy) class to check for private attribute fetches.

We’ll postpone a more complete solution to attribute privacy until Chapter 38, where we’ll use class decorators to intercept and validate attributes more generally. Even though privacy can be emulated this way, though, it almost never is in practice. Python programmers are able to write large OOP frameworks and applications without private declarations—an interesting finding about access controls in general that is beyond the scope of our purposes here.

Catching attribute references and assignments is generally a useful technique; it supports delegation, a design technique that allows controller objects to wrap up embedded objects, add new behaviors, and route other operations back to the wrapped objects (more on delegation and wrapper classes in Chapter 30).

Comparisons: __lt__, __gt__, and Others

As suggested in Table 29-1, classes can define methods to catch all six comparison operators: <, >, <=, >=, ==, and !=. These methods are generally straightforward to use, but keep the following qualifications in mind:

Unlike the __add__/__radd__ pairings discussed earlier, there are no right-side variants of comparison methods. Instead, reflective methods are used when only one operand supports comparison (e.g., __lt__ and __gt__ are each other’s reflection).

There are no implicit relationships among the comparison operators. The truth of == does not imply that != is false, for example, so both __eq__ and __ne__ should be defined to ensure that both operators behave correctly.

In Python 2.6, a __cmp__ method is used by all comparisons if no more specific comparison methods are defined; it returns a number that is less than, equal to, or greater than zero, to signal less than, equal, and greater than results for the comparison of its two arguments (self and another operand). This method often uses the cmp(x, y) built-in to compute its result. Both the __cmp__ method and the cmp built-in function are removed in Python 3.0: use the more specific methods instead.

We don’t have space for an in-depth exploration of comparison methods, but as a quick introduction, consider the following class and test code:

class C:
    data = 'spam'
    def __gt__(self, other):               # 3.0 and 2.6 version
        return self.data > other
    def __lt__(self, other):
        return self.data < other

X = C()
print(X > 'ham')                           # True  (runs __gt__)
print(X < 'ham')                           # False (runs __lt__)

When run under Python 3.0 or 2.6, the prints at the end display the expected results noted in their comments, because the class’s methods intercept and implement comparison expressions.

The 2.6 __cmp__ Method (Removed in 3.0)

In Python 2.6, the __cmp__ method is used as a fallback if more specific methods are not defined: its integer result is used to evaluate the operator being run. The following produces the same result under 2.6, for example, but fails in 3.0 because __cmp__ is no longer used:

class C:
    data = 'spam'                          # 2.6 only
    def __cmp__(self, other):              # __cmp__ not used in 3.0
        return cmp(self.data, other)       # cmp not defined in 3.0

X = C()
print(X > 'ham')                           # True  (runs __cmp__)
print(X < 'ham')                           # False (runs __cmp__)

Notice that this fails in 3.0 because __cmp__ is no longer special, not because the cmp built-in function is no longer present. If we change the prior class to the following to try to simulate the cmp call, the code still works in 2.6 but fails in 3.0:

class C:
    data = 'spam'
    def __cmp__(self, other):
        return (self.data > other) - (self.data < other)

Note

So why, you might be asking, did I just show you a comparison method that is no longer supported in 3.0? While it would be easier to erase history entirely, this book is designed to support both 2.6 and 3.0 readers. Because __cmp__ may appear in code 2.6 readers must reuse or maintain, it’s fair game in this book. Moreover, __cmp__ was removed more abruptly than the __getslice__ method described earlier, and so may endure longer. If you use 3.0, though, or care about running your code under 3.0 in the future, don’t use __cmp__ anymore: use the more specific comparison methods instead.

Object Destruction: __del__

We’ve seen how the __init__ constructor is called whenever an instance is generated. Its counterpart, the destructor method __del__, is run automatically when an instance’s space is being reclaimed (i.e., at “garbage collection” time):

>>> class Life:
...     def __init__(self, name='unknown'):
...         print('Hello', name)
...         self.name = name
...     def __del__(self):
...         print('Goodbye', self.name)
...
>>> brian = Life('Brian')
Hello Brian
>>> brian = 'loretta'
Goodbye Brian

Here, when brian is assigned a string, we lose the last reference to the Life instance and so trigger its destructor method. This works, and it may be useful for implementing some cleanup activities (such as terminating server connections). However, destructors are not as commonly used in Python as in some OOP languages, for a number of reasons.

For one thing, because Python automatically reclaims all space held by an instance when the instance is reclaimed, destructors are not necessary for space management.[68] For another, because you cannot always easily predict when an instance will be reclaimed, it’s often better to code termination activities in an explicitly called method (or try/finally statement, described in the next part of the book); in some cases, there may be lingering references to your objects in system tables that prevent destructors from running.

Note

In fact, __del__ can be tricky to use for even more subtle reasons. Exceptions raised within it, for example, simply print a warning message to sys.stderr (the standard error stream) rather than triggering an exception event, because of the unpredictable context under which it is run by the garbage collector. In addition, cyclic (a.k.a. circular) references among objects may prevent garbage collection from happening when you expect it to; an optional cycle detector, enabled by default, can automatically collect such objects eventually, but only if they do not have __del__ methods. Since this is relatively obscure, we’ll ignore further details here; see Python’s standard manuals’ coverage of both __del__ and the gc garbage collector module for more information.

Chapter Summary

That’s as many overloading examples as we have space for here. Most of the other operator overloading methods work similarly to the ones we’ve explored, and all are just hooks for intercepting built-in type operations; some overloading methods, for example, have unique argument lists or return values. We’ll see a few others in action later in the book:

Chapter 33 uses the __enter__ and __exit__ with statement context manager methods.

Chapter 37 uses the __get__ and __set__ class descriptor fetch/set methods.

Chapter 39 uses the __new__ object creation method in the context of metaclasses.

In addition, some of the methods we’ve studied here, such as __call__ and __str__, will be employed by later examples in this book. For complete coverage, though, I’ll defer to other documentation sources—see Python’s standard language manual or reference books for details on additional overloading methods.

In the next chapter, we leave the realm of class mechanics behind to explore common design patterns—the ways that classes are commonly used and combined to optimize code reuse. Before you read on, though, take a moment to work though the chapter quiz below to review the concepts we’ve covered.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Classes can support iteration by defining (or inheriting) __getitem__ or __iter__. In all iteration contexts, Python tries to use __iter__ (which returns an object that supports the iteration protocol with a __next__ method) first: if no __iter__ is found by inheritance search, Python falls back on the __getitem__ indexing method (which is called repeatedly, with successively higher indexes).

The __str__ and __repr__ methods implement object print displays. The former is called by the print and str built-in functions; the latter is called by print and str if there is no __str__, and always by the repr built-in, interactive echoes, and nested appearances. That is, __repr__ is used everywhere, except by print and str when a __str__ is defined. A __str__ is usually used for user-friendly displays; __repr__ gives extra details or the object’s as-code form.

Slicing is caught by the __getitem__ indexing method: it is called with a slice object, instead of a simple index. In Python 2.6, __getslice__ (defunct in 3.0) may be used as well.

In-place addition tries __iadd__ first, and __add__ with an assignment second. The same pattern holds true for all binary operators. The __radd__ method is also available for right-side addition.

When a class naturally matches, or needs to emulate, a built-in type’s interfaces. For example, collections might imitate sequence or mapping interfaces. You generally shouldn’t implement expression operators if they don’t naturally map to your objects, though—use normally named methods instead.

[68] In the current C implementation of Python, you also don’t need to close file objects held by the instance in destructors because they are automatically closed when reclaimed. However, as mentioned in Chapter 9, it’s better to explicitly call file close methods because auto-close-on-reclaim is a feature of the implementation, not of the language itself (this behavior can vary under Jython, for instance).

Python and OOP

Let’s begin with a review—Python’s implementation of OOP can be summarized by three ideas:

Inheritance

Inheritance is based on attribute lookup in Python (in X.name expressions).

Polymorphism

In X.method, the meaning of method depends on the type (class) of X.

Encapsulation

Methods and operators implement behavior; data hiding is a convention by default.

By now, you should have a good feel for what inheritance is all about in Python. We’ve also talked about Python’s polymorphism a few times already; it flows from Python’s lack of type declarations. Because attributes are always resolved at runtime, objects that implement the same interfaces are interchangeable; clients don’t need to know what sorts of objects are implementing the methods they call.

Encapsulation means packaging in Python—that is, hiding implementation details behind an object’s interface. It does not mean enforced privacy, though that can be implemented with code, as we’ll see in Chapter 38. Encapsulation allows the implementation of an object’s interface to be changed without impacting the users of that object.

Overloading by Call Signatures (or Not)

Some OOP languages also define polymorphism to mean overloading functions based on the type signatures of their arguments. But because there are no type declarations in Python, this concept doesn’t really apply; polymorphism in Python is based on object interfaces, not types.

You can try to overload methods by their argument lists, like this:

class C:
    def meth(self, x):
        ...
    def meth(self, x, y, z):
        ...

This code will run, but because the def simply assigns an object to a name in the class’s scope, the last definition of the method function is the only one that will be retained (it’s just as if you say X = 1 and then X = 2; X will be 2).

Type-based selections can always be coded using the type-testing ideas we met in Chapters 4 and 9, or the argument list tools introduced in Chapter 18:

class C:
    def meth(self, *args):
        if len(args) == 1:
            ...
        elif type(arg[0]) == int:
            ...

You normally shouldn’t do this, though—as described in Chapter 16, you should write your code to expect an object interface, not a specific data type. That way, it will be useful for a broader category of types and applications, both now and in the future:

class C:
    def meth(self, x):
        x.operation()                   # Assume x does the right thing

It’s also generally considered better to use distinct method names for distinct operations, rather than relying on call signatures (no matter what language you code in).

Although Python’s object model is straightforward, much of the art in OOP is in the way we combine classes to achieve a program’s goals. The next section begins a tour of some of the ways larger programs use classes to their advantage.

OOP and Inheritance: “Is-a” Relationships

We’ve explored the mechanics of inheritance in depth already, but I’d like to show you an example of how it can be used to model real-world relationships. From a programmer’s point of view, inheritance is kicked off by attribute qualifications, which trigger searches for names in instances, their classes, and then any superclasses. From a designer’s point of view, inheritance is a way to specify set membership: a class defines a set of properties that may be inherited and customized by more specific sets (i.e., subclasses).

To illustrate, let’s put that pizza-making robot we talked about at the start of this part of the book to work. Suppose we’ve decided to explore alternative career paths and open a pizza restaurant. One of the first things we’ll need to do is hire employees to serve customers, prepare the food, and so on. Being engineers at heart, we’ve decided to build a robot to make the pizzas; but being politically and cybernetically correct, we’ve also decided to make our robot a full-fledged employee with a salary.

Our pizza shop team can be defined by the four classes in the example file, employees.py. The most general class, Employee, provides common behavior such as bumping up salaries (giveRaise) and printing (__repr__). There are two kinds of employees, and so two subclasses of Employee: Chef and Server. Both override the inherited work method to print more specific messages. Finally, our pizza robot is modeled by an even more specific class: PizzaRobot is a kind of Chef, which is a kind of Employee. In OOP terms, we call these relationships “is-a” links: a robot is a chef, which is a(n) employee. Here’s the employees.py file:

class Employee:
    def __init__(self, name, salary=0):
        self.name   = name
        self.salary = salary
    def giveRaise(self, percent):
        self.salary = self.salary + (self.salary * percent)
    def work(self):
        print(self.name, "does stuff")
    def __repr__(self):
        return "<Employee: name=%s, salary=%s>" % (self.name, self.salary)

class Chef(Employee):
    def __init__(self, name):
        Employee.__init__(self, name, 50000)
    def work(self):
        print(self.name, "makes food")

class Server(Employee):
    def __init__(self, name):
        Employee.__init__(self, name, 40000)
    def work(self):
        print(self.name, "interfaces with customer")

class PizzaRobot(Chef):
    def __init__(self, name):
        Chef.__init__(self, name)
    def work(self):
        print(self.name, "makes pizza")

if __name__ == "__main__":
    bob = PizzaRobot('bob')       # Make a robot named bob
    print(bob)                    # Run inherited __repr__
    bob.work()                    # Run type-specific action
    bob.giveRaise(0.20)           # Give bob a 20% raise
    print(bob); print()

    for klass in Employee, Chef, Server, PizzaRobot:
        obj = klass(klass.__name__)
        obj.work()

When we run the self-test code included in this module, we create a pizza-making robot named bob, which inherits names from three classes: PizzaRobot, Chef, and Employee. For instance, printing bob runs the Employee.__repr__ method, and giving bob a raise invokes Employee.giveRaise because that’s where the inheritance search finds that method:

C:\python\examples> python employees.py
<Employee: name=bob, salary=50000>
bob makes pizza
<Employee: name=bob, salary=60000.0>

Employee does stuff
Chef makes food
Server interfaces with customer
PizzaRobot makes pizza

In a class hierarchy like this, you can usually make instances of any of the classes, not just the ones at the bottom. For instance, the for loop in this module’s self-test code creates instances of all four classes; each responds differently when asked to work because the work method is different in each. Really, these classes just simulate real-world objects; work prints a message for the time being, but it could be expanded to do real work later.

OOP and Composition: “Has-a” Relationships

The notion of composition was introduced in Chapter 25. From a programmer’s point of view, composition involves embedding other objects in a container object, and activating them to implement container methods. To a designer, composition is another way to represent relationships in a problem domain. But, rather than set membership, composition has to do with components—parts of a whole.

Composition also reflects the relationships between parts, called a “has-a” relationships. Some OOP design texts refer to composition as aggregation (or distinguish between the two terms by using aggregation to describe a weaker dependency between container and contained); in this text, a “composition” simply refers to a collection of embedded objects. The composite class generally provides an interface all its own and implements it by directing the embedded objects.

Now that we’ve implemented our employees, let’s put them in the pizza shop and let them get busy. Our pizza shop is a composite object: it has an oven, and it has employees like servers and chefs. When a customer enters and places an order, the components of the shop spring into action—the server takes the order, the chef makes the pizza, and so on. The following example (the file pizzashop.py) simulates all the objects and relationships in this scenario:

from employees import PizzaRobot, Server

class Customer:
    def __init__(self, name):
        self.name = name
    def order(self, server):
        print(self.name, "orders from", server)
    def pay(self, server):
        print(self.name, "pays for item to", server)

class Oven:
    def bake(self):
        print("oven bakes")

class PizzaShop:
    def __init__(self):
        self.server = Server('Pat')         # Embed other objects
        self.chef   = PizzaRobot('Bob')     # A robot named bob
        self.oven   = Oven()

    def order(self, name):
        customer = Customer(name)           # Activate other objects
        customer.order(self.server)         # Customer orders from server
        self.chef.work()
        self.oven.bake()
        customer.pay(self.server)

if __name__ == "__main__":
    scene = PizzaShop()                     # Make the composite
    scene.order('Homer')                    # Simulate Homer's order
    print('...')
    scene.order('Shaggy')                   # Simulate Shaggy's order

The PizzaShop class is a container and controller; its constructor makes and embeds instances of the employee classes we wrote in the last section, as well as an Oven class defined here. When this module’s self-test code calls the PizzaShop order method, the embedded objects are asked to carry out their actions in turn. Notice that we make a new Customer object for each order, and we pass on the embedded Server object to Customer methods; customers come and go, but the server is part of the pizza shop composite. Also notice that employees are still involved in an inheritance relationship; composition and inheritance are complementary tools.

When we run this module, our pizza shop handles two orders—one from Homer, and then one from Shaggy:

C:\python\examples> python pizzashop.py
Homer orders from <Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>
Bob makes pizza
oven bakes
Homer pays for item to <Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>
...
Shaggy orders from <Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>
Bob makes pizza
oven bakes
Shaggy pays for item to <Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>

Again, this is mostly just a toy simulation, but the objects and interactions are representative of composites at work. As a rule of thumb, classes can represent just about any objects and relationships you can express in a sentence; just replace nouns with classes, and verbs with methods, and you’ll have a first cut at a design.

Stream Processors Revisited

For a more realistic composition example, recall the generic data stream processor function we partially coded in the introduction to OOP in Chapter 25:

def processor(reader, converter, writer):
    while 1:
        data = reader.read()
        if not data: break
        data = converter(data)
        writer.write(data)

Rather than using a simple function here, we might code this as a class that uses composition to do its work to provide more structure and support inheritance. The following file, streams.py, demonstrates one way to code the class:

class Processor:
    def __init__(self, reader, writer):
        self.reader = reader
        self.writer = writer
    def process(self):
        while 1:
            data = self.reader.readline()
            if not data: break
            data = self.converter(data)
            self.writer.write(data)
    def converter(self, data):
        assert False, 'converter must be defined'       # Or raise exception

This class defines a converter method that it expects subclasses to fill in; it’s an example of the abstract superclass model we outlined in Chapter 28 (more on assert in Part VII). Coded this way, reader and writer objects are embedded within the class instance (composition), and we supply the conversion logic in a subclass rather than passing in a converter function (inheritance). The file converters.py shows how:

from streams import Processor

class Uppercase(Processor):
    def converter(self, data):
        return data.upper()

if __name__ == '__main__':
    import sys
    obj = Uppercase(open('spam.txt'), sys.stdout)
    obj.process()

Here, the Uppercase class inherits the stream-processing loop logic (and anything else that may be coded in its superclasses). It needs to define only what is unique about it—the data conversion logic. When this file is run, it makes and runs an instance that reads from the file spam.txt and writes the uppercase equivalent of that file to the stdout stream:

C:\lp4e> type spam.txt
spam
Spam
SPAM!

C:\lp4e> python converters.py
SPAM
SPAM
SPAM!

To process different sorts of streams, pass in different sorts of objects to the class construction call. Here, we use an output file instead of a stream:

C:\lp4e> python
>>> import converters
>>> prog = converters.Uppercase(open('spam.txt'), open('spamup.txt', 'w'))
>>> prog.process()

C:\lp4e> type spamup.txt
SPAM
SPAM
SPAM!

But, as suggested earlier, we could also pass in arbitrary objects wrapped up in classes that define the required input and output method interfaces. Here’s a simple example that passes in a writer class that wraps up the text inside HTML tags:

C:\lp4e> python
>>> from converters import Uppercase
>>>
>>> class HTMLize:
...      def write(self, line):
...         print('<PRE>%s</PRE>' % line.rstrip())
...
>>> Uppercase(open('spam.txt'), HTMLize()).process()
<PRE>SPAM</PRE>
<PRE>SPAM</PRE>
<PRE>SPAM!</PRE>

If you trace through this example’s control flow, you’ll see that we get both uppercase conversion (by inheritance) and HTML formatting (by composition), even though the core processing logic in the original Processor superclass knows nothing about either step. The processing code only cares that writers have a write method and that a method named convert is defined; it doesn’t care what those methods do when they are called. Such polymorphism and encapsulation of logic is behind much of the power of classes.

As is, the Processor superclass only provides a file-scanning loop. In more realistic work, we might extend it to support additional programming tools for its subclasses, and, in the process, turn it into a full-blown framework. Coding such a tool once in a superclass enables you to reuse it in all of your programs. Even in this simple example, because so much is packaged and inherited with classes, all we had to code was the HTML formatting step; the rest was free.

For another example of composition at work, see exercise 9 at the end of Chapter 31 and its solution in Appendix B; it’s similar to the pizza shop example. We’ve focused on inheritance in this book because that is the main tool that the Python language itself provides for OOP. But, in practice, composition is used as much as inheritance as a way to structure classes, especially in larger systems. As we’ve seen, inheritance and composition are often complementary (and sometimes alternative) techniques. Because composition is a design issue outside the scope of the Python language and this book, though, I’ll defer to other resources for more on this topic.

Why You Will Care: Classes and Persistence

I’ve mentioned Python’s pickle and shelve object persistence support a few times in this part of the book because it works especially well with class instances. In fact, these tools are often compelling enough to motivate the use of classes in general—by pickling or shelving a class instance, we get data storage that contains both data and logic combined.

For example, besides allowing us to simulate real-world interactions, the pizza shop classes developed in this chapter could also be used as the basis of a persistent restaurant database. Instances of classes can be stored away on disk in a single step using Python’s pickle or shelve modules. We used shelves to store instances of classes in the OOP tutorial in Chapter 27, but the object pickling interface is remarkably easy to use as well:

import pickle
object = someClass()
file   = open(filename, 'wb')     # Create external file
pickle.dump(object, file)         # Save object in file

import pickle
file   = open(filename, 'rb')
object = pickle.load(file)        # Fetch it back later

Pickling converts in-memory objects to serialized byte streams (really, strings), which may be stored in files, sent across a network, and so on; unpickling converts back from byte streams to identical in-memory objects. Shelves are similar, but they automatically pickle objects to an access-by-key database, which exports a dictionary-like interface:

import shelve
object = someClass()
dbase  = shelve.open('filename')
dbase['key'] = object             # Save under key

import shelve
dbase  = shelve.open('filename')
object = dbase['key']             # Fetch it back later

In our pizza shop example, using classes to model employees means we can get a simple database of employees and shops with little extra work—pickling such instance objects to a file makes them persistent across Python program executions:

>>> from pizzashop import PizzaShop
>>> shop = PizzaShop()
>>> shop.server, shop.chef
(<Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>, <Employee: name=Bob, salary=50000>)
>>> import pickle
>>> pickle.dump(shop, open('shopfile.dat', 'wb'))

This stores an entire composite shop object in a file all at once. To bring it back later in another session or program, a single step suffices as well. In fact, objects restored this way retain both state and behavior:

>>> import pickle
>>> obj = pickle.load(open('shopfile.dat', 'rb'))
>>> obj.server, obj.chef
(<Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>, <Employee: name=Bob, salary=50000>)
>>> obj.order('Sue')
Sue orders from <Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>
Bob makes pizza
oven bakes
Sue pays for item to <Employee: name=Pat, salary=40000>

See the standard library manual and later examples for more on pickles and shelves.

OOP and Delegation: “Wrapper” Objects

Beside inheritance and composition, object-oriented programmers often also talk about something called delegation, which usually implies controller objects that embed other objects to which they pass off operation requests. The controllers can take care of administrative activities, such as keeping track of accesses and so on. In Python, delegation is often implemented with the __getattr__ method hook; because it intercepts accesses to nonexistent attributes, a wrapper class (sometimes called a proxy class) can use __getattr__ to route arbitrary accesses to a wrapped object. The wrapper class retains the interface of the wrapped object and may add additional operations of its own.

Consider the file trace.py, for instance:

class wrapper:
    def __init__(self, object):
        self.wrapped = object                    # Save object
    def __getattr__(self, attrname):
        print('Trace:', attrname)                # Trace fetch
        return getattr(self.wrapped, attrname)   # Delegate fetch

Recall from Chapter 29 that __getattr__ gets the attribute name as a string. This code makes use of the getattr built-in function to fetch an attribute from the wrapped object by name string—getattr(X,N) is like X.N, except that N is an expression that evaluates to a string at runtime, not a variable. In fact, getattr(X,N) is similar to X.__dict__[N], but the former also performs an inheritance search, like X.N, while the latter does not (see Namespace Dictionaries for more on the __dict__ attribute).

You can use the approach of this module’s wrapper class to manage access to any object with attributes—lists, dictionaries, and even classes and instances. Here, the wrapper class simply prints a trace message on each attribute access and delegates the attribute request to the embedded wrapped object:

>>> from trace import wrapper
>>> x = wrapper([1,2,3])                         # Wrap a list
>>> x.append(4)                                  # Delegate to list method
Trace: append
>>> x.wrapped                                    # Print my member
[1, 2, 3, 4]

>>> x = wrapper({"a": 1, "b": 2})                # Wrap a dictionary
>>> list(x.keys())                               # Delegate to dictionary method
Trace: keys
['a', 'b']

The net effect is to augment the entire interface of the wrapped object, with additional code in the wrapper class. We can use this to log our method calls, route method calls to extra or custom logic, and so on.

We’ll revive the notions of wrapped objects and delegated operations as one way to extend built-in types in Chapter 31. If you are interested in the delegation design pattern, also watch for the discussions in Chapters 31 and 38 of function decorators, a strongly related concept designed to augment a specific function or method call rather than the entire interface of an object, and class decorators, which serve as a way to automatically add such delegation-based wrappers to all instances of a class.

Note

Version skew note: In Python 2.6, operator overloading methods run by built-in operations are routed through generic attribute interception methods like __getattr__. Printing a wrapped object directly, for example, calls this method for __repr__ or __str__, which then passes the call on to the wrapped object. In Python 3.0, this no longer happens: printing does not trigger __getattr__, and a default display is used instead. In 3.0, new-style classes look up operator overloading methods in classes and skip the normal instance lookup entirely. We’ll return to this issue in Chapter 37, in the context of managed attributes; for now, keep in mind that you may need to redefine operator overloading methods in wrapper classes (either by hand, by tools, or by superclasses) if you want them to be intercepted in 3.0.

Pseudoprivate Class Attributes

Besides larger structuring goals, class designs often must address name usage too. In Part V, we learned that every name assigned at the top level of a module file is exported. By default, the same holds for classes—data hiding is a convention, and clients may fetch or change any class or instance attribute they like. In fact, attributes are all “public” and “virtual,” in C++ terms; they’re all accessible everywhere and are looked up dynamically at runtime.[69]

That said, Python today does support the notion of name “mangling” (i.e., expansion) to localize some names in classes. Mangled names are sometimes misleadingly called “private attributes,” but really this is just a way to localize a name to the class that created it—name mangling does not prevent access by code outside the class. This feature is mostly intended to avoid namespace collisions in instances, not to restrict access to names in general; mangled names are therefore better called “pseudoprivate” than “private.”

Pseudoprivate names are an advanced and entirely optional feature, and you probably won’t find them very useful until you start writing general tools or larger class hierarchies for use in multiprogrammer projects. In fact, they are not always used even when they probably should be—more commonly, Python programmers code internal names with a single underscore (e.g., _X), which is just an informal convention to let you know that a name shouldn’t be changed (it means nothing to Python itself).

Because you may see this feature in other people’s code, though, you need to be somewhat aware of it, even if you don’t use it yourself.

Name Mangling Overview

Here’s how name mangling works: names inside a class statement that start with two underscores but don’t end with two underscores are automatically expanded to include the name of the enclosing class. For instance, a name like __X within a class named Spam is changed to _Spam__X automatically: the original name is prefixed with a single underscore and the enclosing class’s name. Because the modified name contains the name of the enclosing class, it’s somewhat unique; it won’t clash with similar names created by other classes in a hierarchy.

Name mangling happens only in class statements, and only for names that begin with two leading underscores. However, it happens for every name preceded with double underscores—both class attributes (like method names) and instance attribute names assigned to self attributes. For example, in a class named Spam, a method named __meth is mangled to _Spam__meth, and an instance attribute reference self.__X is transformed to self._Spam__X. Because more than one class may add attributes to an instance, this mangling helps avoid clashes—but we need to move on to an example to see how.

Why Use Pseudoprivate Attributes?

One of the main problems that the pseudoprivate attribute feature is meant to alleviate has to do with the way instance attributes are stored. In Python, all instance attributes wind up in the single instance object at the bottom of the class tree. This is different from the C++ model, where each class gets its own space for data members it defines.

Within a class method in Python, whenever a method assigns to a self attribute (e.g., self.attr = value), it changes or creates an attribute in the instance (inheritance searches happen only on reference, not on assignment). Because this is true even if multiple classes in a hierarchy assign to the same attribute, collisions are possible.

For example, suppose that when a programmer codes a class, she assumes that she owns the attribute name X in the instance. In this class’s methods, the name is set, and later fetched:

class C1:
    def meth1(self): self.X = 88         # I assume X is mine
    def meth2(self): print(self.X)

Suppose further that another programmer, working in isolation, makes the same assumption in a class that he codes:

class C2:
    def metha(self): self.X = 99         # Me too
    def methb(self): print(self.X)

Both of these classes work by themselves. The problem arises if the two classes are ever mixed together in the same class tree:

class C3(C1, C2): ...
I = C3()                                 # Only 1 X in I!

Now, the value that each class gets back when it says self.X will depend on which class assigned it last. Because all assignments to self.X refer to the same single instance, there is only one X attribute—I.X—no matter how many classes use that attribute name.

To guarantee that an attribute belongs to the class that uses it, prefix the name with double underscores everywhere it is used in the class, as in this file, private.py:

class C1:
    def meth1(self): self.__X = 88       # Now X is mine
    def meth2(self): print(self.__X)     # Becomes _C1__X in I
class C2:
    def metha(self): self.__X = 99       # Me too
    def methb(self): print(self.__X)     # Becomes _C2__X in I

class C3(C1, C2): pass
I = C3()                                 # Two X names in I

I.meth1(); I.metha()
print(I.__dict__)
I.meth2(); I.methb()

When thus prefixed, the X attributes will be expanded to include the names of their classes before being added to the instance. If you run a dir call on I or inspect its namespace dictionary after the attributes have been assigned, you’ll see the expanded names, _C1__X and _C2__X, but not X. Because the expansion makes the names unique within the instance, the class coders can safely assume that they truly own any names that they prefix with two underscores:

% python private.py
{'_C2__X': 99, '_C1__X': 88}
88
99

This trick can avoid potential name collisions in the instance, but note that it does not amount to true privacy. If you know the name of the enclosing class, you can still access either of these attributes anywhere you have a reference to the instance by using the fully expanded name (e.g., I._C1__X = 77). On the other hand, this feature makes it less likely that you will accidentally step on a class’s names.

Pseudoprivate attributes are also useful in larger frameworks or tools, both to avoid introducing new method names that might accidentally hide definitions elsewhere in the class tree and to reduce the chance of internal methods being replaced by names defined lower in the tree. If a method is intended for use only within a class that may be mixed into other classes, the double underscore prefix ensures that the method won’t interfere with other names in the tree, especially in multiple-inheritance scenarios:

class Super:
    def method(self): ...                  # A real application method

class Tool:
    def __method(self): ...                # Becomes _Tool__method
    def other(self): self.__method()       # Use my internal method

class Sub1(Tool, Super): ...
    def actions(self): self.method()       # Runs Super.method as expected

class Sub2(Tool):
    def __init__(self): self.method = 99   # Doesn't break Tool.__method

We met multiple inheritance briefly in Chapter 25 and will explore it in more detail later in this chapter. Recall that superclasses are searched according to their left-to-right order in class header lines. Here, this means Sub1 prefers Tool attributes to those in Super. Although in this example we could force Python to pick the application class’s methods first by switching the order of the superclasses listed in the Sub1 class header, pseudoprivate attributes resolve the issue altogether. Pseudoprivate names also prevent subclasses from accidentally redefining the internal method’s names, as in Sub2.

Again, I should note that this feature tends to be of use primarily for larger, multiprogrammer projects, and then only for selected names. Don’t be tempted to clutter your code unnecessarily; only use this feature for names that truly need to be controlled by a single class. For simpler programs, it’s probably overkill.

For more examples that make use of the __X naming feature, see the lister.py mix-in classes introduced later in this chapter, in the section on multiple inheritance, as well as the discussion of Private class decorators in Chapter 38. If you care about privacy in general, you might want to review the emulation of private instance attributes sketched in the section Attribute Reference: __getattr__ and __setattr__ in Chapter 29, and watch for the Private class decorator in Chapter 38 that we will base upon this special method. Although it’s possible to emulate true access controls in Python classes, this is rarely done in practice, even for large systems.

Methods Are Objects: Bound or Unbound

Methods in general, and bound methods in particular, simplify the implementation of many design goals in Python. We met bound methods briefly while studying __call__ in Chapter 29. The full story, which we’ll flesh out here, turns out to be more general and flexible than you might expect.

In Chapter 19, we learned how functions can be processed as normal objects. Methods are a kind of object too, and can be used generically in much the same way as other objects—they can be assigned, passed to functions, stored in data structures, and so on. Because class methods can be accessed from an instance or a class, though, they actually come in two flavors in Python:

Unbound class method objects: no self

Accessing a function attribute of a class by qualifying the class returns an unbound method object. To call the method, you must provide an instance object explicitly as the first argument. In Python 3.0, an unbound method is the same as a simple function and can be called though the class’s name; in 2.6 it’s a distinct type and cannot be called without providing an instance.

Bound instance method objects: self + function pairs

Accessing a function attribute of a class by qualifying an instance returns a bound method object. Python automatically packages the instance with the function in the bound method object, so you don’t need to pass an instance to call the method.

Both kinds of methods are full-fledged objects; they can be transferred around a program at will, just like strings and numbers. Both also require an instance in their first argument when run (i.e., a value for self). This is why we had to pass in an instance explicitly when calling superclass methods from subclass methods in the previous chapter; technically, such calls produce unbound method objects.

When calling a bound method object, Python provides an instance for you automatically—the instance used to create the bound method object. This means that bound method objects are usually interchangeable with simple function objects, and makes them especially useful for interfaces originally written for functions (see the sidebar Why You Will Care: Bound Methods and Callbacks for a realistic example).

To illustrate, suppose we define the following class:

class Spam:
    def doit(self, message):
        print(message)

Now, in normal operation, we make an instance and call its method in a single step to print the passed-in argument:

object1 = Spam()
object1.doit('hello world')

Really, though, a bound method object is generated along the way, just before the method call’s parentheses. In fact, we can fetch a bound method without actually calling it. An object.name qualification is an object expression. In the following, it returns a bound method object that packages the instance (object1) with the method function (Spam.doit). We can assign this bound method pair to another name and then call it as though it were a simple function:

object1 = Spam()
x = object1.doit        # Bound method object: instance+function
x('hello world')        # Same effect as object1.doit('...')

On the other hand, if we qualify the class to get to doit, we get back an unbound method object, which is simply a reference to the function object. To call this type of method, we must pass in an instance as the leftmost argument:

object1 = Spam()
t = Spam.doit           # Unbound method object (a function in 3.0: see ahead)
t(object1, 'howdy')     # Pass in instance (if the method expects one in 3.0)

By extension, the same rules apply within a class’s method if we reference self attributes that refer to functions in the class. A self.method expression is a bound method object because self is an instance object:

class Eggs:
    def m1(self, n):
        print(n)
    def m2(self):
        x = self.m1     # Another bound method object
        x(42)           # Looks like a simple function

Eggs().m2()             # Prints 42

Most of the time, you call methods immediately after fetching them with attribute qualification, so you don’t always notice the method objects generated along the way. But if you start writing code that calls objects generically, you need to be careful to treat unbound methods specially—they normally require an explicit instance object to be passed in.[70]

Unbound Methods are Functions in 3.0

In Python 3.0, the language has dropped the notion of unbound methods. What we describe as an unbound method here is treated as a simple function in 3.0. For most purposes, this makes no difference to your code; either way, an instance will be passed to a method’s first argument when it’s called through an instance.

Programs that do explicit type testing might be impacted, though—if you print the type of an instance-less class method, it displays “unbound method” in 2.6, and “function” in 3.0.

Moreover, in 3.0 it is OK to call a method without an instance, as long as the method does not expect one and you call it only through the class and never through an instance. That is, Python 3.0 will pass along an instance to methods only for through-instance calls. When calling through a class, you must pass an instance manually only if the method expects one:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> class Selfless:
...     def __init__(self, data):
...         self.data = data
...     def selfless(arg1, arg2):               # A simple function in 3.0
...         return arg1 + arg2
...     def normal(self, arg1, arg2):           # Instance expected when called
...         return self.data + arg1 + arg2
...
>>> X = Selfless(2)
>>> X.normal(3, 4)                  # Instance passed to self automatically
9
>>> Selfless.normal(X, 3, 4)        # self expected by method: pass manually
9
>>> Selfless.selfless(3, 4)         # No instance: works in 3.0, fails in 2.6!
7

The last test in this fails in 2.6, because unbound methods require an instance to be passed by default; it works in 3.0 because such methods are treated as simple functions not requiring an instance. Although this removes some potential error trapping in 3.0 (what if a programmer accidentally forgets to pass an instance?), it allows class methods to be used as simple functions as long as they are not passed and do not expect a “self” instance argument.

The following two calls still fail in both 3.0 and 2.6, though—the first (calling through an instance) automatically passes an instance to a method that does not expect one, while the second (calling through a class) does not pass an instance to a method that does expect one:

>>> X.selfless(3, 4)
TypeError: selfless() takes exactly 2 positional arguments (3 given)

>>> Selfless.normal(3, 4)
TypeError: normal() takes exactly 3 positional arguments (2 given)

Because of this change, the staticmethod decorator described in the next chapter is not needed in 3.0 for methods without a self argument that are called only through the class name, and never through an instance—such methods are run as simple functions, without receiving an instance argument. In 2.6, such calls are errors unless an instance is passed manually (more on static methods in the next chapter).

It’s important to be aware of the differences in behavior in 3.0, but bound methods are generally more important from a practical perspective anyway. Because they pair together the instance and function in a single object, they can be treated as callables generically. The next section demonstrates what this means in code.

Note

For a more visual illustration of unbound method treatment in Python 3.0 and 2.6, see also the lister.py example in the multiple inheritance section later in this chapter. Its classes print the value of methods fetched from both instances and classes, in both versions of Python.

Bound Methods and Other Callable Objects

As mentioned earlier, bound methods can be processed as generic objects, just like simple functions—they can be passed around a program arbitrarily. Moreover, because bound methods combine both a function and an instance in a single package, they can be treated like any other callable object and require no special syntax when invoked. The following, for example, stores four bound method objects in a list and calls them later with normal call expressions:

>>> class Number:
...     def __init__(self, base):
...         self.base = base
...     def double(self):
...         return self.base * 2
...     def triple(self):
...         return self.base * 3
...
>>> x = Number(2)                                       # Class instance objects
>>> y = Number(3)                                       # State + methods
>>> z = Number(4)
>>> x.double()                                          # Normal immediate calls
4

>>> acts = [x.double, y.double, y.triple, z.double]     # List of bound methods
>>> for act in acts:                                    # Calls are deferred
...     print(act())                                    # Call as though functions
...
4
6
9
8

Like simple functions, bound method objects have introspection information of their own, including attributes that give access to the instance object and method function they pair. Calling the bound method simply dispatches the pair:

>>> bound = x.double
>>> bound.__self__, bound.__func__
(<__main__.Number object at 0x0278F610>, <function double at 0x027A4ED0>)
>>> bound.__self__.base
2
>>> bound()                             # Calls bound.__func__(bound.__self__, ...)
4

In fact, bound methods are just one of a handful of callable object types in Python. As the following demonstrates, simple functions coded with a def or lambda, instances that inherit a __call__, and bound instance methods can all be treated and called the same way:

>>> def square(arg):
...     return arg ** 2                          # Simple functions (def or lambda)
...
>>> class Sum:
...     def __init__(self, val):                 # Callable instances
...         self.val = val
...     def __call__(self, arg):
...         return self.val + arg
...
>>> class Product:
...     def __init__(self, val):                 # Bound methods
...         self.val = val
...     def method(self, arg):
...         return self.val * arg
...
>>> sobject = Sum(2)
>>> pobject = Product(3)
>>> actions = [square, sobject, pobject.method]  # Function, instance, method

>>> for act in actions:                          # All 3 called same way
...     print(act(5))                            # Call any 1-arg callable
...
25
7
15
>>> actions[-1](5)                               # Index, comprehensions, maps
15
>>> [act(5) for act in actions]
[25, 7, 15]
>>> list(map(lambda act: act(5), actions))
[25, 7, 15]

Technically speaking, classes belong in the callable objects category too, but we normally call them to generate instances rather than to do actual work, as shown here:

>>> class Negate:
...     def __init__(self, val):                 # Classes are callables too
...         self.val = -val                      # But called for object, not work
...     def __repr__(self):                      # Instance print format
...         return str(self.val)
...
>>> actions = [square, sobject, pobject.method, Negate]     # Call a class too
>>> for act in actions:
...     print(act(5))
...
25
7
15
-5
>>> [act(5) for act in actions]                     # Runs __repr__ not __str__!
[25, 7, 15, −5]

>>> table = {act(5): act for act in actions}        # 3.0 dict comprehension
>>> for (key, value) in table.items():
...     print('{0:2} => {1}'.format(key, value))    # 2.6/3.0 str.format
...
-5 => <class '__main__.Negate'>
25 => <function square at 0x025D4978>
15 => <bound method Product.method of <__main__.Product object at 0x025D0F90>>
 7 => <__main__.Sum object at 0x025D0F70>

As you can see, bound methods, and Python’s callable objects model in general, are some of the many ways that Python’s design makes for an incredibly flexible language.

You should now understand the method object model. For other examples of bound methods at work, see the upcoming sidebar as well as the prior chapter’s discussion of callback handlers in the section on the method __call__.

Why You Will Care: Bound Methods and Callbacks

Because bound methods automatically pair an instance with a class method function, you can use them anywhere a simple function is expected. One of the most common places you’ll see this idea put to work is in code that registers methods as event callback handlers in the tkinter GUI interface (named Tkinter in Python 2.6). Here’s the simple case:

def handler():
    ...use globals for state...
...
widget = Button(text='spam', command=handler)

To register a handler for button click events, we usually pass a callable object that takes no arguments to the command keyword argument. Function names (and lambdas) work here, and so do class methods, as long as they are bound methods:

class MyWidget:
    def handler(self):
        ...use self.attr for state...
    def makewidgets(self):
        b = Button(text='spam', command=self.handler)

Here, the event handler is self.handler—a bound method object that remembers both self and MyGui.handler. Because self will refer to the original instance when handler is later invoked on events, the method will have access to instance attributes that can retain state between events. With simple functions, state normally must be retained in global variables or enclosing function scopes instead. See also the discussion of __call__ operator overloading in Chapter 29 for another way to make classes compatible with function-based APIs.

Multiple Inheritance: “Mix-in” Classes

Many class-based designs call for combining disparate sets of methods. In a class statement, more than one superclass can be listed in parentheses in the header line. When you do this, you use something called multiple inheritance—the class and its instances inherit names from all the listed superclasses.

When searching for an attribute, Python’s inheritance search traverses all superclasses in the class header from left to right until a match is found. Technically, because any of the superclasses may have superclasses of its own, this search can be a bit more complex for larger class tress:

In classic classes (the default until Python 3.0), the attribute search proceeds depth-first all the way to the top of the inheritance tree, and then from left to right.

In new-style classes (and all classes in 3.0), the attribute search proceeds across by tree levels, in a more breadth-first fashion (see the new-style class discussion in the next chapter).

In either model, though, when a class has multiple superclasses, they are searched from left to right according to the order listed in the class statement header lines.

In general, multiple inheritance is good for modeling objects that belong to more than one set. For instance, a person may be an engineer, a writer, a musician, and so on, and inherit properties from all such sets. With multiple inheritance, objects obtain the union of the behavior in all their superclasses.

Perhaps the most common way multiple inheritance is used is to “mix in” general-purpose methods from superclasses. Such superclasses are usually called mix-in classes—they provide methods you add to application classes by inheritance. In a sense, mix-in classes are similar to modules: they provide packages of methods for use in their client subclasses. Unlike simple functions in modules, though, methods in mix-ins also have access to the self instance, for using state information and other methods. The next section demonstrates one common use case for such tools.

Coding Mix-in Display Classes

As we’ve seen, Python’s default way to print a class instance object isn’t incredibly useful:

>>> class Spam:
...     def __init__(self):                   # No __repr__ or __str__
...         self.data1 = "food"
...
>>> X = Spam()
>>> print(X)                                  # Default: class, address
<__main__.Spam object at 0x00864818>          # Displays "instance" in Python 2.6

As you saw in Chapter 29 when studying operator overloading, you can provide a __str__ or __repr__ method to implement a custom string representation of your own. But, rather than coding one of these in each and every class you wish to print, why not code it once in a general-purpose tool class and inherit it in all your classes?

That’s what mix-ins are for. Defining a display method in a mix-in superclass once enables us to reuse it anywhere we want to see a custom display format. We’ve already seen tools that do related work:

Chapter 27’s AttrDisplay class formatted instance attributes in a generic __str__ method, but it did not climb class trees and was used in single-inheritance mode only.

Chapter 28’s classtree.py module defined functions for climbing and sketching class trees, but it did not display object attributes along the way and was not architected as an inheritable class.

Here, we’re going to revisit these examples’ techniques and expand upon them to code a set of three mix-in classes that serve as generic display tools for listing instance attributes, inherited attributes, and attributes on all objects in a class tree. We’ll also use our tools in multiple-inheritance mode and deploy coding techniques that make classes better suited to use as generic tools.

Listing instance attributes with __dict__

Let’s get started with the simple case—listing attributes attached to an instance. The following class, coded in the file lister.py, defines a mix-in called ListInstance that overloads the __str__ method for all classes that include it in their header lines. Because this is coded as a class, ListInstance is a generic tool whose formatting logic can be used for instances of any subclass:

# File lister.py

class ListInstance:
    """
    Mix-in class that provides a formatted print() or str() of
    instances via inheritance of __str__, coded here; displays
    instance attrs only; self is the instance of lowest class;
    uses __X names to avoid clashing with client's attrs
    """
    def __str__(self):
        return '<Instance of %s, address %s:\n%s>' % (
                           self.__class__.__name__,         # My class's name
                           id(self),                        # My address
                           self.__attrnames())              # name=value list
    def __attrnames(self):
        result = ''
        for attr in sorted(self.__dict__):                  # Instance attr dict
            result += '\tname %s=%s\n' % (attr, self.__dict__ [attr])
        return result

ListInstance uses some previously explored tricks to extract the instance’s class name and attributes:

Each instance has a built-in __class__ attribute that references the class from which it was created, and each class has a __name__ attribute that references the name in the header, so the expression self.__class__.__name__ fetches the name of an instance’s class.

This class does most of its work by simply scanning the instance’s attribute dictionary (remember, it’s exported in __dict__) to build up a string showing the names and values of all instance attributes. The dictionary’s keys are sorted to finesse any ordering differences across Python releases.

In these respects, ListInstance is similar to Chapter 27’s attribute display; in fact, it’s largely just a variation on a theme. Our class here uses two additional techniques, though:

It displays the instance’s memory address by calling the id built-function, which returns any object’s address (by definition, a unique object identifier, which will be useful in later mutations of this code).

It uses the pseudoprivate naming pattern for its worker method: __attrnames. As we learned earlier in his chapter, Python automatically localizes any such name to its enclosing class by expanding the attribute name to include the class name (in this case, it becomes _ListInstance__attrnames). This holds true for both class attributes (like methods) and instance attributes attached to self. This behavior is useful in a general tool like this, as it ensures that its names don’t clash with any names used in its client subclasses.

Because ListInstance defines a __str__ operator overloading method, instances derived from this class display their attributes automatically when printed, giving a bit more information than a simple address. Here is the class in action, in single-inheritance mode (this code works the same in both Python 3.0 and 2.6):

>>> from lister import ListInstance
>>> class Spam(ListInstance):                    # Inherit a __str__ method
...     def __init__(self):
...         self.data1 = 'food'
...
>>> x = Spam()
>>> print(x)                                     # print() and str() run __str__
<Instance of Spam, address 40240880:
        name data1=food
>

You can also fetch the listing output as a string without printing it with str, and interactive echoes still use the default format:

>>> str(x)
'<Instance of Spam, address 40240880:\n\tname data1=food\n>'
>>> x                                            # The __repr__ still is a default
<__main__.Spam object at 0x026606F0>

The ListInstance class is useful for any classes you write—even classes that already have one or more superclasses. This is where multiple inheritance comes in handy: by adding ListInstance to the list of superclasses in a class header (i.e., mixing it in), you get its __str__ “for free” while still inheriting from the existing superclass(es). The file testmixin.py demonstrates:

# File testmixin.py

from lister import *                  # Get lister tool classes

class Super:
    def __init__(self):               # Superclass __init__
        self.data1 = 'spam'           # Create instance attrs
    def ham(self):
        pass

class Sub(Super, ListInstance):       # Mix in ham and a __str__
    def __init__(self):               # listers have access to self
        Super.__init__(self)
        self.data2 = 'eggs'           # More instance attrs
        self.data3 = 42
    def spam(self):                   # Define another method here
        pass

if __name__ == '__main__':
    X = Sub()
    print(X)                          # Run mixed-in __str__

Here, Sub inherits names from both Super and ListInstance; it’s a composite of its own names and names in both its superclasses. When you make a Sub instance and print it, you automatically get the custom representation mixed in from ListInstance (in this case, this script’s output is the same under both Python 3.0 and 2.6, except for object addresses):

C:\misc> C:\python30\python testmixin.py
<Instance of Sub, address 40962576:
        name data1=spam
        name data2=eggs
        name data3=42
>

ListInstance works in any class it’s mixed into because self refers to an instance of the subclass that pulls this class in, whatever that may be. In a sense, mix-in classes are the class equivalent of modules—packages of methods useful in a variety of clients. For example, here is Lister working again in single-inheritance mode on a different class’s instances, with import and attributes set outside the class:

>>> import lister
>>> class C(lister.ListInstance): pass
...
>>> x = C()
>>> x.a = 1; x.b = 2; x.c = 3
>>> print(x)
<Instance of C, address 40961776:
        name a=1
        name b=2
        name c=3
>

Besides the utility they provide, mix-ins optimize code maintenance, like all classes do. For example, if you later decide to extend ListInstance’s __str__ to also print all the class attributes that an instance inherits, you’re safe; because it’s an inherited method, changing __str__ automatically updates the display of each subclass that imports the class and mixes it in. Since it’s now officially “later,” let’s move on to the next section to see what such an extension might look like.

Listing inherited attributes with dir

As it is, our Lister mix-in displays instance attributes only (i.e., names attached to the instance object itself). It’s trivial to extend the class to display all the attributes accessible from an instance, though—both its own and those it inherits from its classes. The trick is to use the dir built-in function instead of scanning the instance’s __dict__ dictionary; the latter holds instance attributes only, but the former also collects all inherited attributes in Python 2.2 and later.

The following mutation codes this scheme; I’ve renamed it to facilitate simple testing, but if this were to replace the original version, all existing clients would pick up the new display automatically:

# File lister.py, continued

class ListInherited:
    """
    Use dir() to collect both instance attrs and names
    inherited from its classes; Python 3.0 shows more
    names than 2.6 because of the implied object superclass
    in the new-style class model; getattr() fetches inherited
    names not in self.__dict__; use __str__, not __repr__,
    or else this loops when printing bound methods!
    """
    def __str__(self):
        return '<Instance of %s, address %s:\n%s>' % (
                           self.__class__.__name__,         # My class's name
                           id(self),                        # My address
                           self.__attrnames())              # name=value list
    def __attrnames(self):
        result = ''
        for attr in dir(self):                              # Instance dir()
            if attr[:2] == '__' and attr[-2:] == '__':      # Skip internals
                result += '\tname %s=<>\n' % attr
            else:
                result += '\tname %s=%s\n' % (attr, getattr(self, attr))
        return result

Notice that this code skips __X__ names’ values; most of these are internal names that we don’t generally care about in a generic listing like this. This version also must use the getattr built-in function to fetch attributes by name string instead of using instance attribute dictionary indexing—getattr employs the inheritance search protocol, and some of the names we’re listing here are not stored on the instance itself.

To test the new version, change the testmixin.py file to use this new class instead:

class Sub(Super, ListInherited):                            # Mix in a __str__

This file’s output varies per release. In Python 2.6, we get the following; notice the name mangling at work in the lister’s method name (I shortened its full value display to fit on this page):

C:\misc> c:\python26\python testmixin.py
<Instance of Sub, address 40073136:
        name _ListInherited__attrnames=<bound method Sub.__attrnames of <...more...>>
        name __doc__=<>
        name __init__=<>
        name __module__=<>
        name __str__=<>
        name data1=spam
        name data2=eggs
        name data3=42
        name ham=<bound method Sub.ham of <__main__.Sub instance at 0x026377B0>>
        name spam=<bound method Sub.spam of <__main__.Sub instance at 0x026377B0>>
>

In Python 3.0, more attributes are displayed because all classes are “new-style” and inherit names from the implied object superclass (more on this in Chapter 31). Because so many names are inherited from the default superclass, I’ve omitted many here; run this on your own for the full listing:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python testmixin.py
<Instance of Sub, address 40831792:
        name _ListInherited__attrnames=<bound method Sub.__attrnames of <...more...>>
        name __class__=<>
        name __delattr__=<>
        name __dict__=<>
        name __doc__=<>
        name __eq__=<>
        ...more names omitted...
        name __repr__=<>
        name __setattr__=<>
        name __sizeof__=<>
        name __str__=<>
        name __subclasshook__=<>
        name __weakref__=<>
        name data1=spam
        name data2=eggs
        name data3=42
        name ham=<bound method Sub.ham of <__main__.Sub object at 0x026F0B30>>
        name spam=<bound method Sub.spam of <__main__.Sub object at 0x026F0B30>>
>

One caution here—now that we’re displaying inherited methods too, we have to use __str__ instead of __repr__ to overload printing. With __repr__, this code will loop—displaying the value of a method triggers the __repr__ of the method’s class, in order to display the class. That is, if the lister’s __repr__ tries to display a method, displaying the method’s class will trigger the lister’s __repr__ again. Subtle, but true! Change __str__ to __repr__ here to see this for yourself. If you must use __repr__ in such a context, you can avoid the loops by using isinstance to compare the type of attribute values against types.MethodType in the standard library, to know which items to skip.

Listing attributes per object in class trees

Let’s code one last extension. As it is, our lister doesn’t tell us which class an inherited name comes from. As we saw in the classtree.py example near the end of Chapter 28, though, it’s straightforward to climb class inheritance trees in code. The following mix-in class makes use of this same technique to display attributes grouped by the classes they live in—it sketches the full class tree, displaying attributes attached to each object along the way. It does so by traversing the inheritance tree from an instance’s __class__ to its class, and then from the class’s __bases__ to all superclasses recursively, scanning object __dicts__s along the way:

# File lister.py, continued

class ListTree:
    """
    Mix-in that returns an __str__ trace of the entire class
    tree and all its objects' attrs at and above self;
    run by print(), str() returns constructed string;
    uses __X attr names to avoid impacting clients;
    uses generator expr to recurse to superclasses;
    uses str.format() to make substitutions clearer
    """
    def __str__(self):
        self.__visited = {}
        return '<Instance of {0}, address {1}:\n{2}{3}>'.format(
                           self.__class__.__name__,
                           id(self),
                           self.__attrnames(self, 0),
                           self.__listclass(self.__class__, 4))

    def __listclass(self, aClass, indent):
        dots = '.' * indent
        if aClass in self.__visited:
            return '\n{0}<Class {1}:, address {2}: (see above)>\n'.format(
                           dots,
                           aClass.__name__,
                           id(aClass))
        else:
            self.__visited[aClass] = True
            genabove = (self.__listclass(c, indent+4) for c in aClass.__bases__)
            return '\n{0}<Class {1}, address {2}:\n{3}{4}{5}>\n'.format(
                           dots,
                           aClass.__name__,
                           id(aClass),
                           self.__attrnames(aClass, indent),
                           ''.join(genabove),
                           dots)

    def __attrnames(self, obj, indent):
        spaces = ' ' * (indent + 4)
        result = ''
        for attr in sorted(obj.__dict__):
            if attr.startswith('__') and attr.endswith('__'):
                result += spaces + '{0}=<>\n'.format(attr)
            else:
                result += spaces + '{0}={1}\n'.format(attr, getattr(obj, attr))
        return result

Note the use of a generator expression to direct the recursive calls for superclasses; it’s activated by the nested string join method. Also see how this version uses the Python 3.0 and 2.6 string format method instead of % formatting expressions, to make substitutions clearer; when many substitutions are applied like this, explicit argument numbers may make the code easier to decipher. In short, in this version we exchange the first of the following lines for the second:

        return '<Instance of %s, address %s:\n%s%s>' % (...)          # Expression
        return '<Instance of {0}, address {1}:\n{2}{3}>'.format(...)  # Method

Now, change testmixin.py to inherit from this new class again to test:

class Sub(Super, ListTree):         # Mix in a __str__

The file’s tree-sketcher output in Python 2.6 is then as follows:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python testmixin.py
<Instance of Sub, address 40728496:
    _ListTree__visited={}
    data1=spam
    data2=eggs
    data3=42

....<Class Sub, address 40701168:
        __doc__=<>
        __init__=<>
        __module__=<>
        spam=<unbound method Sub.spam>

........<Class Super, address 40701120:
            __doc__=<>
            __init__=<>
            __module__=<>
            ham=<unbound method Super.ham>
........>

........<Class ListTree, address 40700688:
            _ListTree__attrnames=<unbound method ListTree.__attrnames>
            _ListTree__listclass=<unbound method ListTree.__listclass>
            __doc__=<>
            __module__=<>
            __str__=<>
........>
....>
>

Notice in this output how methods are unbound now under 2.6, because we fetch them from classes directly, instead of from instances. Also observe how the lister’s __visited table has its name mangled in the instance’s attribute dictionary; unless we’re very unlucky, this won’t clash with other data there.

Under Python 3.0, we get extra attributes and superclasses again. Notice that unbound methods are simple functions in 3.0, as described in an earlier note in this chapter (and that again, I’ve deleted most built-in attributes in object to save space here; run this on your own for the complete listing):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python testmixin.py
<Instance of Sub, address 40635216:
    _ListTree__visited={}
    data1=spam
    data2=eggs
    data3=42

....<Class Sub, address 40914752:
        __doc__=<>
        __init__=<>
        __module__=<>
        spam=<function spam at 0x026D53D8>

........<Class Super, address 40829952:
            __dict__=<>
            __doc__=<>
            __init__=<>
            __module__=<>
            __weakref__=<>
            ham=<function ham at 0x026D5228>

............<Class object, address 505114624:
                __class__=<>
                __delattr__=<>
                __doc__=<>
                __eq__=<>
                ...more omitted...
                __repr__=<>
                __setattr__=<>
                __sizeof__=<>
                __str__=<>
                __subclasshook__=<>
............>
........>

........<Class ListTree, address 40829496:
            _ListTree__attrnames=<function __attrnames at 0x026D5660>
            _ListTree__listclass=<function __listclass at 0x026D56A8>
            __dict__=<>
            __doc__=<>
            __module__=<>
            __str__=<>
            __weakref__=<>

............<Class object:, address 505114624: (see above)>
........>
....>
>

This version avoids listing the same class object twice by keeping a table of classes visited so far (this is why an object’s id is included—to serve as a key for a previously displayed item). Like the transitive module reloader of Chapter 24, a dictionary works to avoid repeats and cycles here because class objects may be dictionary keys; a set would provide similar functionality.

This version also takes care to avoid large internal objects by skipping __X__ names again. If you comment out the test for these names, their values will display normally. Here’s an excerpt from the output in 2.6 with this temporary change made (it’s much larger in its entirety, and it gets even worse in 3.0, which is why these names are probably better skipped!):

C:\misc> c:\python26\python testmixin.py
...more omitted...

........<Class ListTree, address 40700688:
            _ListTree__attrnames=<unbound method ListTree.__attrnames>
            _ListTree__listclass=<unbound method ListTree.__listclass>
            __doc__=
    Mix-in that returns the __str__ trace of the entire class
    tree and all its objects' attrs at and above self;
    run by print, str returns constructed string;
    uses __X attr names to avoid impacting clients;
    uses generator expr to recurse to superclasses;
    uses str.format() to make substitutions clearer

            __module__=lister
            __str__=<unbound method ListTree.__str__>
........>

For more fun, try mixing this class into something more substantial, like the Button class of Python’s tkinter GUI toolkit module. In general, you’ll want to name ListTree first (leftmost) in a class header, so its __str__ is picked up; Button has one, too, and the leftmost superclass is searched first in multiple inheritance. The output of the following is fairly massive (18K characters), so run this code on your own to see the full listing (and if you’re using Python 2.6, recall that you should use Tkinter for the module name instead of tkinter):

>>> from lister import ListTree
>>> from tkinter import Button                  # Both classes have a __str__
>>> class MyButton(ListTree, Button): pass      # ListTree first: use its __str__
...
>>> B = MyButton(text='spam')
>>> open('savetree.txt', 'w').write(str(B))     # Save to a file for later viewing
18247
>>> print(B)                                    # Print the display here
<Instance of MyButton, address 44355632:
    _ListTree__visited={}
    _name=44355632
    _tclCommands=[]
    ...much more omitted...
>

Of course, there’s much more we could do here (sketching the tree in a GUI might be a natural next step), but we’ll leave further work as a suggested exercise. We’ll also extend this code in the exercises at the end of this part of the book, to list superclass names in parentheses at the start of instance and class displays.

The main point here is that OOP is all about code reuse, and mix-in classes are a powerful example. Like almost everything else in programming, multiple inheritance can be a useful device when applied well. In practice, though, it is an advanced feature and can become complicated if used carelessly or excessively. We’ll revisit this topic as a gotcha at the end of the next chapter. In that chapter, we’ll also meet the new-style class model, which modifies the search order for one special multiple inheritance case. For more ideas, see also Python manuals for the class.mro() new-style class object method, which returns a list giving the class tree search order used by inheritance; this could be used by a class lister to show attribute sources.

Note

Supporting slots: Because they scan instance dictionaries, the ListInstance and ListTree classes presented here don’t directly support attributes stored in slots—a newer and relatively rarely used option we’ll meet in the next chapter, where instance attributes are declared in a __slots__ class attribute. For example, if in textmixin.py we assign __slots__=['data1'] in Super and __slots__=['data3'] in Sub, only the data2 attribute is displayed in the instance by these two lister classes; ListTree also displays data1 and data3, but as attributes of the Super and Sub class objects and with a special format for their values (technically, they are class-level descriptors).

To better support slot attributes in these classes, change the __dict__ scanning loops to also iterate through __slots__ lists using code the next chapter will present, and use the getattr built-in function to fetch values instead of __dict__ indexing (ListTree already does). Since instances inherit only the lowest class’s __slots__, you may also need to come up with a policy when __slots__ lists appear in multiple superclasses (ListTree already displays them as class attributes). ListInherited is immune to all this, because dir results combine both __dict__ names and all classes’ __slots__ names.

Alternatively, as a policy we could simply let our code handle slot-based attributes as it currently does, rather than complicating it for a rare, advanced feature. Slots and normal instance attributes are different kinds of names. We’ll investigate slots further in the next chapter; I omitted addressing them in these examples to avoid a forward dependency (not counting this note, of course!)—not exactly a valid design goal, but reasonable for a book.

Classes Are Objects: Generic Object Factories

Sometimes, class-based designs require objects to be created in response to conditions that can’t be predicted when a program is written. The factory design pattern allows such a deferred approach. Due in large part to Python’s flexibility, factories can take multiple forms, some of which don’t seem special at all.

Because classes are objects, it’s easy to pass them around a program, store them in data structures, and so on. You can also pass classes to functions that generate arbitrary kinds of objects; such functions are sometimes called factories in OOP design circles. Factories are a major undertaking in a strongly typed language such as C++ but are almost trivial to implement in Python. The call syntax we met in Chapter 18 can call any class with any number of constructor arguments in one step to generate any sort of instance:[71]

def factory(aClass, *args):           # Varargs tuple
    return aClass(*args)              # Call aClass (or apply in 2.6 only)

class Spam:
    def doit(self, message):
        print(message)

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job

object1 = factory(Spam)                      # Make a Spam object
object2 = factory(Person, "Guido", "guru")   # Make a Person object

In this code, we define an object generator function called factory. It expects to be passed a class object (any class will do) along with one or more arguments for the class’s constructor. The function uses special “varargs” call syntax to call the function and return an instance.

The rest of the example simply defines two classes and generates instances of both by passing them to the factory function. And that’s the only factory function you’ll ever need to write in Python; it works for any class and any constructor arguments.

One possible improvement worth noting is that to support keyword arguments in constructor calls, the factory can collect them with a **args argument and pass them along in the class call, too:

def factory(aClass, *args, **kwargs):        # +kwargs dict
    return aClass(*args, **kwargs)           # Call aClass

By now, you should know that everything is an “object” in Python, including things like classes, which are just compiler input in languages like C++. However, as mentioned at the start of this part of the book, only objects derived from classes are OOP objects in Python.

Why Factories?

So what good is the factory function (besides providing an excuse to illustrate class objects in this book)? Unfortunately, it’s difficult to show applications of this design pattern without listing much more code than we have space for here. In general, though, such a factory might allow code to be insulated from the details of dynamically configured object construction.

For instance, recall the processor example presented in the abstract in Chapter 25, and then again as a composition example in this chapter. It accepts reader and writer objects for processing arbitrary data streams. The original version of this example manually passed in instances of specialized classes like FileWriter and SocketReader to customize the data streams being processed; later, we passed in hardcoded file, stream, and formatter objects. In a more dynamic scenario, external devices such as configuration files or GUIs might be used to configure the streams.

In such a dynamic world, we might not be able to hardcode the creation of stream interface objects in our scripts, but might instead create them at runtime according to the contents of a configuration file.

For example, the file might simply give the string name of a stream class to be imported from a module, plus an optional constructor call argument. Factory-style functions or code might come in handy here because they would allow us to fetch and pass in classes that are not hardcoded in our program ahead of time. Indeed, those classes might not even have existed at all when we wrote our code:

classname = ...parse from config file...
classarg  = ...parse from config file...

import streamtypes                           # Customizable code
aclass = getattr(streamtypes, classname)     # Fetch from module
reader = factory(aclass, classarg)           # Or aclass(classarg)
processor(reader, ...)

Here, the getattr built-in is again used to fetch a module attribute given a string name (it’s like saying obj.attr, but attr is a string). Because this code snippet assumes a single constructor argument, it doesn’t strictly need factory or apply—we could make an instance with just aclass(classarg). They may prove more useful in the presence of unknown argument lists, however, and the general factory coding pattern can improve the code’s flexibility.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Multiple inheritance occurs when a class inherits from more than one superclass; it’s useful for mixing together multiple packages of class-based code. The left-to-right order in class statement headers determines the order of attribute searches.

Delegation involves wrapping an object in a proxy class, which adds extra behavior and passes other operations to the wrapped object. The proxy retains the interface of the wrapped object.

Composition is a technique whereby a controller class embeds and directs a number of objects, and provides an interface all its own; it’s a way to build up larger structures with classes.

Bound methods combine an instance and a method function; you can call them without passing in an instance object explicitly because the original instance is still available.

Pseudoprivate attributes (whose names begin with two leading underscores: __X) are used to localize names to the enclosing class. This includes both class attributes like methods defined inside the class, and self instance attributes assigned inside the class. Such names are expanded to include the class name, which makes them unique.

[69] This tends to scare people with a C++ background unnecessarily. In Python, it’s even possible to change or completely delete a class method at runtime. On the other hand, almost nobody ever does this in practical programs. As a scripting language, Python is more about enabling than restricting. Also, recall from our discussion of operator overloading in Chapter 29 that __getattr__ and __setattr__ can be used to emulate privacy, but are generally not used for this purpose in practice. More on this when we code a more realistic privacy decorator Chapter 38.

[70] See the discussion of static and class methods in Chapter 31 for an optional exception to this rule. Like bound methods, static methods can masquerade as basic functions because they do not expect instances when called. Python supports three kinds of class methods—instance, static, and class—and 3.0 allows simple functions in classes, too.

[71] Actually, this syntax can invoke any callable object, including functions, classes, and methods. Hence, the factory function here can also run any callable object, not just a class (despite the argument name). Also, as we learned in Chapter 18, Python 2.6 has an alternative to aClass(*args): the apply(aClass, args) built-in call, which has been removed in Python 3.0 because of its redundancy and limitations.

Chapter 31. Advanced Class Topics

This chapter concludes our look at OOP in Python by presenting a few more advanced class-related topics: we will survey subclassing built-in types, “new-style” class changes and extensions, static and class methods, function decorators, and more.

As we’ve seen, Python’s OOP model is, at its core, very simple, and some of the topics presented in this chapter are so advanced and optional that you may not encounter them very often in your Python applications-programming career. In the interest of completeness, though, we’ll round out our discussion of classes with a brief look at these advanced tools for OOP work.

As usual, because this is the last chapter in this part of the book, it ends with a section on class-related “gotchas,” and the set of lab exercises for this part. I encourage you to work through the exercises to help cement the ideas we’ve studied here. I also suggest working on or studying larger OOP Python projects as a supplement to this book. As with much in computing, the benefits of OOP tend to become more apparent with practice.

Note

Content note: This chapter collects advanced class topics, but some are even too advanced for this chapter to cover well. Topics such as properties, descriptors, decorators, and metaclasses are only briefly mentioned here, and are covered more fully in the final part of this book. Be sure to look ahead for more complete examples and extended coverage of some of the subjects that fall into this chapter’s category.

Extending Built-in Types

Besides implementing new kinds of objects, classes are sometimes used to extend the functionality of Python’s built-in types to support more exotic data structures. For instance, to add queue insert and delete methods to lists, you can code classes that wrap (embed) a list object and export insert and delete methods that process the list specially, like the delegation technique we studied in Chapter 30. As of Python 2.2, you can also use inheritance to specialize built-in types. The next two sections show both techniques in action.

Extending Types by Embedding

Remember those set functions we wrote in Chapters 16 and 18? Here’s what they look like brought back to life as a Python class. The following example (the file setwrapper.py) implements a new set object type by moving some of the set functions to methods and adding some basic operator overloading. For the most part, this class just wraps a Python list with extra set operations. But because it’s a class, it also supports multiple instances and customization by inheritance in subclasses. Unlike our earlier functions, using classes here allows us to make multiple self-contained set objects with preset data and behavior, rather than passing lists into functions manually:

class Set:
   def __init__(self, value = []):    # Constructor
       self.data = []                 # Manages a list
       self.concat(value)

   def intersect(self, other):        # other is any sequence
       res = []                       # self is the subject
       for x in self.data:
           if x in other:             # Pick common items
               res.append(x)
       return Set(res)                # Return a new Set

   def union(self, other):            # other is any sequence
       res = self.data[:]             # Copy of my list
       for x in other:                # Add items in other
           if not x in res:
               res.append(x)
       return Set(res)

   def concat(self, value):           # value: list, Set...
       for x in value:                # Removes duplicates
          if not x in self.data:
               self.data.append(x)

   def __len__(self):          return len(self.data)            # len(self)
   def __getitem__(self, key): return self.data[key]            # self[i]
   def __and__(self, other):   return self.intersect(other)     # self & other
   def __or__(self, other):    return self.union(other)         # self | other
   def __repr__(self):         return 'Set:' + repr(self.data)  # print()

To use this class, we make instances, call methods, and run defined operators as usual:

x = Set([1, 3, 5, 7])
print(x.union(Set([1, 4, 7])))       # prints Set:[1, 3, 5, 7, 4]
print(x | Set([1, 4, 6]))            # prints Set:[1, 3, 5, 7, 4, 6]

Overloading operations such as indexing enables instances of our Set class to masquerade as real lists. Because you will interact with and extend this class in an exercise at the end of this chapter, I won’t say much more about this code until Appendix B.

Extending Types by Subclassing

Beginning with Python 2.2, all the built-in types in the language can now be subclassed directly. Type-conversion functions such as list, str, dict, and tuple have become built-in type names—although transparent to your script, a type-conversion call (e.g., list('spam')) is now really an invocation of a type’s object constructor.

This change allows you to customize or extend the behavior of built-in types with user-defined class statements: simply subclass the new type names to customize them. Instances of your type subclasses can be used anywhere that the original built-in type can appear. For example, suppose you have trouble getting used to the fact that Python list offsets begin at 0 instead of 1. Not to worry—you can always code your own subclass that customizes this core behavior of lists. The file typesubclass.py shows how:

# Subclass built-in list type/class
# Map 1..N to 0..N-1; call back to built-in version.

class MyList(list):
    def __getitem__(self, offset):
        print('(indexing %s at %s)' % (self, offset))
        return list.__getitem__(self, offset - 1)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    print(list('abc'))
    x = MyList('abc')               # __init__ inherited from list
    print(x)                        # __repr__ inherited from list

    print(x[1])                     # MyList.__getitem__
    print(x[3])                     # Customizes list superclass method

    x.append('spam'); print(x)      # Attributes from list superclass
    x.reverse();      print(x)

In this file, the MyList subclass extends the built-in list’s __getitem__ indexing method only to map indexes 1 to N back to the required 0 to N−1. All it really does is decrement the submitted index and call back to the superclass’s version of indexing, but it’s enough to do the trick:

% python typesubclass.py
['a', 'b', 'c']
['a', 'b', 'c']
(indexing ['a', 'b', 'c'] at 1)
a
(indexing ['a', 'b', 'c'] at 3)
c
['a', 'b', 'c', 'spam']
['spam', 'c', 'b', 'a']

This output also includes tracing text the class prints on indexing. Of course, whether changing indexing this way is a good idea in general is another issue—users of your MyList class may very well be confused by such a core departure from Python sequence behavior. The ability to customize built-in types this way can be a powerful asset, though.

For instance, this coding pattern gives rise to an alternative way to code a set—as a subclass of the built-in list type, rather than a standalone class that manages an embedded list object, as shown earlier in this section. As we learned in Chapter 5, Python today comes with a powerful built-in set object, along with literal and comprehension syntax for making new sets. Coding one yourself, though, is still a great way to learn about type subclassing in general.

The following class, coded in the file setsubclass.py, customizes lists to add just methods and operators related to set processing. Because all other behavior is inherited from the built-in list superclass, this makes for a shorter and simpler alternative:

class Set(list):
    def __init__(self, value = []):      # Constructor
        list.__init__([])                # Customizes list
        self.concat(value)               # Copies mutable defaults

    def intersect(self, other):          # other is any sequence
        res = []                         # self is the subject
        for x in self:
            if x in other:               # Pick common items
                res.append(x)
        return Set(res)                  # Return a new Set

    def union(self, other):              # other is any sequence
        res = Set(self)                  # Copy me and my list
        res.concat(other)
        return res

    def concat(self, value):             # value: list, Set . . .
        for x in value:                  # Removes duplicates
            if not x in self:
                self.append(x)

    def __and__(self, other): return self.intersect(other)
    def __or__(self, other):  return self.union(other)
    def __repr__(self):       return 'Set:' + list.__repr__(self)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    x = Set([1,3,5,7])
    y = Set([2,1,4,5,6])
    print(x, y, len(x))
    print(x.intersect(y), y.union(x))
    print(x & y, x | y)
    x.reverse(); print(x)

Here is the output of the self-test code at the end of this file. Because subclassing core types is an advanced feature, I’ll omit further details here, but I invite you to trace through these results in the code to study its behavior:

% python setsubclass.py
Set:[1, 3, 5, 7] Set:[2, 1, 4, 5, 6] 4
Set:[1, 5] Set:[2, 1, 4, 5, 6, 3, 7]
Set:[1, 5] Set:[1, 3, 5, 7, 2, 4, 6]
Set:[7, 5, 3, 1]

There are more efficient ways to implement sets with dictionaries in Python, which replace the linear scans in the set implementations shown here with dictionary index operations (hashing) and so run much quicker. (For more details, see Programming Python.) If you’re interested in sets, also take another look at the set object type we explored in Chapter 5; this type provides extensive set operations as built-in tools. Set implementations are fun to experiment with, but they are no longer strictly required in Python today.

For another type subclassing example, see the implementation of the bool type in Python 2.3 and later. As mentioned earlier in the book, bool is a subclass of int with two instances (True and False) that behave like the integers 1 and 0 but inherit custom string-representation methods that display their names.

The “New-Style” Class Model

In Release 2.2, Python introduced a new flavor of classes, known as “new-style” classes; classes following the original model became known as “classic classes” when compared to the new kind. In 3.0 the class story has merged, but it remains split for Python 2.X users:

As of Python 3.0, all classes are automatically what we used to call “new-style,” whether they explicitly inherit from object or not. All classes inherit from object, whether implicitly or explicitly, and all objects are instances of object.

In Python 2.6 and earlier, classes must explicitly inherit from object (or another built-in type) to be considered “new-style” and obtain all new-style features.

Because all classes are automatically new-style in 3.0, the features of new-style classes are simply normal class features. I’ve opted to keep their descriptions in this section separate, however, in deference to users of Python 2.X code—classes in such code acquire new-style features only when they are derived from object.

In other words, when Python 3.0 users see descriptions of “new-style” features in this section, they should take them to be descriptions of existing features of their classes. For 2.6 readers, these are a set of optional extensions.

In Python 2.6 and earlier, the only syntactic difference for new-style classes is that they are derived from either a built-in type, such as list, or a special built-in class known as object. The built-in name object is provided to serve as a superclass for new-style classes if no other built-in type is appropriate to use:

class newstyle(object):
    ...normal code...

Any class derived from object, or any other built-in type, is automatically treated as a new-style class. As long as a built-in type is somewhere in the superclass tree, the new class is treated as a new-style class. Classes not derived from built-ins such as object are considered classic.

New-style classes are only slightly different from classic classes, and the ways in which they differ are irrelevant to the vast majority of Python users. Moreover, the classic class model still available in 2.6 works exactly as it has for almost two decades.

In fact, new-style classes are almost completely backward compatible with classic classes in syntax and behavior; they mostly just add a few advanced new features. However, because they modify a handful of class behaviors, they had to be introduced as a distinct tool so as to avoid impacting any existing code that depends on the prior behaviors. For example, some subtle differences, such as diamond pattern inheritance search and the behavior of built-in operations with managed attribute methods such as __getattr__, can cause some legacy code to fail if left unchanged.

The next two sections provide overviews of the ways the new-style classes differ and the new tools they provide. Again, because all classes are new-style today, these topics represent changes to Python 2.X readers but simply additional advanced class topics to Python 3.0 readers.

New-Style Class Extensions

Beyond the changes described in the prior section (which, frankly, may be too academic and obscure to matter to many readers of this book), new-style classes provide a handful of more advanced class tools that have more direct and practical application. The following sections provide an overview of each of these additional features, available for new-style class in Python 2.6 and all classes in Python 3.0.

Instance Slots

By assigning a sequence of string attribute names to a special __slots__ class attribute, it is possible for a new-style class to both limit the set of legal attributes that instances of the class will have and optimize memory and speed performance.

This special attribute is typically set by assigning a sequence of string names to the variable __slots__ at the top level of a class statement: only those names in the __slots__ list can be assigned as instance attributes. However, like all names in Python, instance attribute names must still be assigned before they can be referenced, even if they’re listed in __slots__. For example:

>>> class limiter(object):
...     __slots__ = ['age', 'name', 'job']
...
>>> x = limiter()
>>> x.age                                           # Must assign before use
AttributeError: age

>>> x.age = 40
>>> x.age
40
>>> x.ape = 1000                                    # Illegal: not in __slots__
AttributeError: 'limiter' object has no attribute 'ape'

Slots are something of a break with Python’s dynamic nature, which dictates that any name may be created by assignment. However, this feature is envisioned as both a way to catch “typo” errors like this (assignments to illegal attribute names not in __slots__ are detected), as well as an optimization mechanism. Allocating a namespace dictionary for every instance object can become expensive in terms of memory if many instances are created and only a few attributes are required. To save space and speed execution (to a degree that can vary per program), instead of allocating a dictionary for each instance, slot attributes are stored sequentially for quicker lookup.

Slots and generic code

In fact, some instances with slots may not have a __dict__ attribute dictionary at all, which can make some metaprograms more complex (including some coded in this book). Tools that generically list attributes or access attributes by string name, for example, must be careful to use more storage-neutral tools than __dict__, such as the getattr, setattr, and dir built-in functions, which apply to attributes based on either __dict__ or __slots__ storage. In some cases, both attribute sources may need to be queried for completeness.

For example, when slots are used, instances do not normally have an attribute dictionary—Python uses the class descriptors feature covered in Chapter 37 to allocate space for slot attributes in the instance instead. Only names in the slots list can be assigned to instances, but slot-based attributes can still be fetched and set by name using generic tools. In Python 3.0 (and in 2.6 for classes derived from object):

>>> class C:
...     __slots__ = ['a', 'b']           # __slots__ means no __dict__ by default
...
>>> X = C()
>>> X.a = 1
>>> X.a
1
>>> X.__dict__
AttributeError: 'C' object has no attribute '__dict__'
>>> getattr(X, 'a')
1
>>> setattr(X, 'b', 2)                   # But getattr() and setattr() still work
>>> X.b
2
>>> 'a' in dir(X)                        # And dir() finds slot attributes too
True
>>> 'b' in dir(X)
True

Without an attribute namespaces dictionary, it’s not possible to assign new names to instances that are not names in the slots list:

>>> class D:
...     __slots__ = ['a', 'b']
...     def __init__(self): self.d = 4   # Cannot add new names if no __dict__
...
>>> X = D()
AttributeError: 'D' object has no attribute 'd'

However, extra attributes can still be accommodated by including __dict__ in __slots__, in order to allow for an attribute namespace dictionary. In this case, both storage mechanisms are used, but generic tools such as getattr allow us to treat them as a single set of attributes:

>>> class D:
...     __slots__ = ['a', 'b', '__dict__']    # List __dict__ to include one too
...     c = 3                                 # Class attrs work normally
...     def __init__(self): self.d = 4        # d put in __dict__, a in __slots__
...
>>> X = D()
>>> X.d
4
>>> X.__dict__                   # Some objects have both __dict__ and __slots__
{'d': 4}                         # getattr() can fetch either type of attr
>>> X.__slots__
['a', 'b', '__dict__']
>>> X.c
3
>>> X.a                          # All instance attrs undefined until assigned
AttributeError: a
>>> X.a = 1
>>> getattr(X, 'a',), getattr(X, 'c'), getattr(X, 'd')
(1, 3, 4)

Code that wishes to list just all instance attributes generically, though, may still need to allow for both storage forms, since dir also returns inherited attributes (this relies on dictionary iterators to collect keys):

>>> for attr in list(X.__dict__) + X.__slots__:
...     print(attr, '=>', getattr(X, attr))

d => 4
a => 1
b => 2
__dict__ => {'d': 4}

Since either can be omitted, this is more correctly coded as follows (getattr allows for defaults):

>>> for attr in list(getattr(X, '__dict__', [])) + getattr(X, '__slots__', []):
...     print(attr, '=>', getattr(X, attr))


d => 4
a => 1
b => 2
__dict__ => {'d': 4}

Multiple __slot__ lists in superclasses

Note, however, that this code addresses only slot names in the lowest __slots__ attribute inherited by an instance. If multiple classes in a class tree have their own __slots__ attributes, generic programs must develop other policies for listing attributes (e.g., classifying slot names as attributes of classes, not instances).

Slot declarations can appear in multiple classes in a class tree, but they are subject to a number of constraints that are somewhat difficult to rationalize unless you understand the implementation of slots as class-level descriptors (a tool we’ll study in detail in the last part of this book):

If a subclass inherits from a superclass without a __slots__, the __dict__ attribute of the superclass will always be accessible, making a __slots__ in the subclass meaningless.

If a class defines the same slot name as a superclass, the version of the name defined by the superclass slot will be accessible only by fetching its descriptor directly from the superclass.

Because the meaning of a __slots__ declaration is limited to the class in which it appears, subclasses will have a __dict__ unless they also define a __slots__.

In terms of listing instance attributes generically, slots in multiple classes might require manual class tree climbs, dir usage, or a policy that treats slot names as a different category of names altogether:

>>> class E:
...     __slots__ = ['c', 'd']            # Superclass has slots
...
>>> class D(E):
...     __slots__ = ['a', '__dict__']     # So does its subclass
...
>>> X = D()
>>> X.a = 1; X.b = 2; X.c = 3             # The instance is the union
>>> X.a, X.c
(1, 3)

>>> E.__slots__                           # But slots are not concatenated
['c', 'd']
>>> D.__slots__
['a', '__dict__']
>>> X.__slots__                           # Instance inherits *lowest* __slots__
['a', '__dict__']
>>> X.__dict__                            # And has its own an attr dict
{'b': 2}

>>> for attr in list(getattr(X, '__dict__', [])) + getattr(X, '__slots__', []):
...     print(attr, '=>', getattr(X, attr))
...
b => 2                                    # Superclass slots missed!
a => 1
__dict__ => {'b': 2}

>>> dir(X)                                # dir() includes all slot names
[...many names omitted... 'a', 'b', 'c', 'd']

When such generality is possible, slots are probably best treated as class attributes, rather than trying to mold them to appear the same as normal instance attributes. For more on slots in general, see the Python standard manual set. Also watch for an example that allows for attributes based on both __slots__ and __dict__ storage in the Private decorator discussion of Chapter 38.

For a prime example of why generic programs may need to care about slots, see the lister.py display mix-in classes example in the multiple inheritance section of the prior chapter; a note there describes the example’s slot concerns. In such a tool that attempts to list attributes generically, slot usage requires either extra code or the implementation of policies regarding the handling of slot-based attributes in general.

Class Properties

A mechanism known as properties provides another way for new-style classes to define automatically called methods for access or assignment to instance attributes. At least for specific attributes, this feature is an alternative to many current uses of the __getattr__ and __setattr__ overloading methods we studied in Chapter 29. Properties have a similar effect to these two methods, but they incur an extra method call only for accesses to names that require dynamic computation. Properties (and slots) are based on a new notion of attribute descriptors, which is too advanced for us to cover here.

In short, a property is a type of object assigned to a class attribute name. A property is generated by calling the property built-in with three methods (handlers for get, set, and delete operations), as well as a docstring; if any argument is passed as None or omitted, that operation is not supported. Properties are typically assigned at the top level of a class statement [e.g., name = property(...)]. When thus assigned, accesses to the class attribute itself (e.g., obj.name) are automatically routed to one of the accessor methods passed into the property. For example, the __getattr__ method allows classes to intercept undefined attribute references:

>>> class classic:
...     def __getattr__(self, name):
...         if name == 'age':
...             return 40
...         else:
...             raise AttributeError
...
>>> x = classic()
>>> x.age                                         # Runs __getattr__
40
>>> x.name                                        # Runs __getattr__
AttributeError

Here is the same example, coded with properties instead (note that properties are available for all classes but require the new-style object derivation in 2.6 to work properly for intercepting attribute assignments):

>>> class newprops(object):
...     def getage(self):
...         return 40
...     age = property(getage, None, None, None)  # get, set, del, docs
...
>>> x = newprops()
>>> x.age                                         # Runs getage
40
>>> x.name                                        # Normal fetch
AttributeError: newprops instance has no attribute 'name'

For some coding tasks, properties can be less complex and quicker to run than the traditional techniques. For example, when we add attribute assignment support, properties become more attractive—there’s less code to type, and no extra method calls are incurred for assignments to attributes we don’t wish to compute dynamically:

>>> class newprops(object):
...     def getage(self):
...         return 40
...     def setage(self, value):
...         print('set age:', value)
...         self._age = value
...     age = property(getage, setage, None, None)
...
>>> x = newprops()
>>> x.age                                         # Runs getage
40
>>> x.age = 42                                    # Runs setage
set age: 42
>>> x._age                                        # Normal fetch; no getage call
42
>>> x.job = 'trainer'                             # Normal assign; no setage call
>>> x.job                                         # Normal fetch; no getage call
'trainer'

The equivalent classic class incurs extra method calls for assignments to attributes not being managed and needs to route attribute assignments through the attribute dictionary (or, for new-style classes, to the object superclass’s __setattr__) to avoid loops:

>>> class classic:
...     def __getattr__(self, name):              # On undefined reference
...         if name == 'age':
...             return 40
...         else:
...             raise AttributeError
...     def __setattr__(self, name, value):       # On all assignments
...         print('set:', name, value)
...         if name == 'age':
...             self.__dict__['_age'] = value
...         else:
...             self.__dict__[name] = value
...
>>> x = classic()
>>> x.age                                         # Runs __getattr__
40
>>> x.age = 41                                    # Runs __setattr__
set: age 41
>>> x._age                                        # Defined: no __getattr__ call
41
>>> x.job = 'trainer'                             # Runs __setattr__ again
set: job trainer
>>> x.job                                         # Defined: no __getattr__ call
'trainer'

Properties seem like a win for this simple example. However, some applications of __getattr__ and __setattr__ may still require more dynamic or generic interfaces than properties directly provide. For example, in many cases, the set of attributes to be supported cannot be determined when the class is coded, and may not even exist in any tangible form (e.g., when delegating arbitrary method references to a wrapped/embedded object generically). In such cases, a generic __getattr__ or a __setattr__ attribute handler with a passed-in attribute name may be preferable. Because such generic handlers can also handle simpler cases, properties are often an optional extension.

For more details on both options, stay tuned for Chapter 37 in the final part of this book. As we’ll see there, it’s also possible to code properties using function decorator syntax, a topic introduced later in this chapter.

__getattribute__ and Descriptors

The __getattribute__ method, available for new-style classes only, allows a class to intercept all attribute references, not just undefined references, like __getattr__. It is also somewhat trickier to use than __getattr__: it is prone to loops, much like __setattr__, but in different ways.

In addition to properties and operator overloading methods, Python supports the notion of attribute descriptors—classes with __get__ and __set__ methods, assigned to class attributes and inherited by instances, that intercept read and write accesses to specific attributes. Descriptors are in a sense a more general form of properties; in fact, properties are a simplified way to define a specific type of descriptor, one that runs functions on access. Descriptors are also used to implement the slots feature we met earlier.

Because properties, __getattribute__, and descriptors are somewhat advanced topics, we’ll defer the rest of their coverage, as well as more on properties, to Chapter 37 in the final part of this book.

Metaclasses

Most of the changes and feature additions of new-style classes integrate with the notion of subclassable types mentioned earlier in this chapter, because subclassable types and new-style classes were introduced in conjunction with a merging of the type/class dichotomy in Python 2.2 and beyond. As we’ve seen, in 3.0, this merging is complete: classes are now types, and types are classes.

Along with these changes, Python also grew a more coherent protocol for coding metaclasses, which are classes that subclass the type object and intercept class creation calls. As such, they provide a well-defined hook for management and augmentation of class objects. They are also an advanced topic that is optional for most Python programmers, so we’ll postpone further details here. We’ll meet metaclasses briefly later in this chapter in conjunction with class decorators, and we’ll explore them in full detail in Chapter 39, in the final part of this book.

Static and Class Methods

As of Python 2.2, it is possible to define two kinds of methods within a class that can be called without an instance: static methods work roughly like simple instance-less functions inside a class, and class methods are passed a class instead of an instance. Although this feature was added in conjunction with the new-style classes discussed in the prior sections, static and class methods work for classic classes too.

To enable these method modes, special built-in functions called staticmethod and classmethod must be called within the class, or invoked with the decoration syntax we’ll meet later in this chapter. In Python 3.0, instance-less methods called only through a class name do not require a staticmethod declaration, but such methods called through instances do.

Why the Special Methods?

As we’ve learned, a class method is normally passed an instance object in its first argument, to serve as the implied subject of the method call. Today, though, there are two ways to modify this model. Before I explain what they are, I should explain why this might matter to you.

Sometimes, programs need to process data associated with classes instead of instances. Consider keeping track of the number of instances created from a class, or maintaining a list of all of a class’s instances that are currently in memory. This type of information and its processing are associated with the class rather than its instances. That is, the information is usually stored on the class itself and processed in the absence of any instance.

For such tasks, simple functions coded outside a class can often suffice—because they can access class attributes through the class name, they have access to class data and never require access to an instance. However, to better associate such code with a class, and to allow such processing to be customized with inheritance as usual, it would be better to code these types of functions inside the class itself. To make this work, we need methods in a class that are not passed, and do not expect, a self instance argument.

Python supports such goals with the notion of static methods—simple functions with no self argument that are nested in a class and are designed to work on class attributes instead of instance attributes. Static methods never receive an automatic self argument, whether called through a class or an instance. They usually keep track of information that spans all instances, rather than providing behavior for instances.

Although less commonly used, Python also supports the notion of class methods—methods of a class that are passed a class object in their first argument instead of an instance, regardless of whether they are called through an instance or a class. Such methods can access class data through their self class argument even if called through an instance. Normal methods (now known in formal circles as instance methods) still receive a subject instance when called; static and class methods do not.

Static Methods in 2.6 and 3.0

The concept of static methods is the same in both Python 2.6 and 3.0, but its implementation requirements have evolved somewhat in Python 3.0. Since this book covers both versions, I need to explain the differences in the two underlying models before we get to the code.

Really, we already began this story in the preceding chapter, when we explored the notion of unbound methods. Recall that both Python 2.6 and 3.0 always pass an instance to a method that is called through an instance. However, Python 3.0 treats methods fetched directly from a class differently than 2.6:

In Python 2.6, fetching a method from a class produces an unbound method, which cannot be called without manually passing an instance.

In Python 3.0, fetching a method from a class produces a simple function, which can be called normally with no instance present.

In other words, Python 2.6 class methods always require an instance to be passed in, whether they are called through an instance or a class. By contrast, in Python 3.0 we are required to pass an instance to a method only if the method expects one—methods without a self instance argument can be called through the class without passing an instance. That is, 3.0 allows simple functions in a class, as long as they do not expect and are not passed an instance argument. The net effect is that:

In Python 2.6, we must always declare a method as static in order to call it without an instance, whether it is called through a class or an instance.

In Python 3.0, we need not declare such methods as static if they will be called through a class only, but we must do so in order to call them through an instance.

To illustrate, suppose we want to use class attributes to count how many instances are generated from a class. The following file, spam.py, makes a first attempt—its class has a counter stored as a class attribute, a constructor that bumps up the counter by one each time a new instance is created, and a method that displays the counter’s value. Remember, class attributes are shared by all instances. Therefore, storing the counter in the class object itself ensures that it effectively spans all instances:

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances = Spam.numInstances + 1
    def printNumInstances():
        print("Number of instances created: ", Spam.numInstances)

The printNumInstances method is designed to process class data, not instance data—it’s about all the instances, not any one in particular. Because of that, we want to be able to call it without having to pass an instance. Indeed, we don’t want to make an instance to fetch the number of instances, because this would change the number of instances we’re trying to fetch! In other words, we want a self-less “static” method.

Whether this code works or not, though, depends on which Python you use, and which way you call the method—through the class or through an instance. In 2.6 (and 2.X in general), calls to a self-less method function through both the class and instances fail (I’ve omitted some error text here for space):

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> from spam import Spam
>>> a = Spam()                   # Cannot call unbound class methods in 2.6
>>> b = Spam()                   # Methods expect a self object by default
>>> c = Spam()

>>> Spam.printNumInstances()
TypeError: unbound method printNumInstances() must be called with Spam instance
as first argument (got nothing instead)
>>> a.printNumInstances()
TypeError: printNumInstances() takes no arguments (1 given)

The problem here is that unbound instance methods aren’t exactly the same as simple functions in 2.6. Even though there are no arguments in the def header, the method still expects an instance to be passed in when it’s called, because the function is associated with a class. In Python 3.0 (and later 3.X releases), calls to self-less methods made through classes work, but calls from instances fail:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> from spam import Spam
>>> a = Spam()                       # Can call functions in class in 3.0
>>> b = Spam()                       # Calls through instances still pass a self
>>> c = Spam()

>>> Spam.printNumInstances()         # Differs in 3.0
Number of instances created:  3
>>> a.printNumInstances()
TypeError: printNumInstances() takes no arguments (1 given)

That is, calls to instance-less methods like printNumInstances made through the class fail in Python 2.6 but work in Python 3.0. On the other hand, calls made through an instance fail in both Pythons, because an instance is automatically passed to a method that does not have an argument to receive it:

Spam.printNumInstances()             # Fails in 2.6, works in 3.0
instance.printNumInstances()         # Fails in both 2.6 and 3.0

If you’re able to use 3.0 and stick with calling self-less methods through classes only, you already have a static method feature. However, to allow self-less methods to be called through classes in 2.6 and through instances in both 2.6 and 3.0, you need to either adopt other designs or be able to somehow mark such methods as special. Let’s look at both options in turn.

Static Method Alternatives

Short of marking a self-less method as special, there are a few different coding structures that can be tried. If you want to call functions that access class members without an instance, perhaps the simplest idea is to just make them simple functions outside the class, not class methods. This way, an instance isn’t expected in the call. For example, the following mutation of spam.py works the same in Python 3.0 and 2.6 (albeit displaying extra parentheses in 2.6 for its print statement):

def printNumInstances():
    print("Number of instances created: ", Spam.numInstances)

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances = Spam.numInstances + 1

>>> import spam
>>> a = spam.Spam()
>>> b = spam.Spam()
>>> c = spam.Spam()
>>> spam.printNumInstances()           # But function may be too far removed
Number of instances created:  3        # And cannot be changed via inheritance
>>> spam.Spam.numInstances
3

Because the class name is accessible to the simple function as a global variable, this works fine. Also, note that the name of the function becomes global, but only to this single module; it will not clash with names in other files of the program.

Prior to static methods in Python, this structure was the general prescription. Because Python already provides modules as a namespace-partitioning tool, one could argue that there’s not typically any need to package functions in classes unless they implement object behavior. Simple functions within modules like the one here do much of what instance-less class methods could, and are already associated with the class because they live in the same module.

Unfortunately, this approach is still less than ideal. For one thing, it adds to this file’s scope an extra name that is used only for processing a single class. For another, the function is much less directly associated with the class; in fact, its definition could be hundreds of lines away. Perhaps worse, simple functions like this cannot be customized by inheritance, since they live outside a class’s namespace: subclasses cannot directly replace or extend such a function by redefining it.

We might try to make this example work in a version-neutral way by using a normal method and always calling it through (or with) an instance, as usual:

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances = Spam.numInstances + 1
    def printNumInstances(self):
        print("Number of instances created: ", Spam.numInstances)

>>> from spam import Spam
>>> a, b, c = Spam(), Spam(), Spam()
>>> a.printNumInstances()
Number of instances created:  3
>>> Spam.printNumInstances(a)
Number of instances created:  3
>>> Spam().printNumInstances()         # But fetching counter changes counter!
Number of instances created:  4

Unfortunately, as mentioned earlier, such an approach is completely unworkable if we don’t have an instance available, and making an instance changes the class data, as illustrated in the last line here. A better solution would be to somehow mark a method inside a class as never requiring an instance. The next section shows how.

Using Static and Class Methods

Today, there is another option for coding simple functions associated with a class that may be called through either the class or its instances. As of Python 2.2, we can code classes with static and class methods, neither of which requires an instance argument to be passed in when invoked. To designate such methods, classes call the built-in functions staticmethod and classmethod, as hinted in the earlier discussion of new-style classes. Both mark a function object as special—i.e., as requiring no instance if static and requiring a class argument if a class method. For example:

class Methods:
    def imeth(self, x):            # Normal instance method: passed a self
        print(self, x)

    def smeth(x):                  # Static: no instance passed
        print(x)

    def cmeth(cls, x):             # Class: gets class, not instance
        print(cls, x)

    smeth = staticmethod(smeth)    # Make smeth a static method
    cmeth = classmethod(cmeth)     # Make cmeth a class method

Notice how the last two assignments in this code simply reassign the method names smeth and cmeth. Attributes are created and changed by any assignment in a class statement, so these final assignments simply overwrite the assignments made earlier by the defs.

Technically, Python now supports three kinds of class-related methods: instance, static, and class. Moreover, Python 3.0 extends this model by also allowing simple functions in a class to serve the role of static methods without extra protocol, when called through a class.

Instance methods are the normal (and default) case that we’ve seen in this book. An instance method must always be called with an instance object. When you call it through an instance, Python passes the instance to the first (leftmost) argument automatically; when you call it through a class, you must pass along the instance manually (for simplicity, I’ve omitted some class imports in interactive sessions like this one):

>>> obj = Methods()                # Make an instance

>>> obj.imeth(1)                   # Normal method, call through instance
<__main__.Methods object...> 1     # Becomes imeth(obj, 1)

>>> Methods.imeth(obj, 2)          # Normal method, call through class
<__main__.Methods object...> 2     # Instance passed explicitly

By contrast, static methods are called without an instance argument. Unlike simple functions outside a class, their names are local to the scopes of the classes in which they are defined, and they may be looked up by inheritance. Instance-less functions can be called through a class normally in Python 3.0, but never by default in 2.6. Using the staticmethod built-in allows such methods to also be called through an instance in 3.0 and through both a class and an instance in Python 2.6 (the first of these works in 3.0 without staticmethod, but the second does not):

>>> Methods.smeth(3)               # Static method, call through class
3                                  # No instance passed or expected

>>> obj.smeth(4)                   # Static method, call through instance
4                                  # Instance not passed

Class methods are similar, but Python automatically passes the class (not an instance) in to a class method’s first (leftmost) argument, whether it is called through a class or an instance:

>>> Methods.cmeth(5)               # Class method, call through class
<class '__main__.Methods'> 5       # Becomes cmeth(Methods, 5)

>>> obj.cmeth(6)                   # Class method, call through instance
<class '__main__.Methods'> 6       # Becomes cmeth(Methods, 6)

Counting Instances with Static Methods

Now, given these built-ins, here is the static method equivalent of this section’s instance-counting example—it marks the method as special, so it will never be passed an instance automatically:

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0                         # Use static method for class data
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances += 1
    def printNumInstances():
        print("Number of instances:", Spam.numInstances)
    printNumInstances = staticmethod(printNumInstances)

Using the static method built-in, our code now allows the self-less method to be called through the class or any instance of it, in both Python 2.6 and 3.0:

>>> a = Spam()
>>> b = Spam()
>>> c = Spam()
>>> Spam.printNumInstances()                 # Call as simple function
Number of instances: 3
>>> a.printNumInstances()                    # Instance argument not passed
Number of instances: 3

Compared to simply moving printNumInstances outside the class, as prescribed earlier, this version requires an extra staticmethod call; however, it localizes the function name in the class scope (so it won’t clash with other names in the module), moves the function code closer to where it is used (inside the class statement), and allows subclasses to customize the static method with inheritance—a more convenient approach than importing functions from the files in which superclasses are coded. The following subclass and new testing session illustrate:

class Sub(Spam):
    def printNumInstances():                 # Override a static method
        print("Extra stuff...")              # But call back to original
        Spam.printNumInstances()
    printNumInstances = staticmethod(printNumInstances)

>>> a = Sub()
>>> b = Sub()
>>> a.printNumInstances()                    # Call from subclass instance
Extra stuff...
Number of instances: 2
>>> Sub.printNumInstances()                  # Call from subclass itself
Extra stuff...
Number of instances: 2
>>> Spam.printNumInstances()
Number of instances: 2

Moreover, classes can inherit the static method without redefining it—it is run without an instance, regardless of where it is defined in a class tree:

>>> class Other(Spam): pass                  # Inherit static method verbatim

>>> c = Other()
>>> c.printNumInstances()
Number of instances: 3

Counting Instances with Class Methods

Interestingly, a class method can do similar work here—the following has the same behavior as the static method version listed earlier, but it uses a class method that receives the instance’s class in its first argument. Rather than hardcoding the class name, the class method uses the automatically passed class object generically:

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0                         # Use class method instead of static
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances += 1
    def printNumInstances(cls):
        print("Number of instances:", cls.numInstances)
    printNumInstances = classmethod(printNumInstances)

This class is used in the same way as the prior versions, but its printNumInstances method receives the class, not the instance, when called from both the class and an instance:

>>> a, b = Spam(), Spam()
>>> a.printNumInstances()                    # Passes class to first argument
Number of instances: 2
>>> Spam.printNumInstances()                 # Also passes class to first argument
Number of instances: 2

When using class methods, though, keep in mind that they receive the most specific (i.e., lowest) class of the call’s subject. This has some subtle implications when trying to update class data through the passed-in class. For example, if in module test.py we subclass to customize as before, augment Spam.printNumInstances to also display its cls argument, and start a new testing session:

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0                         # Trace class passed in
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances += 1
    def printNumInstances(cls):
        print("Number of instances:", cls.numInstances, cls)
    printNumInstances = classmethod(printNumInstances)

class Sub(Spam):
    def printNumInstances(cls):              # Override a class method
        print("Extra stuff...", cls)         # But call back to original
        Spam.printNumInstances()
    printNumInstances = classmethod(printNumInstances)

class Other(Spam): pass                      # Inherit class method verbatim

the lowest class is passed in whenever a class method is run, even for subclasses that have no class methods of their own:

>>> x, y = Sub(), Spam()
>>> x.printNumInstances()                    # Call from subclass instance
Extra stuff... <class 'test.Sub'>
Number of instances: 2 <class 'test.Spam'>
>>> Sub.printNumInstances()                  # Call from subclass itself
Extra stuff... <class 'test.Sub'>
Number of instances: 2 <class 'test.Spam'>
>>> y.printNumInstances()
Number of instances: 2 <class 'test.Spam'>

In the first call here, a class method call is made through an instance of the Sub subclass, and Python passes the lowest class, Sub, to the class method. All is well in this case—since Sub’s redefinition of the method calls the Spam superclass’s version explicitly, the superclass method in Spam receives itself in its first argument. But watch what happens for an object that simply inherits the class method:

>>> z = Other()
>>> z.printNumInstances()
Number of instances: 3 <class 'test.Other'>

This last call here passes Other to Spam’s class method. This works in this example because fetching the counter finds it in Spam by inheritance. If this method tried to assign to the passed class’s data, though, it would update Other, not Spam! In this specific case, Spam is probably better off hardcoding its own class name to update its data, rather than relying on the passed-in class argument.

Counting instances per class with class methods

In fact, because class methods always receive the lowest class in an instance’s tree:

Static methods and explicit class names may be a better solution for processing data local to a class.

Class methods may be better suited to processing data that may differ for each class in a hierarchy.

Code that needs to manage per-class instance counters, for example, might be best off leveraging class methods. In the following, the top-level superclass uses a class method to manage state information that varies for and is stored on each class in the tree—similar in spirit to the way instance methods manage state information in class instances:

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0
    def count(cls):                    # Per-class instance counters
        cls.numInstances += 1          # cls is lowest class above instance
    def __init__(self):
        self.count()                   # Passes self.__class__ to count
    count = classmethod(count)

class Sub(Spam):
    numInstances = 0
    def __init__(self):                # Redefines __init__
        Spam.__init__(self)

class Other(Spam):                     # Inherits __init__
    numInstances = 0

>>> x = Spam()
>>> y1, y2 = Sub(), Sub()
>>> z1, z2, z3 = Other(), Other(), Other()
>>> x.numInstances, y1.numInstances, z1.numInstances
(1, 2, 3)
>>> Spam.numInstances, Sub.numInstances, Other.numInstances
(1, 2, 3)

Static and class methods have additional advanced roles, which we will finesse here; see other resources for more use cases. In recent Python versions, though, the static and class method designations have become even simpler with the advent of function decoration syntax—a way to apply one function to another that has roles well beyond the static method use case that was its motivation. This syntax also allows us to augment classes in Python 2.6 and 3.0—to initialize data like the numInstances counter in the last example, for instance. The next section explains how.

Decorators and Metaclasses: Part 1

Because the staticmethod call technique described in the prior section initially seemed obscure to some users, a feature was eventually added to make the operation simpler. Function decorators provide a way to specify special operation modes for functions, by wrapping them in an extra layer of logic implemented as another function.

Function decorators turn out to be general tools: they are useful for adding many types of logic to functions besides the static method use case. For instance, they may be used to augment functions with code that logs calls made to them, checks the types of passed arguments during debugging, and so on. In some ways, function decorators are similar to the delegation design pattern we explored in Chapter 30, but they are designed to augment a specific function or method call, not an entire object interface.

Python provides some built-in function decorators for operations such as marking static methods, but programmers can also code arbitrary decorators of their own. Although they are not strictly tied to classes, user-defined function decorators often are coded as classes to save the original functions, along with other data, as state information. There’s also a more recent related extension available in Python 2.6 and 3.0: class decorators are directly tied to the class model, and their roles overlap with metaclasses.

Function Decorator Basics

Syntactically, a function decorator is a sort of runtime declaration about the function that follows. A function decorator is coded on a line by itself just before the def statement that defines a function or method. It consists of the @ symbol, followed by what we call a metafunction—a function (or other callable object) that manages another function. Static methods today, for example, may be coded with decorator syntax like this:

class C:
   @staticmethod                                 # Decoration syntax
   def meth():
       ...

Internally, this syntax has the same effect as the following (passing the function through the decorator and assigning the result back to the original name):

class C:
   def meth():
       ...
   meth = staticmethod(meth)                     # Rebind name

Decoration rebinds the method name to the decorator’s result. The net effect is that calling the method function’s name later actually triggers the result of its staticmethod decorator first. Because a decorator can return any sort of object, this allows the decorator to insert a layer of logic to be run on every call. The decorator function is free to return either the original function itself, or a new object that saves the original function passed to the decorator to be invoked indirectly after the extra logic layer runs.

With this addition, here’s a better way to code our static method example from the prior section in either Python 2.6 or 3.0 (the classmethod decorator is used the same way):

class Spam:
    numInstances = 0
    def __init__(self):
        Spam.numInstances = Spam.numInstances + 1

    @staticmethod
    def printNumInstances():
        print("Number of instances created: ", Spam.numInstances)

a = Spam()
b = Spam()
c = Spam()
Spam.printNumInstances()      # Calls from both classes and instances work now!
a.printNumInstances()         # Both print "Number of instances created:  3"

Keep in mind that staticmethod is still a built-in function; it may be used in decoration syntax, just because it takes a function as argument and returns a callable. In fact, any such function can be used in this way—even user-defined functions we code ourselves, as the next section explains.

A First Function Decorator Example

Although Python provides a handful of built-in functions that can be used as decorators, we can also write custom decorators of our own. Because of their wide utility, we’re going to devote an entire chapter to coding decorators in the final part of this book. As a quick example, though, let’s look at a simple user-defined decorator at work.

Recall from Chapter 29 that the __call__ operator overloading method implements a function-call interface for class instances. The following code uses this to define a class that saves the decorated function in the instance and catches calls to the original name. Because this is a class, it also has state information (a counter of calls made):

class tracer:
    def __init__(self, func):
        self.calls = 0
        self.func  = func
    def __call__(self, *args):
        self.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (self.calls, self.func.__name__))
        self.func(*args)

@tracer                       # Same as spam = tracer(spam)
def spam(a, b, c):            # Wrap spam in a decorator object
    print(a, b, c)

spam(1, 2, 3)                 # Really calls the tracer wrapper object
spam('a', 'b', 'c')           # Invokes __call__ in class
spam(4, 5, 6)                 # __call__ adds logic and runs original object

Because the spam function is run through the tracer decorator, when the original spam name is called it actually triggers the __call__ method in the class. This method counts and logs the call, and then dispatches it to the original wrapped function. Note how the *name argument syntax is used to pack and unpack the passed-in arguments; because of this, this decorator can be used to wrap any function with any number of positional arguments.

The net effect, again, is to add a layer of logic to the original spam function. Here is the script’s output—the first line comes from the tracer class, and the second comes from the spam function:

call 1 to spam
1 2 3
call 2 to spam
a b c
call 3 to spam
4 5 6

Trace through this example’s code for more insight. As it is, this decorator works for any function that takes positional arguments, but it does not return the decorated function’s result, doesn’t handle keyword arguments, and cannot decorate class method functions (in short, for methods its __call__ would be passed a tracer instance only). As we’ll see in Part VIII, there are a variety of ways to code function decorators, including nested def statements; some of the alternatives are better suited to methods than the version shown here.

Class Decorators and Metaclasses

Function decorators turned out to be so useful that Python 2.6 and 3.0 expanded the model, allowing decorators to be applied to classes as well as functions. In short, class decorators are similar to function decorators, but they are run at the end of a class statement to rebind a class name to a callable. As such, they can be used to either manage classes just after they are created, or insert a layer of wrapper logic to manage instances when they are later created. Symbolically, the code structure:

def decorator(aClass): ...

@decorator
class C: ...

is mapped to the following equivalent:

def decorator(aClass): ...

class C: ...
C = decorator(C)

The class decorator is free to augment the class itself, or return an object that intercepts later instance construction calls. For instance, in the example in the section Counting instances per class with class methods, we could use this hook to automatically augment the classes with instance counters and any other data required:

def count(aClass):
    aClass.numInstances = 0
    return aClass                  # Return class itself, instead of a wrapper

@count
class Spam: ...                    # Same as Spam = count(Spam)

@count
class Sub(Spam): ...               # numInstances = 0 not needed here

@count
class Other(Spam): ...

Metaclasses are a similarly advanced class-based tool whose roles often intersect with those of class decorators. They provide an alternate model, which routes the creation of a class object to a subclass of the top-level type class, at the conclusion of a class statement:

class Meta(type):
    def __new__(meta, classname, supers, classdict): ...

class C(metaclass=Meta): ...

In Python 2.6, the effect is the same, but the coding differs—use a class attribute instead of a keyword argument in the class header:

class C:
    __metaclass__ = Meta
    ...

The metaclass generally redefines the __new__ or __init__ method of the type class, in order to assume control of the creation or initialization of a new class object. The net effect, as with class decorators, is to define code to be run automatically at class creation time. Both schemes are free to augment a class or return an arbitrary object to replace it—a protocol with almost limitless class-based possibilities.

For More Details

Naturally, there’s much more to the decorator and metaclass stories than I’ve shown here. Although they are a general mechanism, decorators and metaclasses are advanced features of interest primarily to tool writers, not application programmers, so we’ll defer additional coverage until the final part of this book:

Chapter 37 shows how to code properties using function decorator syntax.

Chapter 38 has much more on decorators, including more comprehensive examples.

Chapter 39 covers metaclasses, and more on the class and instance management story.

Although these chapters cover advanced topics, they’ll also provide us with a chance to see Python at work in more substantial examples than much of the rest of the book was able to provide.

Class Gotchas

Most class issues can be boiled down to namespace issues (which makes sense, given that classes are just namespaces with a few extra tricks). Some of the topics we’ll cover in this section are more like case studies of advanced class usage than real problems, and one or two of these gotchas have been eased by recent Python releases.

Changing Class Attributes Can Have Side Effects

Theoretically speaking, classes (and class instances) are mutable objects. Like built-in lists and dictionaries, they can be changed in-place by assigning to their attributes—and as with lists and dictionaries, this means that changing a class or instance object may impact multiple references to it.

That’s usually what we want (and is how objects change their state in general), but awareness of this issue becomes especially critical when changing class attributes. Because all instances generated from a class share the class’s namespace, any changes at the class level are reflected in all instances, unless they have their own versions of the changed class attributes.

Because classes, modules, and instances are all just objects with attribute namespaces, you can normally change their attributes at runtime by assignments. Consider the following class. Inside the class body, the assignment to the name a generates an attribute X.a, which lives in the class object at runtime and will be inherited by all of X’s instances:

>>> class X:
...     a = 1       # Class attribute
...
>>> I = X()
>>> I.a             # Inherited by instance
1
>>> X.a
1

So far, so good—this is the normal case. But notice what happens when we change the class attribute dynamically outside the class statement: it also changes the attribute in every object that inherits from the class. Moreover, new instances created from the class during this session or program run also get the dynamically set value, regardless of what the class’s source code says:

>>> X.a = 2         # May change more than X
>>> I.a             # I changes too
2
>>> J = X()         # J inherits from X's runtime values
>>> J.a             # (but assigning to J.a changes a in J, not X or I)
2

Is this a useful feature or a dangerous trap? You be the judge. As we learned in Chapter 26, you can actually get work done by changing class attributes without ever making a single instance; this technique can simulate the use of “records” or “structs” in other languages. As a refresher, consider the following unusual but legal Python program:

class X: pass                       # Make a few attribute namespaces
class Y: pass

X.a = 1                             # Use class attributes as variables
X.b = 2                             # No instances anywhere to be found
X.c = 3
Y.a = X.a + X.b + X.c

for X.i in range(Y.a): print(X.i)   # Prints 0..5

Here, the classes X and Y work like “fileless” modules—namespaces for storing variables we don’t want to clash. This is a perfectly legal Python programming trick, but it’s less appropriate when applied to classes written by others; you can’t always be sure that class attributes you change aren’t critical to the class’s internal behavior. If you’re out to simulate a C struct, you may be better off changing instances than classes, as that way only one object is affected:

class Record: pass
X = Record()
X.name = 'bob'
X.job  = 'Pizza maker'

Changing Mutable Class Attributes Can Have Side Effects, Too

This gotcha is really an extension of the prior. Because class attributes are shared by all instances, if a class attribute references a mutable object, changing that object in-place from any instance impacts all instances at once:

>>> class C:
...     shared = []                 # Class attribute
...     def __init__(self):
...         self.perobj = []        # Instance attribute
...
>>> x = C()                         # Two instances
>>> y = C()                         # Implicitly share class attrs
>>> y.shared, y.perobj
([], [])

>>> x.shared.append('spam')         # Impacts y's view too!
>>> x.perobj.append('spam')         # Impacts x's data only
>>> x.shared, x.perobj
(['spam'], ['spam'])

>>> y.shared, y.perobj              # y sees change made through x
(['spam'], [])
>>> C.shared                        # Stored on class and shared
['spam']

This effect is no different than many we’ve seen in this book already: mutable objects are shared by simple variables, globals are shared by functions, module-level objects are shared by multiple importers, and mutable function arguments are shared by the caller and the callee. All of these are cases of general behavior—multiple references to a mutable object—and all are impacted if the shared object is changed in-place from any reference. Here, this occurs in class attributes shared by all instances via inheritance, but it’s the same phenomenon at work. It may be made more subtle by the different behavior of assignments to instance attributes themselves:

x.shared.append('spam')    # Changes shared object attached to class in-place
x.shared = 'spam'          # Changed or creates instance attribute attached to x

but again, this is not a problem, it’s just something to be aware of; shared mutable class attributes can have many valid uses in Python programs.

Multiple Inheritance: Order Matters

This may be obvious by now, but it’s worth underscoring: if you use multiple inheritance, the order in which superclasses are listed in the class statement header can be critical. Python always searches superclasses from left to right, according to their order in the header line.

For instance, in the multiple inheritance example we studied in Chapter 30, suppose that the Super class implemented a __str__ method, too:

class ListTree:
    def __str__(self): ...

class Super:
    def __str__(self): ...

class Sub(ListTree, Super):    # Get ListTree's __str__ by listing it first

x = Sub()                      # Inheritance searches ListTree before Super

Which class would we inherit it from—ListTree or Super? As inheritance searches proceed from left to right, we would get the method from whichever class is listed first (leftmost) in Sub’s class header. Presumably, we would list ListTree first because its whole purpose is its custom __str__ (indeed, we had to do this in Chapter 30 when mixing this class with a tkinter.Button that had a __str__ of its own).

But now suppose Super and ListTree have their own versions of other same-named attributes, too. If we want one name from Super and another from ListTree, the order in which we list them in the class header won’t help—we will have to override inheritance by manually assigning to the attribute name in the Sub class:

class ListTree:
    def __str__(self): ...
    def other(self): ...

class Super:
    def __str__(self): ...
    def other(self): ...

class Sub(ListTree, Super):    # Get ListTree's __str__ by listing it first
    other = Super.other        # But explicitly pick Super's version of other
    def __init__(self):
        ...

x = Sub()                      # Inheritance searches Sub before ListTree/Super

Here, the assignment to other within the Sub class creates Sub.other—a reference back to the Super.other object. Because it is lower in the tree, Sub.other effectively hides ListTree.other, the attribute that the inheritance search would normally find. Similarly, if we listed Super first in the class header to pick up its other, we would need to select ListTree’s method explicitly:

class Sub(Super, ListTree):               # Get Super's other by order
    __str__ = Lister.__str__              # Explicitly pick Lister.__str__

Multiple inheritance is an advanced tool. Even if you understood the last paragraph, it’s still a good idea to use it sparingly and carefully. Otherwise, the meaning of a name may come to depend on the order in which classes are mixed in an arbitrarily far-removed subclass. (For another example of the technique shown here in action, see the discussion of explicit conflict resolution in The “New-Style” Class Model.)

As a rule of thumb, multiple inheritance works best when your mix-in classes are as self-contained as possible—because they may be used in a variety of contexts, they should not make assumptions about names related to other classes in a tree. The pseudoprivate __X attributes feature we studied in Chapter 30 can help by localizing names that a class relies on owning and limiting the names that your mix-in classes add to the mix. In this example, for instance, if ListTree only means to export its custom __str__, it can name its other method __other to avoid clashing with like-named classes in the tree.

Methods, Classes, and Nested Scopes

This gotcha went away in Python 2.2 with the introduction of nested function scopes, but I’ve retained it here for historical perspective, for readers working with older Python releases, and because it demonstrates what happens to the new nested function scope rules when one layer of the nesting is a class.

Classes introduce local scopes, just as functions do, so the same sorts of scope behavior can happen in a class statement body. Moreover, methods are further nested functions, so the same issues apply. Confusion seems to be especially common when classes are nested.

In the following example (the file nester.py), the generate function returns an instance of the nested Spam class. Within its code, the class name Spam is assigned in the generate function’s local scope. However, in versions of Python prior to 2.2, within the class’s method function the class name Spam is not visible—method has access only to its own local scope, the module surrounding generate, and built-in names:

def generate():                  # Fails prior to Python 2.2, works later
    class Spam:
        count = 1
        def method(self):        # Name Spam not visible:
            print(Spam.count)    # not local (def), global (module), built-in
    return Spam()

generate().method()

C:\python\examples> python nester.py
...error text omitted...
    print(Spam.count)            # Not local (def), global (module), built-in
NameError: Spam

This example works in Python 2.2 and later because the local scopes of all enclosing function defs are automatically visible to nested defs (including nested method defs, as in this example). However, it doesn’t work before 2.2 (we’ll look at some possible solutions momentarily).

Note that even in 2.2 and later, method defs cannot see the local scope of the enclosing class; they can only see the local scopes of enclosing defs. That’s why methods must go through the self instance or the class name to reference methods and other attributes defined in the enclosing class statement. For example, code in the method must use self.count or Spam.count, not just count.

If you’re using a release prior to 2.2, there are a variety of ways to get the preceding example to work. One of the simplest is to move the name Spam out to the enclosing module’s scope with a global declaration. Because method sees global names in the enclosing module, references to Spam will work:

def generate():
    global Spam                 # Force Spam to module scope
    class Spam:
        count = 1
        def method(self):
            print(Spam.count)   # Works: in global (enclosing module)
    return Spam()

generate().method()             # Prints 1

A better alternative would be to restructure the code such that the class Spam is defined at the top level of the module by virtue of its nesting level, rather than using global declarations. The nested method function and the top-level generate will then find Spam in their global scopes:

def generate():
    return Spam()

class Spam:                    # Define at top level of module
    count = 1
    def method(self):
        print(Spam.count)      # Works: in global (enclosing module)

generate().method()

In fact, this approach is recommended for all Python releases—code tends to be simpler in general if you avoid nesting classes and functions.

If you want to get complicated and tricky, you can also get rid of the Spam reference in method altogether by using the special __class__ attribute, which returns an instance’s class object:

def generate():
    class Spam:
        count = 1
        def method(self):
            print(self.__class__.count)      # Works: qualify to get class
    return Spam()

generate().method()

Delegation-Based Classes in 3.0: __getattr__ and built-ins

We met this issue briefly in our class tutorial in Chapter 27 and our delegation coverage in Chapter 30: classes that use the __getattr__ operator overloading method to delegate attribute fetches to wrapped objects will fail in Python 3.0 unless operator overloading methods are redefined in the wrapper class. In Python 3.0 (and 2.6, when new-style classes are used), the names of operator overloading methods implicitly fetched by built-in operations are not routed through generic attribute-interception methods. The __str__ method used by printing, for example, never invokes __getattr__. Instead, Python 3.0 looks up such names in classes and skips the normal runtime instance lookup mechanism entirely. To work around this, such methods must be redefined in wrapper classes, either by hand, with tools, or by definition in superclasses. We’ll revisit this gotcha in Chapters 37 and 38.

“Overwrapping-itis”

When used well, the code reuse features of OOP make it excel at cutting development time. Sometimes, though, OOP’s abstraction potential can be abused to the point of making code difficult to understand. If classes are layered too deeply, code can become obscure; you may have to search through many classes to discover what an operation does.

For example, I once worked in a C++ shop with thousands of classes (some machine-generated), and up to 15 levels of inheritance. Deciphering method calls in such a complex system was often a monumental task: multiple classes had to be consulted for even the most basic of operations. In fact, the logic of the system was so deeply wrapped that understanding a piece of code in some cases required days of wading through related files.

The most general rule of thumb of Python programming applies here, too: don’t make things complicated unless they truly must be. Wrapping your code in multiple layers of classes to the point of incomprehensibility is always a bad idea. Abstraction is the basis of polymorphism and encapsulation, and it can be a very effective tool when used well. However, you’ll simplify debugging and aid maintainability if you make your class interfaces intuitive, avoid making your code overly abstract, and keep your class hierarchies short and flat unless there is a good reason to do otherwise.

Chapter Summary

This chapter presented a handful of advanced class-related topics, including subclassing built-in types, new-style classes, static methods, and decorators. Most of these are optional extensions to the OOP model in Python, but they may become more useful as you start writing larger object-oriented programs. As mentioned earlier, our discussion of some of the more advanced class tools continues in the final part of this book; be sure to look ahead if you need more details on properties, descriptors, decorators, and metaclasses.

This is the end of the class part of this book, so you’ll find the usual lab exercises at the end of the chapter—be sure to work through them to get some practice coding real classes. In the next chapter, we’ll begin our look at our last core language topic, exceptions. Exceptions are Python’s mechanism for communicating errors and other conditions to your code. This is a relatively lightweight topic, but I’ve saved it for last because exceptions are supposed to be coded as classes today. Before we tackle that final core subject, though, take a look at this chapter’s quiz and the lab exercises.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

You can embed a built-in object in a wrapper class, or subclass the built-in type directly. The latter approach tends to be simpler, as most original behavior is automatically inherited.

Function decorators are generally used to add to an existing function a layer of logic that is run each time the function is called. They can be used to log or count calls to a function, check its argument types, and so on. They are also used to “declare” static methods—simple functions in a class that are not passed an instance when called.

New-style classes are coded by inheriting from the object built-in class (or any other built-in type). In Python 3.0, all classes are new-style automatically, so this derivation is not required; in 2.6, classes with this derivation are new-style and those without it are “classic.”

New-style classes search the diamond pattern of multiple inheritance trees differently—they essentially search breadth-first (across), instead of depth-first (up). New-style classes also change the result of the type built-in for instances and classes, do not run generic attribute fetch methods such as __getattr__ for built-in operation methods, and support a set of advanced extra tools including properties, descriptors, and __slots__ instance attribute lists.

Normal (instance) methods receive a self argument (the implied instance), but static methods do not. Static methods are simple functions nested in class objects. To make a method static, it must either be run through a special built-in function or be decorated with decorator syntax. Python 3.0 allows simple functions in a class to be called through the class without this step, but calls through instances still require static method declaration.

Three seconds. (Or, more accurately: “And the Lord spake, saying, ‘First shalt thou take out the Holy Pin. Then, shalt thou count to three, no more, no less. Three shalt be the number thou shalt count, and the number of the counting shall be three. Four shalt thou not count, nor either count thou two, excepting that thou then proceed to three. Five is right out. Once the number three, being the third number, be reached, then lobbest thou thy Holy Hand Grenade of Antioch towards thy foe, who, being naughty in my sight, shall snuff it.’”)[72]

Chapter 32. Exception Basics

This part of the book deals with exceptions, which are events that can modify the flow of control through a program. In Python, exceptions are triggered automatically on errors, and they can be triggered and intercepted by your code. They are processed by four statements we’ll study in this part, the first of which has two variations (listed separately here) and the last of which was an optional extension until Python 2.6 and 3.0:

try/except

Catch and recover from exceptions raised by Python, or by you.

try/finally

Perform cleanup actions, whether exceptions occur or not.

raise

Trigger an exception manually in your code.

assert

Conditionally trigger an exception in your code.

with/as

Implement context managers in Python 2.6 and 3.0 (optional in 2.5).

This topic was saved until nearly the end of the book because you need to know about classes to code exceptions of your own. With a few exceptions (pun intended), though, you’ll find that exception handling is simple in Python because it’s integrated into the language itself as another high-level tool.

Why Use Exceptions?

In a nutshell, exceptions let us jump out of arbitrarily large chunks of a program. Consider the hypothetical pizza-making robot we discussed earlier in the book. Suppose we took the idea seriously and actually built such a machine. To make a pizza, our culinary automaton would need to execute a plan, which we would implement as a Python program: it would take an order, prepare the dough, add toppings, bake the pie, and so on.

Now, suppose that something goes very wrong during the “bake the pie” step. Perhaps the oven is broken, or perhaps our robot miscalculates its reach and spontaneously combusts. Clearly, we want to be able to jump to code that handles such states quickly. As we have no hope of finishing the pizza task in such unusual cases, we might as well abandon the entire plan.

That’s exactly what exceptions let you do: you can jump to an exception handler in a single step, abandoning all function calls begun since the exception handler was entered. Code in the exception handler can then respond to the raised exception as appropriate (by calling the fire department, for instance!).

One way to think of an exception is as a sort of structured “super go to.” An exception handler (try statement) leaves a marker and executes some code. Somewhere further ahead in the program, an exception is raised that makes Python jump back to that marker, abandoning any active functions that were called after the marker was left. This protocol provides a coherent way to respond to unusual events. Moreover, because Python jumps to the handler statement immediately, your code is simpler—there is usually no need to check status codes after every call to a function that could possibly fail.

Exception Roles

In Python programs, exceptions are typically used for a variety of purposes. Here are some of their most common roles:

Error handling

Python raises exceptions whenever it detects errors in programs at runtime. You can catch and respond to the errors in your code, or ignore the exceptions that are raised. If an error is ignored, Python’s default exception-handling behavior kicks in: it stops the program and prints an error message. If you don’t want this default behavior, code a try statement to catch and recover from the exception—Python will jump to your try handler when the error is detected, and your program will resume execution after the try.

Event notification

Exceptions can also be used to signal valid conditions without you having to pass result flags around a program or test them explicitly. For instance, a search routine might raise an exception on failure, rather than returning an integer result code (and hoping that the code will never be a valid result).

Special-case handling

Sometimes a condition may occur so rarely that it’s hard to justify convoluting your code to handle it. You can often eliminate special-case code by handling unusual cases in exception handlers in higher levels of your program.

Termination actions

As you’ll see, the try/finally statement allows you to guarantee that required closing-time operations will be performed, regardless of the presence or absence of exceptions in your programs.

Unusual control flows

Finally, because exceptions are a sort of high-level “go to,” you can use them as the basis for implementing exotic control flows. For instance, although the language does not explicitly support backtracking, it can be implemented in Python by using exceptions and a bit of support logic to unwind assignments.[73] There is no “go to” statement in Python (thankfully!), but exceptions can sometimes serve similar roles.

We’ll see such typical use cases in action later in this part of the book. For now, let’s get started with a look at Python’s exception-processing tools.

Exceptions: The Short Story

Compared to some other core language topics we’ve met in this book, exceptions are a fairly lightweight tool in Python. Because they are so simple, let’s jump right into some code.

Default Exception Handler

Suppose we write the following function:

>>> def fetcher(obj, index):
...     return obj[index]
...

There’s not much to this function—it simply indexes an object on a passed-in index. In normal operation, it returns the result of a legal index:

>>> x = 'spam'
>>> fetcher(x, 3)                         # Like x[3]
'm'

However, if we ask this function to index off the end of the string, an exception will be triggered when the function tries to run obj[index]. Python detects out-of-bounds indexing for sequences and reports it by raising (triggering) the built-in IndexError exception:

>>> fetcher(x, 4)                         # Default handler - shell interface
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
  File "<stdin>", line 2, in fetcher
IndexError: string index out of range

Because our code does not explicitly catch this exception, it filters back up to the top level of the program and invokes the default exception handler, which simply prints the standard error message. By this point in the book, you’ve probably seen your share of standard error messages. They include the exception that was raised, along with a stack trace—a list of all the lines and functions that were active when the exception occurred.

The error message text here was printed by Python 3.0; it can vary slightly per release, and even per interactive shell. When coding interactively in the basic shell interface, the filename is just “<stdin>,” meaning the standard input stream. When working in the IDLE GUI’s interactive shell, the filename is “<pyshell>”, and source lines are displayed, too. Either way, file line numbers are not very meaningful when there is no file (we’ll see more interesting error messages later in this part of the book):

>>> fetcher(x, 4)                         # Default handler - IDLE GUI interface
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<pyshell#6>", line 1, in <module>
    fetcher(x, 4)
  File "<pyshell#3>", line 2, in fetcher
    return obj[index]
IndexError: string index out of range

In a more realistic program launched outside the interactive prompt, after printing an error message the default handler at the top also terminates the program immediately. That course of action makes sense for simple scripts; errors often should be fatal, and the best you can do when they occur is inspect the standard error message.

Catching Exceptions

Sometimes, this isn’t what you want, though. Server programs, for instance, typically need to remain active even after internal errors. If you don’t want the default exception behavior, wrap the call in a try statement to catch exceptions yourself:

>>> try:
...     fetcher(x, 4)
... except IndexError:                    # Catch and recover
...     print('got exception')
...
got exception
>>>

Now, Python jumps to your handler (the block under the except clause that names the exception raised) automatically when an exception is triggered while the try block is running. When working interactively like this, after the except clause runs, we wind up back at the Python prompt. In a more realistic program, try statements not only catch exceptions, but also recover from them:

>>> def catcher():
...     try:
...         fetcher(x, 4)
...     except IndexError:
...         print('got exception')
...     print('continuing')
...
>>> catcher()
got exception
continuing
>>>

This time, after the exception is caught and handled, the program resumes execution after the entire try statement that caught it—which is why we get the “continuing” message here. We don’t see the standard error message, and the program continues on its way normally.

Raising Exceptions

So far, we’ve been letting Python raise exceptions for us by making mistakes (on purpose this time!), but our scripts can raise exceptions too—that is, exceptions can be raised by Python or by your program, and can be caught or not. To trigger an exception manually, simply run a raise statement. User-triggered exceptions are caught the same way as those Python raises. The following may not be the most useful Python code ever penned, but it makes the point:

>>> try:
...     raise IndexError                  # Trigger exception manually
... except IndexError:
...     print('got exception')
...
got exception

As usual, if they’re not caught, user-triggered exceptions are propagated up to the top-level default exception handler and terminate the program with a standard error message:

>>> raise IndexError
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
IndexError

As we’ll see in the next chapter, the assert statement can be used to trigger exceptions, too—it’s a conditional raise, used mostly for debugging purposes during development:

>>> assert False, 'Nobody expects the Spanish Inquisition!'
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
AssertionError: Nobody expects the Spanish Inquisition!

User-Defined Exceptions

The raise statement introduced in the prior section raises a built-in exception defined in Python’s built-in scope. As you’ll learn later in this part of the book, you can also define new exceptions of your own that are specific to your programs. User-defined exceptions are coded with classes, which inherit from a built-in exception class: usually the class named Exception. Class-based exceptions allow scripts to build exception categories, inherit behavior, and have attached state information:

>>> class Bad(Exception):                 # User-defined exception
...     pass
...
>>> def doomed():
...     raise Bad()                       # Raise an instance
...
>>> try:
...     doomed()
... except Bad:                           # Catch class name
...     print('got Bad')
...
got Bad
>>>

Termination Actions

Finally, try statements can say “finally”—that is, they may include finally blocks. These look like except handlers for exceptions, but the try/finally combination specifies termination actions that always execute “on the way out,” regardless of whether an exception occurs in the try block:

>>> try:
...     fetcher(x, 3)
... finally:                              # Termination actions
...     print('after fetch')
...
'm'
after fetch
>>>

Here, if the try block finishes without an exception, the finally block will run, and the program will resume after the entire try. In this case, this statement seems a bit silly—we might as well have simply typed the print right after a call to the function, and skipped the try altogether:

fetcher(x, 3)
print('after fetch')

There is a problem with coding this way, though: if the function call raises an exception, the print will never be reached. The try/finally combination avoids this pitfall—when an exception does occur in a try block, finally blocks are executed while the program is being unwound:

>>> def after():
...     try:
...         fetcher(x, 4)
...     finally:
...         print('after fetch')
...     print('after try?')
...
>>> after()
after fetch
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
  File "<stdin>", line 3, in after
  File "<stdin>", line 2, in fetcher
IndexError: string index out of range
>>>

Here, we don’t get the “after try?” message because control does not resume after the try/finally block when an exception occurs. Instead, Python jumps back to run the finally action, and then propagates the exception up to a prior handler (in this case, to the default handler at the top). If we change the call inside this function so as not to trigger an exception, the finally code still runs, but the program continues after the try:

>>> def after():
...     try:
...         fetcher(x, 3)
...     finally:
...         print('after fetch')
...     print('after try?')
...
>>> after()
after fetch
after try?
>>>

In practice, try/except combinations are useful for catching and recovering from exceptions, and try/finally combinations come in handy to guarantee that termination actions will fire regardless of any exceptions that may occur in the try block’s code. For instance, you might use try/except to catch errors raised by code that you import from a third-party library, and try/finally to ensure that calls to close files or terminate server connections are always run. We’ll see some such practical examples later in this part of the book.

Although they serve conceptually distinct purposes, as of Python 2.5, we can now mix except and finally clauses in the same try statement—the finally is run on the way out regardless of whether an exception was raised, and regardless of whether the exception was caught by an except clause.

As we’ll learn in the next chapter, Python 2.6 and 3.0 provide an alternative to try/finally when using some types of objects. The with/as statement runs an object’s context management logic to guarantee that termination actions occur:

>>> with open('lumberjack.txt', 'w') as file:        # Always close file on exit
...     file.write('The larch!\n')

Although this option requires fewer lines of code, it’s only applicable when processing certain object types, so try/finally is a more general termination structure. On the other hand, with/as may also run startup actions and supports user-defined context management code.

Why You Will Care: Error Checks

One way to see how exceptions are useful is to compare coding styles in Python and languages without exceptions. For instance, if you want to write robust programs in the C language, you generally have to test return values or status codes after every operation that could possibly go astray, and propagate the results of the tests as your programs run:

doStuff()
{                                 # C program
    if (doFirstThing() == ERROR)  # Detect errors everywhere
        return ERROR;             # even if not handled here
    if (doNextThing() == ERROR)
        return ERROR;
    ...
    return doLastThing();
}

main()
{
    if (doStuff() == ERROR)
        badEnding();
    else
        goodEnding();
}

In fact, realistic C programs often have as much code devoted to error detection as to doing actual work. But in Python, you don’t have to be so methodical (and neurotic!). You can instead wrap arbitrarily vast pieces of a program in exception handlers and simply write the parts that do the actual work, assuming all is well:

def doStuff():        # Python code
    doFirstThing()    # We don't care about exceptions here,
    doNextThing()     # so we don't need to detect them
    ...
    doLastThing()

if __name__ == '__main__':
    try:
        doStuff()     # This is where we care about results,
    except:           # so it's the only place we must check
        badEnding()
    else:
        goodEnding()

Because control jumps immediately to a handler when an exception occurs, there’s no need to instrument all your code to guard for errors. Moreover, because Python detects errors automatically, your code usually doesn’t need to check for errors in the first place. The upshot is that exceptions let you largely ignore the unusual cases and avoid error-checking code.

Chapter Summary

And that is the majority of the exception story; exceptions really are a simple tool.

To summarize, Python exceptions are a high-level control flow device. They may be raised by Python, or by your own programs. In both cases, they may be ignored (to trigger the default error message), or caught by try statements (to be processed by your code). The try statement comes in two logical formats that, as of Python 2.5, can be combined—one that handles exceptions, and one that executes finalization code regardless of whether exceptions occur or not. Python’s raise and assert statements trigger exceptions on demand (both built-ins and new exceptions we define with classes); the with/as statement is an alternative way to ensure that termination actions are carried out for objects that support it.

In the rest of this part of the book, we’ll fill in some of the details about the statements involved, examine the other sorts of clauses that can appear under a try, and discuss class-based exception objects. The next chapter begins our tour by taking a closer look at the statements we introduced here. Before you turn the page, though, here are a few quiz questions to review.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Exception processing is useful for error handling, termination actions, and event notification. It can also simplify the handling of special cases and can be used to implement alternative control flows. In general, exception processing also cuts down on the amount of error-checking code your program may require—because all errors filter up to handlers, you may not need to test the outcome of every operation.

Any uncaught exception eventually filters up to the default exception handler Python provides at the top of your program. This handler prints the familiar error message and shuts down your program.

If you don’t want the default message and shutdown, you can code try/except statements to catch and recover from exceptions that are raised. Once an exception is caught, the exception is terminated and your program continues.

The raise and assert statements can be used to trigger an exception, exactly as if it had been raised by Python itself. In principle, you can also raise an exception by making a programming mistake, but that’s not usually an explicit goal!

The try/finally statement can be used to ensure actions are run after a block of code exits, regardless of whether it raises an exception or not. The with/as statement can also be used to ensure termination actions are run, but only when processing object types that support it.

[73] True backtracking is an advanced topic that is not part of the Python language, so I won’t say much more about it here (even the generator functions and expressions we met in Chapter 20 are not true backtracking—they simply respond to next(G) requests). Roughly, backtracking undoes all computations before it jumps; Python exceptions do not (i.e., variables assigned between the time a try statement is entered and the time an exception is raised are not reset to their prior values). See a book on artificial intelligence or the Prolog or Icon programming languages if you’re curious.

Chapter 33. Exception Coding Details

In the prior chapter we took a quick look at exception-related statements in action. Here, we’re going to dig a bit deeper—this chapter provides a more formal introduction to exception processing syntax in Python. Specifically, we’ll explore the details behind the try, raise, assert, and with statements. As we’ll see, although these statements are mostly straightforward, they offer powerful tools for dealing with exceptions in Python code.

Note

One procedural note up front: The exception story has changed in major ways in recent years. As of Python 2.5, the finally clause can appear in the same try statement as except and else clauses (previously, they could not be combined). Also, as of Python 3.0 and 2.6, the new with context manager statement has become official, and user-defined exceptions must now be coded as class instances, which should inherit from a built-in exception superclass. Moreover, 3.0 sports slightly modified syntax for the raise statement and except clauses. I will focus on the state of exceptions in Python 2.6 and 3.0 in this edition, but because you are still very likely to see the original techniques in code for some time to come, along the way I’ll point out how things have evolved in this domain.

The try/except/else Statement

Now that we’ve seen the basics, it’s time for the details. In the following discussion, I’ll first present try/except/else and try/finally as separate statements, because in versions of Python prior to 2.5 they serve distinct roles and cannot be combined. As mentioned in the preceding note, in Python 2.5 and later except and finally can be mixed in a single try statement; I’ll explain the implications of this change after we’ve explored the two original forms in isolation.

The try is a compound statement; its most complete form is sketched below. It starts with a try header line, followed by a block of (usually) indented statements, then one or more except clauses that identify exceptions to be caught, and an optional else clause at the end. The words try, except, and else are associated by indenting them to the same level (i.e., lining them up vertically). For reference, here’s the general format in Python 3.0:

try:
    <statements>            # Run this main action first
except <name1>:
    <statements>            # Run if name1 is raised during try block
except (name2, name3):
    <statements>            # Run if any of these exceptions occur
except <name4> as <data>:
    <statements>            # Run if name4 is raised, and get instance raised
except:
    <statements>            # Run for all (other) exceptions raised
else:
    <statements>            # Run if no exception was raised during try block

In this statement, the block under the try header represents the main action of the statement—the code you’re trying to run. The except clauses define handlers for exceptions raised during the try block, and the else clause (if coded) provides a handler to be run if no exceptions occur. The <data> entry here has to do with a feature of raise statements and exception classes, which we will discuss later in this chapter.

Here’s how try statements work. When a try statement is entered, Python marks the current program context so it can return to it if an exception occurs. The statements nested under the try header are run first. What happens next depends on whether exceptions are raised while the try block’s statements are running:

If an exception does occur while the try block’s statements are running, Python jumps back to the try and runs the statements under the first except clause that matches the raised exception. Control resumes below the entire try statement after the except block runs (unless the except block raises another exception).

If an exception happens in the try block and no except clause matches, the exception is propagated up to the last matching try statement that was entered in the program or, if it’s the first such statement, to the top level of the process (in which case Python kills the program and prints a default error message).

If no exception occurs while the statements under the try header run, Python runs the statements under the else line (if present), and control then resumes below the entire try statement.

In other words, except clauses catch any exceptions that happen while the try block is running, and the else clause runs only if no exceptions happen while the try block runs.

except clauses are focused exception handlers—they catch exceptions that occur only within the statements in the associated try block. However, as the try block’s statements can call functions coded elsewhere in a program, the source of an exception may be outside the try statement itself. I’ll have more to say about this when we explore try nesting in Chapter 35.

try Statement Clauses

When you write a try statement, a variety of clauses can appear after the try header. Table 33-1 summarizes all the possible forms—you must use at least one. We’ve already met some of these: as you know, except clauses catch exceptions, finally clauses run on the way out, and else clauses run if no exceptions are encountered.

Syntactically, there may be any number of except clauses, but you can code else only if there is at least one except, and there can be only one else and one finally. Through Python 2.4, the finally clause must appear alone (without else or except); the try/finally is really a different statement. As of Python 2.5, however, a finally can appear in the same statement as except and else (more on the ordering rules later in this chapter when we meet the unified try statement).

Table 33-1. try statement clause forms

Clause form

|

Interpretation

except:

|

Catch all (or all other) exception types.

except name:

|

Catch a specific exception only.

except name as value:

|

Catch the listed exception and its instance.

except (name1, name2):

|

Catch any of the listed exceptions.

except (name1, name2) as value:

|

Catch any listed exception and its instance.

else:

|

Run if no exceptions are raised.

finally:

|

Always perform this block.

We’ll explore the entries with the extra as value part when we meet the raise statement. They provide access to the objects that are raised as exceptions.

The first and fourth entries in Table 33-1 are new here:

except clauses that list no exception name (except:) catch all exceptions not previously listed in the try statement.

except clauses that list a set of exceptions in parentheses (except (e1, e2, e3):) catch any of the listed exceptions.

Because Python looks for a match within a given try by inspecting the except clauses from top to bottom, the parenthesized version has the same effect as listing each exception in its own except clause, but you have to code the statement body only once. Here’s an example of multiple except clauses at work, which demonstrates just how specific your handlers can be:

try:
    action()
except NameError:
    ...
except IndexError:
    ...
except KeyError:
    ...
except (AttributeError, TypeError, SyntaxError):
    ...
else:
    ...

In this example, if an exception is raised while the call to the action function is running, Python returns to the try and searches for the first except that names the exception raised. It inspects the except clauses from top to bottom and left to right, and runs the statements under the first one that matches. If none match, the exception is propagated past this try. Note that the else runs only when no exception occurs in action—it does not run when an exception without a matching except is raised.

If you really want a general “catch-all” clause, an empty except does the trick:

try:
    action()
except NameError:
    ...                   # Handle NameError
except IndexError:
    ...                   # Handle IndexError
except:
    ...                   # Handle all other exceptions
else:
    ...                   # Handle the no-exception case

The empty except clause is a sort of wildcard feature—because it catches everything, it allows your handlers to be as general or specific as you like. In some scenarios, this form may be more convenient than listing all possible exceptions in a try. For example, the following catches everything without listing anything:

try:
    action()
except:
    ...                   # Catch all possible exceptions

Empty excepts also raise some design issues, though. Although convenient, they may catch unexpected system exceptions unrelated to your code, and they may inadvertently intercept exceptions meant for another handler. For example, even system exit calls in Python trigger exceptions, and you usually want these to pass. That said, this structure may also catch genuine programming mistakes for you which you probably want to see an error message. We’ll revisit this as a gotcha at the end of this part of the book. For now, I’ll just say “use with care.”

Python 3.0 introduced an alternative that solves one of these problems—catching an exception named Exception has almost the same effect as an empty except, but ignores exceptions related to system exits:

try:
    action()
except Exception:
    ...                   # Catch all possible exceptions, except exits

This has most of the same convenience of the empty except, but also most of the same dangers. We’ll explore how this form works its voodoo in the next chapter, when we study exception classes.

Note

Version skew note: Python 3.0 requires the except E as V: handler clause form listed in Table 33-1 and used in this book, rather than the older except E, V: form. The latter form is still available (but not recommended) in Python 2.6: if used, it’s converted to the former. The change was made to eliminate errors that occur when confusing the older form with two alternate exceptions, properly coded in 2.6 as except (E1, E2):. Because 3.0 supports the as form only, commas in a handler clause are always taken to mean a tuple, regardless of whether parentheses are used or not, and the values are interpreted as alternative exceptions to be caught. This change also modifies the scoping rules: with the new as syntax, the variable V is deleted at the end of the except block.

The try else Clause

The purpose of the else clause is not always immediately obvious to Python newcomers. Without it, though, there is no way to tell (without setting and checking Boolean flags) whether the flow of control has proceeded past a try statement because no exception was raised, or because an exception occurred and was handled:

try:
    ...run code...
except IndexError:
    ...handle exception...
# Did we get here because the try failed or not?

Much like the way else clauses in loops make the exit cause more apparent, the else clause provides syntax in a try that makes what has happened obvious and unambiguous:

try:
    ...run code...
except IndexError:
    ...handle exception...
else:
    ...no exception occurred...

You can almost emulate an else clause by moving its code into the try block:

try:
    ...run code...
    ...no exception occurred...
except IndexError:
    ...handle exception...

This can lead to incorrect exception classifications, though. If the “no exception occurred” action triggers an IndexError, it will register as a failure of the try block and erroneously trigger the exception handler below the try (subtle, but true!). By using an explicit else clause instead, you make the logic more obvious and guarantee that except handlers will run only for real failures in the code you’re wrapping in a try, not for failures in the else case’s action.

Example: Default Behavior

Because the control flow through a program is easier to capture in Python than in English, let’s run some examples that further illustrate exception basics. I’ve mentioned that exceptions not caught by try statements percolate up to the top level of the Python process and run Python’s default exception-handling logic (i.e., Python terminates the running program and prints a standard error message). Let’s look at an example. Running the following module file, bad.py, generates a divide-by-zero exception:

def gobad(x, y):
    return x / y

def gosouth(x):
    print(gobad(x, 0))

gosouth(1)

Because the program ignores the exception it triggers, Python kills the program and prints a message:

% python bad.py
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "bad.py", line 7, in <module>
    gosouth(1)
  File "bad.py", line 5, in gosouth
    print(gobad(x, 0))
  File "bad.py", line 2, in gobad
    return x / y
ZeroDivisionError: int division or modulo by zero

I ran this in a shell window with Python 3.0. The message consists of a stack trace (“Traceback”) and the name of and details about the exception that was raised. The stack trace lists all lines active when the exception occurred, from oldest to newest. Note that because we’re not working at the interactive prompt, in this case the file and line number information is more useful. For example, here we can see that the bad divide happens at the last entry in the trace—line 2 of the file bad.py, a return statement.[74]

Because Python detects and reports all errors at runtime by raising exceptions, exceptions are intimately bound up with the ideas of error handling and debugging in general. If you’ve worked through this book’s examples, you’ve undoubtedly seen an exception or two along the way—even typos usually generate a SyntaxError or other exception when a file is imported or executed (that’s when the compiler is run). By default, you get a useful error display like the one just shown, which helps you track down the problem.

Often, this standard error message is all you need to resolve problems in your code. For more heavy-duty debugging jobs, you can catch exceptions with try statements, or use one of the debugging tools that I introduced in Chapter 3 and will summarize again in Chapter 35 (such as the pdb standard library module).

Example: Catching Built-in Exceptions

Python’s default exception handling is often exactly what you want—especially for code in a top-level script file, an error generally should terminate your program immediately. For many programs, there is no need to be more specific about errors in your code.

Sometimes, though, you’ll want to catch errors and recover from them instead. If you don’t want your program terminated when Python raises an exception, simply catch it by wrapping the program logic in a try. This is an important capability for programs such as network servers, which must keep running persistently. For example, the following code catches and recovers from the TypeError Python raises immediately when you try to concatenate a list and a string (the + operator expects the same sequence type on both sides):

def kaboom(x, y):
    print(x + y)               # Trigger TypeError

try:
    kaboom([0,1,2], "spam")
except TypeError:              # Catch and recover here
    print('Hello world!')
print('resuming here')         # Continue here if exception or not

When the exception occurs in the function kaboom, control jumps to the try statement’s except clause, which prints a message. Since an exception is “dead” after it’s been caught like this, the program continues executing below the try rather than being terminated by Python. In effect, the code processes and clears the error, and your script recovers:

% python kaboom.py
Hello world!
resuming here

Notice that once you’ve caught an error, control resumes at the place where you caught it (i.e., after the try); there is no direct way to go back to the place where the exception occurred (here, in the function kaboom). In a sense, this makes exceptions more like simple jumps than function calls—there is no way to return to the code that triggered the error.

The try/finally Statement

The other flavor of the try statement is a specialization that has to do with finalization actions. If a finally clause is included in a try, Python will always run its block of statements “on the way out” of the try statement, whether an exception occurred while the try block was running or not. Its general form is:

try:
    <statements>               # Run this action first
finally:
    <statements>               # Always run this code on the way out

With this variant, Python begins by running the statement block associated with the try header line. What happens next depends on whether an exception occurs during the try block:

If no exception occurs while the try block is running, Python jumps back to run the finally block and then continues execution past below the try statement.

If an exception does occur during the try block’s run, Python still comes back and runs the finally block, but it then propagates the exception up to a higher try or the top-level default handler; the program does not resume execution below the try statement. That is, the finally block is run even if an exception is raised, but unlike an except, the finally does not terminate the exception—it continues being raised after the finally block runs.

The try/finally form is useful when you want to be completely sure that an action will happen after some code runs, regardless of the exception behavior of the program. In practice, it allows you to specify cleanup actions that always must occur, such as file closes and server disconnects.

Note that the finally clause cannot be used in the same try statement as except and else in Python 2.4 and earlier, so the try/finally is best thought of as a distinct statement form if you are using an older release. In Python 2.5, and later, however, finally can appear in the same statement as except and else, so today there is really a single try statement with many optional clauses (more about this shortly). Whichever version you use, though, the finally clause still serves the same purpose—to specify “cleanup” actions that must always be run, regardless of any exceptions.

Note

As we’ll also see later in this chapter, in Python 2.6 and 3.0, the new with statement and its context managers provide an object-based way to do similar work for exit actions. Unlike finally, this new statement also supports entry actions, but it is limited in scope to objects that implement the context manager protocol.

Example: Coding Termination Actions with try/finally

We saw some simple try/finally examples in the prior chapter. Here’s a more realistic example that illustrates a typical role for this statement:

class MyError(Exception): pass

def stuff(file):
    raise MyError()

file = open('data', 'w')     # Open an output file
try:
    stuff(file)              # Raises exception
finally:
    file.close()             # Always close file to flush output buffers
print('not reached')         # Continue here only if no exception

In this code, we’ve wrapped a call to a file-processing function in a try with a finally clause to make sure that the file is always closed, and thus finalized, whether the function triggers an exception or not. This way, later code can be sure that the file’s output buffer’s content has been flushed from memory to disk. A similar code structure can guarantee that server connections are closed, and so on.

As we learned in Chapter 9, file objects are automatically closed on garbage collection; this is especially useful for temporary files that we don’t assign to variables. However, it’s not always easy to predict when garbage collection will occur, especially in larger programs. The try statement makes file closes more explicit and predictable and pertains to a specific block of code. It ensures that the file will be closed on block exit, regardless of whether an exception occurs or not.

This particular example’s function isn’t all that useful (it just raises an exception), but wrapping calls in try/finally statements is a good way to ensure that your closing-time (i.e., termination) activities always run. Again, Python always runs the code in your finally blocks, regardless of whether an exception happens in the try block.[75]

When the function here raises its exception, the control flow jumps back and runs the finally block to close the file. The exception is then propagated on to either another try or the default top-level handler, which prints the standard error message and shuts down the program; the statement after this try is never reached. If the function here did not raise an exception, the program would still execute the finally block to close the file, but it would then continue below the entire try statement.

Notice that the user-defined exception here is again defined with a class—as we’ll see in the next chapter, exceptions today must all be class instances in both 2.6 and 3.0.

Unified try/except/finally

In all versions of Python prior to Release 2.5 (for its first 15 years of life, more or less), the try statement came in two flavors and was really two separate statements—we could either use a finally to ensure that cleanup code was always run, or write except blocks to catch and recover from specific exceptions and optionally specify an else clause to be run if no exceptions occurred.

That is, the finally clause could not be mixed with except and else. This was partly because of implementation issues, and partly because the meaning of mixing the two seemed obscure—catching and recovering from exceptions seemed a disjoint concept from performing cleanup actions.

In Python 2.5 and later, though (including 2.6 and 3.0, the versions used in this book), the two statements have merged. Today, we can mix finally, except, and else clauses in the same statement. That is, we can now write a statement of this form:

try:                               # Merged form
    main-action
except Exception1:
    handler1
except Exception2:
    handler2
...
else:
    else-block
finally:
    finally-block

The code in this statement’s main-action block is executed first, as usual. If that code raises an exception, all the except blocks are tested, one after another, looking for a match to the exception raised. If the exception raised is Exception1, the handler1 block is executed; if it’s Exception2, handler2 is run, and so on. If no exception is raised, the else-block is executed.

No matter what’s happened previously, the finally-block is executed once the main action block is complete and any raised exceptions have been handled. In fact, the code in the finally-block will be run even if there is an error in an exception handler or the else-block and a new exception is raised.

As always, the finally clause does not end the exception—if an exception is active when the finally-block is executed, it continues to be propagated after the finally-block runs, and control jumps somewhere else in the program (to another try, or to the default top-level handler). If no exception is active when the finally is run, control resumes after the entire try statement.

The net effect is that the finally is always run, regardless of whether:

An exception occurred in the main action and was handled.

An exception occurred in the main action and was not handled.

No exceptions occurred in the main action.

A new exception was triggered in one of the handlers.

Again, the finally serves to specify cleanup actions that must always occur on the way out of the try, regardless of what exceptions have been raised or handled.

Unified try Statement Syntax

When combined like this, the try statement must have either an except or a finally, and the order of its parts must be like this:

try -> except -> else -> finally

where the else and finally are optional, and there may be zero or more except, but there must be at least one except if an else appears. Really, the try statement consists of two parts: excepts with an optional else, and/or the finally.

In fact, it’s more accurate to describe the merged statement’s syntactic form this way (square brackets mean optional and star means zero-or-more here):

try:                               # Format 1
    statements
except [type [as value]]:          # [type [, value]] in Python 2
    statements
[except [type [as value]]:
    statements]*
[else:
    statements]
[finally:
    statements]

try:                               # Format 2
    statements
finally:
    statements

Because of these rules, the else can appear only if there is at least one except, and it’s always possible to mix except and finally, regardless of whether an else appears or not. It’s also possible to mix finally and else, but only if an except appears too (though the except can omit an exception name to catch everything and run a raise statement, described later, to reraise the current exception). If you violate any of these ordering rules, Python will raise a syntax error exception before your code runs.

Combining finally and except by Nesting

Prior to Python 2.5, it is actually possible to combine finally and except clauses in a try by syntactically nesting a try/except in the try block of a try/finally statement (we’ll explore this technique more fully in Chapter 35). In fact, the following has the same effect as the new merged form shown at the start of this section:

try:                               # Nested equivalent to merged form
    try:
        main-action
    except Exception1:
        handler1
    except Exception2:
        handler2
    ...
    else:
        no-error
finally:
    cleanup

Again, the finally block is always run on the way out, regardless of what happened in the main action and regardless of any exception handlers run in the nested try (trace through the four cases listed previously to see how this works the same). Since an else always requires an except, this nested form even sports the same mixing constraints of the unified statement form outlined in the preceding section.

However, this nested equivalent is more obscure and requires more code than the new merged form (one four-character line, at least). Mixing finally into the same statement makes your code easier to write and read, so this is the generally preferred technique today.

Unified try Example

Here’s a demonstration of the merged try statement form at work. The following file, mergedexc.py, codes four common scenarios, with print statements that describe the meaning of each:

sep = '-' * 32 + '\n'
print(sep + 'EXCEPTION RAISED AND CAUGHT')
try:
    x = 'spam'[99]
except IndexError:
    print('except run')
finally:
    print('finally run')
print('after run')


print(sep + 'NO EXCEPTION RAISED')
try:
    x = 'spam'[3]
except IndexError:
    print('except run')
finally:
    print('finally run')
print('after run')


print(sep + 'NO EXCEPTION RAISED, WITH ELSE')
try:
    x = 'spam'[3]
except IndexError:
    print('except run')
else:
    print('else run')
finally:
    print('finally run')
print('after run')


print(sep + 'EXCEPTION RAISED BUT NOT CAUGHT')
try:
    x = 1 / 0
except IndexError:
    print('except run')
finally:
    print('finally run')
print('after run')

When this code is run, the following output is produced in Python 3.0 (actually, its behavior and output are the same in 2.6, because the print calls each print a single item). Trace through the code to see how exception handling produces the output of each of the four tests here:

c:\misc> C:\Python30\python mergedexc.py
--------------------------------
EXCEPTION RAISED AND CAUGHT
except run
finally run
after run
--------------------------------
NO EXCEPTION RAISED
finally run
after run
--------------------------------
NO EXCEPTION RAISED, WITH ELSE
else run
finally run
after run
--------------------------------
EXCEPTION RAISED BUT NOT CAUGHT
finally run
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "mergedexc.py", line 36, in <module>
    x = 1 / 0
ZeroDivisionError: int division or modulo by zero

This example uses built-in operations in the main action to trigger exceptions (or not), and it relies on the fact that Python always checks for errors as code is running. The next section shows how to raise exceptions manually instead.

The raise Statement

To trigger exceptions explicitly, you can code raise statements. Their general form is simple—a raise statement consists of the word raise, optionally followed by the class to be raised or an instance of it:

raise <instance>             # Raise instance of class
raise <class>                # Make and raise instance of class
raise                        # Reraise the most recent exception

As mentioned earlier, exceptions are always instances of classes in Python 2.6 and 3.0. Hence, the first raise form here is the most common—we provide an instance directly, either created before the raise or within the raise statement itself. If we pass a class instead, Python calls the class with no constructor arguments, to create an instance to be raised; this form is equivalent to adding parentheses after the class reference. The last form reraises the most recently raised exception; it’s commonly used in exception handlers to propagate exceptions that have been caught.

To make this clearer, let’s look at some examples. With built-in exceptions, the following two forms are equivalent—both raise an instance of the exception class named, but the first creates the instance implicitly:

raise IndexError             # Class (instance created)
raise IndexError()           # Instance (created in statement)

We can also create the instance ahead of time—because the raise statement accepts any kind of object reference, the following two examples raise IndexError just like the prior two:

exc = IndexError()           # Create instance ahead of time
raise exc

excs = [IndexError, TypeError]
raise excs[0]

When an exception is raised, Python sends the raised instance along with the exception. If a try includes an except name as X: clause, the variable X will be assigned the instance provided in the raise:

try:
    ...
except IndexError as X:      # X assigned the raised instance object
   ...

The as is optional in a try handler (if it’s omitted, the instance is simply not assigned to a name), but including it allows the handler to access both data in the instance and methods in the exception class.

This model works the same for user-defined exceptions we code with classes—the following, for example, passes to the exception class constructor arguments that become available in the handler through the assigned instance:

class MyExc(Exception): pass
...
raise MyExc('spam')          # Exception class with constructor args
...
try:
    ...
except MyExc as X:           # Instance attributes available in handler
    print(X.args)

Because this encroaches on the next chapter’s topic, though, I’ll defer further details until then.

Regardless of how you name them, exceptions are always identified by instance objects, and at most one is active at any given time. Once caught by an except clause anywhere in the program, an exception dies (i.e., won’t propagate to another try), unless it’s reraised by another raise statement or error.

Propagating Exceptions with raise

A raise statement that does not include an exception name or extra data value simply reraises the current exception. This form is typically used if you need to catch and handle an exception but don’t want the exception to die in your code:

>>> try:
...     raise IndexError('spam')         # Exceptions remember arguments
... except IndexError:
...     print('propagating')
...     raise                            # Reraise most recent exception
...
propagating
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 2, in <module>
IndexError: spam

Running a raise this way reraises the exception and propagates it to a higher handler (or the default handler at the top, which stops the program with a standard error message). Notice how the argument we passed to the exception class shows up in the error messages; you’ll learn why this happens in the next chapter.

Python 3.0 Exception Chaining: raise from

Python 3.0 (but not 2.6) also allows raise statements to have an optional from clause:

raise exception from otherexception

When the from is used, the second expression specifies another exception class or instance to attach to the raised exception’s __cause__ attribute. If the raised exception is not caught, Python prints both exceptions as part of the standard error message:

>>> try:
...    1 / 0
... except Exception as E:
...    raise TypeError('Bad!') from E
...
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 2, in <module>
ZeroDivisionError: int division or modulo by zero

The above exception was the direct cause of the following exception:

Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 4, in <module>
TypeError: Bad!

When an exception is raised inside an exception handler, a similar procedure is followed implicitly: the previous exception is attached to the new exception’s __context__ attribute and is again displayed in the standard error message if the exception goes uncaught. This is an advanced and still somewhat obscure extension, so see Python’s manuals for more details.

Note

Version skew note: Python 3.0 no longer supports the raise Exc, Args form that is still available in Python 2.6. In 3.0, use the raise Exc(Args) instance-creation call form described in this book instead. The equivalent comma form in 2.6 is legacy syntax provided for compatibility with the now defunct string-based exceptions model, and it’s deprecated in 2.6. If used, it is converted to the 3.0 call form. As in earlier releases, a raise Exc form is also allowed—it is converted to raise Exc() in both versions, calling the class constructor with no arguments.

with/as Context Managers

Python 2.6 and 3.0 introduced a new exception-related statement—the with, and its optional as clause. This statement is designed to work with context manager objects, which support a new method-based protocol. This feature is also available as an option in 2.5, enabled with an import of this form:

from __future__ import with_statement

In short, the with/as statement is designed to be an alternative to a common try/finally usage idiom; like that statement, it is intended for specifying termination-time or “cleanup” activities that must run regardless of whether an exception occurs in a processing step. Unlike try/finally, though, the with statement supports a richer object-based protocol for specifying both entry and exit actions around a block of code.

Python enhances some built-in tools with context managers, such as files that automatically close themselves and thread locks that automatically lock and unlock, but programmers can code context managers of their own with classes, too.

Basic Usage

The basic format of the with statement looks like this:

with expression [as variable]:
    with-block

The expression here is assumed to return an object that supports the context management protocol (more on this protocol in a moment). This object may also return a value that will be assigned to the name variable if the optional as clause is present.

Note that the variable is not necessarily assigned the result of the expression; the result of the expression is the object that supports the context protocol, and the variable may be assigned something else intended to be used inside the statement. The object returned by the expression may then run startup code before the with-block is started, as well as termination code after the block is done, regardless of whether the block raised an exception or not.

Some built-in Python objects have been augmented to support the context management protocol, and so can be used with the with statement. For example, file objects (covered in Chapter 9) have a context manager that automatically closes the file after the with block regardless of whether an exception is raised:

with open(r'C:\misc\data') as myfile:
    for line in myfile:
        print(line)
        ...more code here...

Here, the call to open returns a simple file object that is assigned to the name myfile. We can use myfile with the usual file tools—in this case, the file iterator reads line by line in the for loop.

However, this object also supports the context management protocol used by the with statement. After this with statement has run, the context management machinery guarantees that the file object referenced by myfile is automatically closed, even if the for loop raised an exception while processing the file.

Although file objects are automatically closed on garbage collection, it’s not always straightforward to know when that will occur. The with statement in this role is an alternative that allows us to be sure that the close will occur after execution of a specific block of code. As we saw earlier, we can achieve a similar effect with the more general and explicit try/finally statement, but it requires four lines of administrative code instead of one in this case:

myfile = open(r'C:\misc\data')
try:
    for line in myfile:
        print(line)
        ...more code here...
finally:
    myfile.close()

We won’t cover Python’s multithreading modules in this book (for more on that topic, see follow-up application-level texts such as Programming Python), but the lock and condition synchronization objects they define may also be used with the with statement, because they support the context management protocol:

lock = threading.Lock()
with lock:
    # critical section of code
    ...access shared resources...

Here, the context management machinery guarantees that the lock is automatically acquired before the block is executed and released once the block is complete, regardless of exception outcomes.

As introduced in Chapter 5, the decimal module also uses context managers to simplify saving and restoring the current decimal context, which specifies the precision and rounding characteristics for calculations:

with decimal.localcontext() as ctx:
    ctx.prec = 2
    x = decimal.Decimal('1.00') / decimal.Decimal('3.00')

After this statement runs, the current thread’s context manager state is automatically restored to what it was before the statement began. To do the same with a try/finally, we would need to save the context before and restore it manually.

The Context Management Protocol

Although some built-in types come with context managers, we can also write new ones of our own. To implement context managers, classes use special methods that fall into the operator overloading category to tap into the with statement. The interface expected of objects used in with statements is somewhat complex, and most programmers only need to know how to use existing context managers. For tool builders who might want to write new application-specific context managers, though, let’s take a quick look at what’s involved.

Here’s how the with statement actually works:

The expression is evaluated, resulting in an object known as a context manager that must have __enter__ and __exit__ methods.

The context manager’s __enter__ method is called. The value it returns is assigned to the variable in the as clause if present, or simply discarded otherwise.

The code in the nested with block is executed.

If the with block raises an exception, the __exit__(type, value, traceback) method is called with the exception details. Note that these are the same values returned by sys.exc_info, described in the Python manuals and later in this part of the book. If this method returns a false value, the exception is reraised; otherwise, the exception is terminated. The exception should normally be reraised so that it is propagated outside the with statement.

If the with block does not raise an exception, the __exit__ method is still called, but its type, value, and traceback arguments are all passed in as None.

Let’s look at a quick demo of the protocol in action. The following defines a context manager object that traces the entry and exit of the with block in any with statement it is used for:

class TraceBlock:
    def message(self, arg):
        print('running', arg)
    def __enter__(self):
        print('starting with block')
        return self
    def __exit__(self, exc_type, exc_value, exc_tb):
        if exc_type is None:
            print('exited normally\n')
        else:
            print('raise an exception!', exc_type)
            return False                                  # Propagate

with TraceBlock() as action:
    action.message('test 1')
    print('reached')

with TraceBlock() as action:
    action.message('test 2')
    raise TypeError
    print('not reached')

Notice that this class’s __exit__ method returns False to propagate the exception; deleting the return statement would have the same effect, as the default None return value of functions is False by definition. Also notice that the __enter__ method returns self as the object to assign to the as variable; in other use cases, this might return a completely different object instead.

When run, the context manager traces the entry and exit of the with statement block with its __enter__ and __exit__ methods. Here’s the script in action being run under Python 3.0 (it runs in 2.6, too, but prints some extra tuple parentheses):

% python withas.py
starting with block
running test 1
reached
exited normally

starting with block
running test 2
raise an exception! <class 'TypeError'>
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "withas.py", line 20, in <module>
    raise TypeError
TypeError

Context managers are somewhat advanced devices for tool builders, so we’ll skip additional details here (see Python’s standard manuals for the full story—for example, there’s a new contextlib standard module that provides additional tools for coding context managers). For simpler purposes, the try/finally statement provides sufficient support for termination-time activities.

Note

In the upcoming Python 3.1 release, the with statement may also specify multiple (sometimes referred to as “nested”) context managers with new comma syntax. In the following, for example, both files’ exit actions are automatically run when the statement block exits, regardless of exception outcomes:

with open('data') as fin, open('res', 'w') as fout:
    for line in fin:
        if 'some key' in line:
            fout.write(line)

Any number of context manager items may be listed, and multiple items work the same as nested with statements. In general, the 3.1 (and later) code:

with A() as a, B() as b:
    ...statements...

is equivalent to the following, which works in 3.1, 3.0, and 2.6:

with A() as a:
    with B() as b:
        ...statements...

See Python 3.1 release notes for additional details.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The try statement catches and recovers from exceptions—it specifies a block of code to run, and one or more handlers for exceptions that may be raised during the block’s execution.

The two common variations on the try statement are try/except/else (for catching exceptions) and try/finally (for specifying cleanup actions that must occur whether an exception is raised or not). In Python 2.4, these were separate statements that could be combined by syntactic nesting; in 2.5 and later, except and finally blocks may be mixed in the same statement, so the two statement forms are merged. In the merged form, the finally is still run on the way out of the try, regardless of what exceptions may have been raised or handled.

The raise statement raises (triggers) an exception. Python raises built-in exceptions on errors internally, but your scripts can trigger built-in or user-defined exceptions with raise, too.

The assert statement raises an AssertionError exception if a condition is false. It works like a conditional raise statement wrapped up in an if statement.

The with/as statement is designed to automate startup and termination activities that must occur around a block of code. It is roughly like a try/finally statement in that its exit actions run whether an exception occurred or not, but it allows a richer object-based protocol for specifying entry and exit actions.

[74] As mentioned in the prior chapter, the text of error messages and stack traces tends to vary slightly over time and shells. Don’t be alarmed if your error messages don’t exactly match mine. When I ran this example in Python 3.0’s IDLE GUI, for instance, its error message text showed filenames with full absolute directory paths.

[75] Unless Python crashes completely, of course. It does a good job of avoiding this, though, by checking all possible errors as a program runs. When a program does crash hard, it is usually due to a bug in linked-in C extension code, outside of Python’s scope.

[76] In most cases, at least. As suggested earlier in the book, if a function has to perform long-running or unrecoverable actions before it reaches the place where an exception will be triggered, you still might want to test for errors. Even in this case, though, be careful not to make your tests overly specific or restrictive, or you will limit your code’s utility.

Chapter 34. Exception Objects

So far, I’ve been deliberately vague about what an exception actually is. As suggested in the prior chapter, in Python 2.6 and 3.0 both built-in and user-defined exceptions are identified by class instance objects. Although this means you must use object-oriented programming to define new exceptions in your programs, classes and OOP in general offer a number of benefits.

Here are some of the advantages of class-based exceptions:

They can be organized into categories. Exception classes support future changes by providing categories—adding new exceptions in the future won’t generally require changes in try statements.

They have attached state information. Exception classes provide a natural place for us to store context information for use in the try handler—they may have both attached state information and callable methods, accessible through instances.

They support inheritance. Class-based exceptions can participate in inheritance hierarchies to obtain and customize common behavior—inherited display methods, for example, can provide a common look and feel for error messages.

Because of these advantages, class-based exceptions support program evolution and larger systems well. In fact, all built-in exceptions are identified by classes and are organized into an inheritance tree, for the reasons just listed. You can do the same with user-defined exceptions of your own.

In Python 3.0, user-defined exceptions inherit from built-in exception superclasses. As we’ll see here, because these superclasses provide useful defaults for printing and state retention, the task of coding user-defined exceptions also involves understanding the roles of these built-ins.

Note

Version skew note: Python 2.6 and 3.0 both require exceptions to be defined by classes. In addition, 3.0 requires exception classes to be derived from the BaseException built-in exception superclass, either directly or indirectly. As we’ll see, most programs inherit from this class’s Exception subclass, to support catchall handlers for normal exception types—naming it in a handler will catch everything most programs should. Python 2.6 allows standalone classic classes to serve as exceptions, too, but it requires new-style classes to be derived from built-in exception classes, the same as 3.0.

Exceptions: Back to the Future

Once upon a time (well, prior to Python 2.6 and 3.0), it was possible to define exceptions in two different ways. This complicated try statements, raise statements, and Python in general. Today, there is only one way to do it. This is a good thing: it removes from the language substantial cruft accumulated for the sake of backward compatibility. Because the old way helps explain why exceptions are as they are today, though, and because it’s not really possible to completely erase the history of something that has been used by a million people over the course of nearly two decades, let’s begin our exploration of the present with a brief look at the past.

String Exceptions Are Right Out!

Prior to Python 2.6 and 3.0, it was possible to define exceptions with both class instances and string objects. String-based exceptions began issuing deprecation warnings in 2.5 and were removed in 2.6 and 3.0, so today you should use class-based exceptions, as shown in this book. If you work with legacy code, though, you might still come across string exceptions. They might also appear in tutorials and web resources written a few years ago (which qualifies as an eternity in Python years!).

String exceptions were straightforward to use—any string would do, and they matched by object identity, not value (that is, using is, not ==):

C:\misc> C:\Python25\python
>>> myexc = "My exception string"                 # Were we ever this young?
>>> try:
...     raise myexc
... except myexc:
...     print('caught')
...
caught

This form of exception was removed because it was not as good as classes for larger programs and code maintenance. Although you can’t use string exceptions today, they actually provide a natural vehicle for introducing the class-based exceptions model.

Class-Based Exceptions

Strings were a simple way to define exceptions. As described earlier, however, classes have some added advantages that merit a quick look. Most prominently, they allow us to identify exception categories that are more flexible to use and maintain than simple strings. Moreover, classes naturally allow for attached exception details and support inheritance. Because they are the better approach, they are now required.

Coding details aside, the chief difference between string and class exceptions has to do with the way that exceptions raised are matched against except clauses in try statements:

String exceptions were matched by simple object identity: the raised exception was matched to except clauses by Python’s is test.

Class exceptions are matched by superclass relationships: the raised exception matches an except clause if that except clause names the exception’s class or any superclass of it.

That is, when a try statement’s except clause lists a superclass, it catches instances of that superclass, as well as instances of all its subclasses lower in the class tree. The net effect is that class exceptions support the construction of exception hierarchies: superclasses become category names, and subclasses become specific kinds of exceptions within a category. By naming a general exception superclass, an except clause can catch an entire category of exceptions—any more specific subclass will match.

String exceptions had no such concept: because they were matched by simple object identity, there was no direct way to organize exceptions into more flexible categories or groups. The net result was that exception handlers were coupled with exception sets in a way that made changes difficult.

In addition to this category idea, class-based exceptions better support exception state information (attached to instances) and allow exceptions to participate in inheritance hierarchies (to obtain common behaviors). Because they offer all the benefits of classes and OOP in general, they provide a more powerful alternative to the now defunct string-based exceptions model in exchange for a small amount of additional code.

Coding Exceptions Classes

Let’s look at an example to see how class exceptions translate to code. In the following file, classexc.py, we define a superclass called General and two subclasses called Specific1 and Specific2. This example illustrates the notion of exception categories—General is a category name, and its two subclasses are specific types of exceptions within the category. Handlers that catch General will also catch any subclasses of it, including Specific1 and Specific2:

class General(Exception): pass
class Specific1(General): pass
class Specific2(General): pass

def raiser0():
    X = General()          # Raise superclass instance
    raise X

def raiser1():
    X = Specific1()        # Raise subclass instance
    raise X

def raiser2():
    X = Specific2()        # Raise different subclass instance
    raise X

for func in (raiser0, raiser1, raiser2):
    try:
        func()
    except General:        # Match General or any subclass of it
        import sys
        print('caught:', sys.exc_info()[0])

C:\python30> python classexc.py
caught: <class '__main__.General'>
caught: <class '__main__.Specific1'>
caught: <class '__main__.Specific2'>

This code is mostly straightforward, but here are a few implementation notes:

Exception superclass

Classes used to build exception category trees have very few requirements—in fact, in this example they are mostly empty, with bodies that do nothing but pass. Notice, though, how the top-level class here inherits from the built-in Exception class. This is required in Python 3.0; Python 2.6 allows standalone classic classes to serve as exceptions too, but it requires new-style classes to be derived from built-in exception classes just like in 3.0. Although we don’t employ it here, because Exception provides some useful behavior we’ll meet later, it’s a good idea to inherit from it in either Python.

Raising instances

In this code, we call classes to make instances for the raise statements. In the class exception model, we always raise and catch a class instance object. If we list a class name without parentheses in a raise, Python calls the class with no constructor argument to make an instance for us. Exception instances can be created before the raise, as done here, or within the raise statement itself.

Catching categories

This code includes functions that raise instances of all three of our classes as exceptions, as well as a top-level try that calls the functions and catches General exceptions. The same try also catches the two specific exceptions, because they are subclasses of General.

Exception details

The exception handler here uses the sys.exc_info call—as we’ll see in more detail in the next chapter, it’s how we can grab hold of the most recently raised exception in a generic fashion. Briefly, the first item in its result is the class of the exception raised, and the second is the actual instance raised. In a general except clause like the one here that catches all classes in a category, sys.exc_info is one way to determine exactly what’s occurred. In this particular case, it’s equivalent to fetching the instance’s __class__ attribute. As we’ll see in the next chapter, the sys.exc_info scheme is also commonly used with empty except clauses that catch everything.

The last point merits further explanation. When an exception is caught, we can be sure that the instance raised is an instance of the class listed in the except, or one of its more specific subclasses. Because of this, the __class__ attribute of the instance also gives the exception type. The following variant, for example, works the same as the prior example:

class General(Exception): pass
class Specific1(General): pass
class Specific2(General): pass

def raiser0(): raise General()
def raiser1(): raise Specific1()
def raiser2(): raise Specific2()

for func in (raiser0, raiser1, raiser2):
    try:
        func()
    except General as X:                     # X is the raised instance
        print('caught:', X.__class__)        # Same as sys.exc_info()[0]

Because __class__ can be used like this to determine the specific type of exception raised, sys.exc_info is more useful for empty except clauses that do not otherwise have a way to access the instance or its class. Furthermore, more realistic programs usually should not have to care about which specific exception was raised at all—by calling methods of the instance generically, we automatically dispatch to behavior tailored for the exception raised. More on this and sys.exc_info in the next chapter; also see Chapter 28 and Part VI at large if you’ve forgotten what __class__ means in an instance.

Why Exception Hierarchies?

Because there are only three possible exceptions in the prior section’s example, it doesn’t really do justice to the utility of class exceptions. In fact, we could achieve the same effects by coding a list of exception names in parentheses within the except clause:

try:
    func()
except (General, Specific1, Specific2):     # Catch any of these
    ...

This approach worked for the defunct string exception model too. For large or high exception hierarchies, however, it may be easier to catch categories using class-based categories than to list every member of a category in a single except clause. Perhaps more importantly, you can extend exception hierarchies by adding new subclasses without breaking existing code.

Suppose, for example, you code a numeric programming library in Python, to be used by a large number of people. While you are writing your library, you identify two things that can go wrong with numbers in your code—division by zero, and numeric overflow. You document these as the two exceptions that your library may raise:

# mathlib.py

class Divzero(Exception): pass
class Oflow(Exception): pass

def func():
    ...
    raise Divzero()

Now, when people use your library, they typically wrap calls to your functions or classes in try statements that catch your two exceptions (if they do not catch your exceptions, exceptions from the library will kill their code):

# client.py

import mathlib

try:
    mathlib.func(...)
except (mathlib.Divzero, mathlib.Oflow):
    ...handle and recover...

This works fine, and lots of people start using your library. Six months down the road, though, you revise it (as programmers are prone to do). Along the way, you identify a new thing that can go wrong—underflow—and add that as a new exception:

# mathlib.py

class Divzero(Exception): pass
class Oflow(Exception): pass
class Uflow(Exception): pass

Unfortunately, when you re-release your code, you create a maintenance problem for your users. If they’ve listed your exceptions explicitly, they now have to go back and change every place they call your library to include the newly added exception name:

# client.py

try:
    mathlib.func(...)
except (mathlib.Divzero, mathlib.Oflow, mathlib.Uflow):
    ...handle and recover...

This may not be the end of the world. If your library is used only in-house, you can make the changes yourself. You might also ship a Python script that tries to fix such code automatically (it would probably be only a few dozen lines, and it would guess right at least some of the time). If many people have to change all their try statements each time you alter your exception set, though, this is not exactly the most polite of upgrade policies.

Your users might try to avoid this pitfall by coding empty except clauses to catch all possible exceptions:

# client.py

try:
    mathlib.func(...)
except:                           # Catch everything here
    ...handle and recover...

But this workaround might catch more than they bargained for—things like running out of memory, keyboard interrupts (Ctrl-C), system exits, and even typos in their own try block’s code will all trigger exceptions, and such things should pass, not be caught and erroneously classified as library errors.

And really, in this scenario users want to catch and recover from only the specific exceptions the library is defined and documented to raise; if any other exception occurs during a library call, it’s likely a genuine bug in the library (and probably time to contact the vendor!). As a rule of thumb, it’s usually better to be specific than general in exception handlers—an idea we’ll revisit as a “gotcha” in the next chapter.[77]

So what to do, then? Class exception hierarchies fix this dilemma completely. Rather than defining your library’s exceptions as a set of autonomous classes, arrange them into a class tree with a common superclass to encompass the entire category:

# mathlib.py

class NumErr(Exception): pass
class Divzero(NumErr): pass
class Oflow(NumErr): pass
...
def func():
    ...
    raise DivZero()

This way, users of your library simply need to list the common superclass (i.e., category) to catch all of your library’s exceptions, both now and in the future:

# client.py

import mathlib
...
try:
    mathlib.func(...)
except mathlib.NumErr:
    ...report and recover...

When you go back and hack your code again, you can add new exceptions as new subclasses of the common superclass:

# mathlib.py

...
class Uflow(NumErr): pass

The end result is that user code that catches your library’s exceptions will keep working, unchanged. In fact, you are free to add, delete, and change exceptions arbitrarily in the future—as long as clients name the superclass, they are insulated from changes in your exceptions set. In other words, class exceptions provide a better answer to maintenance issues than strings do.

Class-based exception hierarchies also support state retention and inheritance in ways that make them ideal in larger programs. To understand these roles, though, we first need to see how user-defined exception classes relate to the built-in exceptions from which they inherit.

Built-in Exception Classes

I didn’t really pull the prior section’s examples out of thin air. All built-in exceptions that Python itself may raise are predefined class objects. Moreover, they are organized into a shallow hierarchy with general superclass categories and specific subclass types, much like the exceptions class tree we developed earlier.

In Python 3.0, all the familiar exceptions you’ve seen (e.g., SyntaxError) are really just predefined classes, available as built-in names in the module named builtins (in Python 2.6, they instead live in __builtin__ and are also attributes of the standard library module exceptions). In addition, Python organizes the built-in exceptions into a hierarchy, to support a variety of catching modes. For example:

BaseException

The top-level root superclass of exceptions. This class is not supposed to be directly inherited by user-defined classes (use Exception instead). It provides default printing and state retention behavior inherited by subclasses. If the str built-in is called on an instance of this class (e.g., by print), the class returns the display strings of the constructor arguments passed when the instance was created (or an empty string if there were no arguments). In addition, unless subclasses replace this class’s constructor, all of the arguments passed to this class at instance construction time are stored in its args attribute as a tuple.

Exception

The top-level root superclass of application-related exceptions. This is an immediate subclass of BaseException and is superclass to every other built-in exception, except the system exit event classes (SystemExit, KeyboardInterrupt, and GeneratorExit). Almost all user-defined classes should inherit from this class, not BaseException. When this convention is followed, naming Exception in a try statement’s handler ensures that your program will catch everything but system exit events, which should normally be allowed to pass. In effect, Exception becomes a catchall in try statements and is more accurate than an empty except.

ArithmeticError

The superclass of all numeric errors (and a subclass of Exception).

OverflowError

A subclass of ArithmeticError that identifies a specific numeric error.

And so on—you can read further about this structure in reference texts such as Python Pocket Reference or the Python library manual. Note that the exceptions class tree differs slightly between Python 3.0 and 2.6. Also note that you can see the class tree in the help text of the exceptions module in Python 2.6 only (this module is removed in 3.0). See Chapters 4 and 15 for help on help:

>>> import exceptions
>>> help(exceptions)
...lots of text omitted...

Built-in Exception Categories

The built-in class tree allows you to choose how specific or general your handlers will be. For example, the built-in exception ArithmeticError is a superclass for more specific exceptions such as OverflowError and ZeroDivisionError. By listing ArithmeticError in a try, you will catch any kind of numeric error raised; by listing just OverflowError, you will intercept just that specific type of error, and no others.

Similarly, because Exception is the superclass of all application-level exceptions in Python 3.0, you can generally use it as a catchall—the effect is much like an empty except, but it allows system exit exceptions to pass as they usually should:

try:
    action()
except Exception:
    ...handle all application exceptions...
else:
    ...handle no-exception case...

This doesn’t quite work universally in Python 2.6, however, because standalone user-defined exceptions coded as classic classes are not required to be subclasses of the Exception root class. This technique is more reliable in Python 3.0, since it requires all classes to derive from built-in exceptions. Even in Python 3.0, though, this scheme suffers most of the same potential pitfalls as the empty except, as described in the prior chapter—it might intercept exceptions intended for elsewhere, and it might mask genuine programming errors. Since this is such a common issue, we’ll revisit it as a “gotcha” in the next chapter.

Whether or not you will leverage the categories in the built-in class tree, it serves as a good example; by using similar techniques for class exceptions in your own code, you can provide exception sets that are flexible and easily modified.

Default Printing and State

Built-in exceptions also provide default print displays and state retention, which is often as much logic as user-defined classes require. Unless you redefine the constructors your classes inherit from them, any constructor arguments you pass to these classes are saved in the instance’s args tuple attribute and are automatically displayed when the instance is printed (an empty tuple and display string are used if no constructor arguments are passed).

This explains why arguments passed to built-in exception classes show up in error messages—any constructor arguments are attached to the instance and displayed when the instance is printed:

>>> raise IndexError                    # Same as IndexError(): no arguments
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
IndexError

>>> raise IndexError('spam')            # Constructor argument attached, printed
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
IndexError: spam

>>> I = IndexError('spam')              # Available in object attribute
>>> I.args
('spam',)

The same holds true for user-defined exceptions, because they inherit the constructor and display methods present in their built-in superclasses:

>>> class E(Exception): pass
...
>>> try:
...    raise E('spam')
... except E as X:
...    print(X, X.args)                 # Displays and saves constructor arguments
...
spam ('spam',)

>>> try:
...    raise E('spam', 'eggs', 'ham')
... except E as X:
...    print(X, X.args)
...
('spam', 'eggs', 'ham') ('spam', 'eggs', 'ham')

Note that exception instance objects are not strings themselves, but use the __str__ operator overloading protocol we studied in Chapter 29 to provide display strings when printed; to concatenate with real strings, perform manual conversions: str(X) + "string".

Although this automatic state and display support is useful by itself, for more specific display and state retention needs you can always redefine inherited methods such as __str__ and __init__ in Exception subclasses—the next section shows how.

Custom Print Displays

As we saw in the preceding section, by default, instances of class-based exceptions display whatever you passed to the class constructor when they are caught and printed:

>>> class MyBad(Exception): pass
...
>>> try:
...     raise MyBad('Sorry--my mistake!')
... except MyBad as X:
...     print(X)
...
Sorry--my mistake!

This inherited default display model is also used if the exception is displayed as part of an error message when the exception is not caught:

>>> raise MyBad('Sorry--my mistake!')
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
__main__.MyBad: Sorry--my mistake!

For many roles, this is sufficient. To provide a more custom display, though, you can define one of two string-representation overloading methods in your class (__repr__ or __str__) to return the string you want to display for your exception. The string the method returns will be displayed if the exception either is caught and printed or reaches the default handler:

>>> class MyBad(Exception):
...     def __str__(self):
...         return 'Always look on the bright side of life...'
...
>>> try:
...     raise MyBad()
... except MyBad as X:
...     print(X)
...
Always look on the bright side of life...

>>> raise MyBad()
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
__main__.MyBad: Always look on the bright side of life...

A subtle point to note here is that you generally must redefine __str__ for this purpose, because the built-in superclasses already have a __str__ method, and __str__ is preferred to __repr__ in most contexts (including printing). If you define a __repr__, printing will happily call the superclass’s __str__ instead! See Chapter 29 for more details on these special methods.

Whatever your method returns is included in error messages for uncaught exceptions and used when exceptions are printed explicitly. The method returns a hardcoded string here to illustrate, but it can also perform arbitrary text processing, possibly using state information attached to the instance object. The next section looks at state information options.

Custom Data and Behavior

Besides supporting flexible hierarchies, exception classes also provide storage for extra state information as instance attributes. As we saw earlier, built-in exception superclasses provide a default constructor that automatically saves constructor arguments in an instance tuple attribute named args. Although the default constructor is adequate for many cases, for more custom needs we can provide a constructor of our own. In addition, classes may define methods for use in handlers that provide precoded exception processing logic.

Providing Exception Details

When an exception is raised, it may cross arbitrary file boundaries—the raise statement that triggers an exception and the try statement that catches it may be in completely different module files. It is not generally feasible to store extra details in global variables because the try statement might not know which file the globals reside in. Passing extra state information along in the exception itself allows the try statement to access it more reliably.

With classes, this is nearly automatic. As we’ve seen, when an exception is raised, Python passes the class instance object along with the exception. Code in try statements can access the raised instance by listing an extra variable after the as keyword in an except handler. This provides a natural hook for supplying data and behavior to the handler.

For example, a program that parses data files might signal a formatting error by raising an exception instance that is filled out with extra details about the error:

>>> class FormatError(Exception):
...     def __init__(self, line, file):
...         self.line = line
...         self.file = file
...
>>> def parser():
...     raise FormatError(42, file='spam.txt')     # When error  found
...
>>> try:
...     parser()
... except FormatError as X:
...     print('Error at', X.file, X.line)
...
Error at spam.txt 42

In the except clause here, the variable X is assigned a reference to the instance that was generated when the exception was raised.[78] This gives access to the attributes attached to the instance by the custom constructor. Although we could rely on the default state retention of built-in superclasses, it’s less relevant to our application:

>>> class FormatError(Exception): pass             # Inherited constructor
...
>>> def parser():
...     raise FormatError(42, 'spam.txt')          # No keywords allowed!
...
>>> try:
...     parser()
... except FormatError as X:
...     print('Error at:', X.args[0], X.args[1])   # Not specific to this app
...
Error at: 42 spam.txt

Providing Exception Methods

Besides enabling application-specific state information, custom constructors also better support extra behavior for exception objects. That is, the exception class can also define methods to be called in the handler. The following, for example, adds a method that uses exception state information to log errors to a file:

class FormatError(Exception):
    logfile = 'formaterror.txt'
    def __init__(self, line, file):
        self.line = line
        self.file = file
    def logerror(self):
        log = open(self.logfile, 'a')
        print('Error at', self.file, self.line, file=log)

def parser():
    raise FormatError(40, 'spam.txt')

try:
    parser()
except FormatError as exc:
    exc.logerror()

When run, this script writes its error message to a file in response to method calls in the exception handler:

C:\misc> C:\Python30\python parse.py
C:\misc> type formaterror.txt
Error at spam.txt 40

In such a class, methods (like logerror) may also be inherited from superclasses, and instance attributes (like line and file) provide a place to save state information that provides extra context for use in later method calls. Moreover, exception classes are free to customize and extend inherited behavior. In other words, because they are defined with classes, all the benefits of OOP that we studied in Part VI are available for use with exceptions in Python.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

In 3.0, exceptions must be defined by classes (that is, a class instance object is raised and caught). In addition, exception classes must be derived from the built-in class BaseException (most programs inherit from its Exception subclass, to support catchall handlers for normal kinds of exceptions).

Class-based exceptions match by superclass relationships: naming a superclass in an exception handler will catch instances of that class, as well as instances of any of its subclasses lower in the class tree. Because of this, you can think of superclasses as general exception categories and subclasses as more specific types of exceptions within those categories.

You can attach context information to class-based exceptions by filling out instance attributes in the instance object raised, usually in a custom class constructor. For simpler needs, built-in exception superclasses provide a constructor that stores its arguments on the instance automatically (in the attribute args). In exception handlers, you list a variable to be assigned to the raised instance, then go through this name to access attached state information and call any methods defined in the class.

The error message text in class-based exceptions can be specified with a custom __str__ operator overloading method. For simpler needs, built-in exception superclasses automatically display anything you pass to the class constructor. Operations like print and str automatically fetch the display string of an exception object when is it printed either explicitly or as part of an error message.

Because Guido said so—they have been removed in both Python 2.6 and 3.0. Really, there are good reasons for this: string-based exceptions did not support categories, state information, or behavior inheritance in the way class-based exceptions do. In practice, this made string-based exceptions easier to use at first, when programs were small, but more complex to use as programs grew larger.

[77] As a clever student of mine suggested, the library module could also provide a tuple object that contains all the exceptions the library can possibly raise—the client could then import the tuple and name it in an except clause to catch all the library’s exceptions (recall that including a tuple in an except means catch any of its exceptions). When new exceptions are added later, the library can just expand the exported tuple. This would work, but you’d still need to keep the tuple up-to-date with raised exceptions inside the library module. Also, class hierarchies offer more benefits than just categories—they also support inherited state and methods and a customization model that individual exceptions do not.

[78] As suggested earlier, the raised instance object is also available generically as the second item in the result tuple of the sys.exc_info() call—a tool that returns information about the most recently raised exception. This interface must be used if you do not list an exception name in an except clause but still need access to the exception that occurred, or to any of its attached state information or methods. More on sys.exc_info in the next chapter.

Exception Idioms

We’ve seen the mechanics behind exceptions. Now let’s take a look at some of the other ways they are typically used.

Exceptions Aren’t Always Errors

In Python, all errors are exceptions, but not all exceptions are errors. For instance, we saw in Chapter 9 that file object read methods return an empty string at the end of a file. In contrast, the built-in input function (which we first met in Chapter 3 and deployed in an interactive loop in Chapter 10) reads a line of text from the standard input stream, sys.stdin, at each call and raises the built-in EOFError at end-of-file. (This function is known as raw_input in Python 2.6.)

Unlike file methods, this function does not return an empty string—an empty string from input means an empty line. Despite its name, the EOFError exception is just a signal in this context, not an error. Because of this behavior, unless the end-of-file should terminate a script, input often appears wrapped in a try handler and nested in a loop, as in the following code:

while True:
    try:
        line = input()           # Read line from stdin
    except EOFError:
        break                    # Exit loop at end-of-file
    else:
        ...process next line here...

Several other built-in exceptions are similarly signals, not errors—calling sys.exit() and pressing Ctrl-C on your keyboard, respectively, raise SystemExit and KeyboardInterrupt, for example. Python also has a set of built-in exceptions that represent warnings rather than errors; some of these are used to signal use of deprecated (phased out) language features. See the standard library manual’s description of built-in exceptions for more information, and consult the warnings module’s documentation for more on warnings.

Functions Can Signal Conditions with raise

User-defined exceptions can also signal nonerror conditions. For instance, a search routine can be coded to raise an exception when a match is found instead of returning a status flag for the caller to interpret. In the following, the try/except/else exception handler does the work of an if/else return-value tester:

class Found(Exception): pass

def searcher():
    if ...success...:
        raise Found()
    else:
        return

try:
    searcher()
except Found:                    # Exception if item was found
    ...success...
else:                            # else returned: not found
    ...failure...

More generally, such a coding structure may also be useful for any function that cannot return a sentinel value to designate success or failure. For instance, if all objects are potentially valid return values, it’s impossible for any return value to signal unusual conditions. Exceptions provide a way to signal results without a return value:

class Failure(Exception): pass

def searcher():
    if ...success...:
        return ...founditem...
    else:
        raise Failure()

try:
    item = searcher()
except Failure:
    ...report...
else:
    ...use item here...

Because Python is dynamically typed and polymorphic to the core, exceptions, rather than sentinel return values, are the generally preferred way to signal such conditions.

Closing Files and Server Connections

We encountered examples in this category in Chapter 33. As a summary, though, exception processing tools are also commonly used to ensure that system resources are finalized, regardless of whether an error occurs during processing or not.

For example, some servers require connections to be closed in order to terminate a session. Similarly, output files may require close calls to flush their buffers to disk, and input files may consume file descriptors if not closed; although file objects are automatically closed when garbage collected if still open, it’s sometimes difficult to be sure when that will occur.

The most general and explicit way to guarantee termination actions for a specific block of code is the try/finally statement:

myfile = open(r'C:\misc\script', 'w')
try:
    ...process myfile...
finally:
    myfile.close()

As we saw in Chapter 33, some objects make this easier in Python 2.6 and 3.0 by providing context managers run by the with/as statement that terminate or close the objects for us automatically:

with open(r'C:\misc\script', 'w') as myfile:
    ...process myfile...

So which option is better here? As usual, it depends on your programs. Compared to the try/finally, context managers are more implicit, which runs contrary to Python’s general design philosophy. Context managers are also arguably less general—they are available only for select objects, and writing user-defined context managers to handle general termination requirements is more complex than coding a try/finally.

On the other hand, using existing context managers requires less code than using try/finally, as shown by the preceding examples. Moreover, the context manager protocol supports entry actions in addition to exit actions. Although the try/finally is perhaps the more widely applicable technique, context managers may be more appropriate where they are already available, or where their extra complexity is warranted.

Debugging with Outer try Statements

You can also make use of exception handlers to replace Python’s default top-level exception-handling behavior. By wrapping an entire program (or a call to it) in an outer try in your top-level code, you can catch any exception that may occur while your program runs, thereby subverting the default program termination.

In the following, the empty except clause catches any uncaught exception raised while the program runs. To get hold of the actual exception that occurred, fetch the sys.exc_info function call result from the built-in sys module; it returns a tuple whose first two items contain the current exception’s class and the instance object raised (more on sys.exc_info in a moment):

try:
    ...run program...
except:                         # All uncaught exceptions come here
    import sys
    print('uncaught!', sys.exc_info()[0], sys.exc_info()[1])

This structure is commonly used during development, to keep programs active even after errors occur—it allows you to run additional tests without having to restart. It’s also used when testing other program code, as described in the next section.

Running In-Process Tests

You might combine some of the coding patterns we’ve just looked at in a test-driver application that tests other code within the same process:

import sys
log = open('testlog', 'a')
from testapi import moreTests, runNextTest, testName
def testdriver():
    while moreTests():
        try:
            runNextTest()
        except:
            print('FAILED', testName(), sys.exc_info()[:2], file=log)
        else:
            print('PASSED', testName(), file=log)
testdriver()

The testdriver function here cycles through a series of test calls (the module testapi is left abstract in this example). Because an uncaught exception in a test case would normally kill this test driver, you need to wrap test case calls in a try if you want to continue the testing process after a test fails. The empty except catches any uncaught exception generated by a test case as usual, and it uses sys.exc_info to log the exception to a file. The else clause is run when no exception occurs—the test success case.

Such boilerplate code is typical of systems that test functions, modules, and classes by running them in the same process as the test driver. In practice, however, testing can be much more sophisticated than this. For instance, to test external programs, you could instead check status codes or outputs generated by program-launching tools such as os.system and os.popen, covered in the standard library manual (such tools do not generally raise exceptions for errors in the external programs—in fact, the test cases may run in parallel with the test driver).

At the end of this chapter, we’ll also meet some more complete testing frameworks provided by Python, such as doctest and PyUnit, which provide tools for comparing expected outputs with actual results.

More on sys.exc_info

The sys.exc_info result used in the last two sections allows an exception handler to gain access to the most recently raised exception generically. This is especially useful when using the empty except clause to catch everything blindly, to determine what was raised:

try:
    ...
except:
    # sys.exc_info()[0:2] are the exception class and instance

If no exception is being handled, this call it returns a tuple containing three None values. Otherwise, the values returned are (type, value, traceback), where:

type is the exception class of the exception being handled.

value is the exception class instance that was raised.

traceback is a traceback object that represents the call stack at the point where the exception originally occurred (see the traceback module’s documentation for tools that may be used in conjunction with this object to generate error messages manually).

As we saw in the prior chapter, sys.exc_info can also sometimes be useful to determine the specific exception type when catching exception category superclasses. As we saw, though, because in this case you can also get the exception type by fetching the __class__ attribute of the instance obtained with the as clause, sys.exc_info is mostly used by the empty except today:

try:
    ...
except General as instance:
    # instance.__class__ is the exception class

That said, using the instance object’s interfaces and polymorphism is often a better approach than testing exception types—exception methods can be defined per class and run generically:

try:
    ...
except General as instance:
    # instance.method() does the right thing for this instance

As usual, being too specific in Python can limit your code’s flexibility. A polymorphic approach like the last example here generally supports future evolution better.

Note

Version skew note: In Python 2.6, the older tools sys.exc_type and sys.exc_value still work to fetch the most recent exception type and value, but they can manage only a single, global exception for the entire process. These two names have been removed in Python 3.0. The newer and preferred sys.exc_info() call available in both 2.6 and 3.0 instead keeps track of each thread’s exception information, and so is thread-specific. Of course, this distinction matters only when using multiple threads in Python programs (a subject beyond this book’s scope), but 3.0 forces the issue. See other resources for more details.

Exception Design Tips and Gotchas

I’m lumping design tips and gotchas together in this chapter, because it turns out that the most common gotchas largely stem from design issues. By and large, exceptions are easy to use in Python. The real art behind them is in deciding how specific or general your except clauses should be and how much code to wrap up in try statements. Let’s address the second of these concerns first.

What Should Be Wrapped

In principle, you could wrap every statement in your script in its own try, but that would just be silly (the try statements would then need to be wrapped in try statements!). What to wrap is really a design issue that goes beyond the language itself, and it will become more apparent with use. But for now, here are a few rules of thumb:

Operations that commonly fail should generally be wrapped in try statements. For example, operations that interface with system state (file opens, socket calls, and the like) are prime candidates for trys.

However, there are exceptions to the prior rule—in a simple script, you may want failures of such operations to kill your program instead of being caught and ignored. This is especially true if the failure is a showstopper. Failures in Python typically result in useful error messages (not hard crashes), and this is often the best outcome you could hope for.

You should implement termination actions in try/finally statements to guarantee their execution, unless a context manager is available as a with/as option. The try/finally statement form allows you to run code whether exceptions occur or not in arbitrary scenarios.

It is sometimes more convenient to wrap the call to a large function in a single try statement, rather than littering the function itself with many try statements. That way, all exceptions in the function percolate up to the try around the call, and you reduce the amount of code within the function.

The types of programs you write will probably influence the amount of exception handling you code as well. Servers, for instance, must generally keep running persistently and so will likely require try statements to catch and recover from exceptions. In-process testing programs of the kind we saw in this chapter will probably handle exceptions as well. Simpler one-shot scripts, though, will often ignore exception handling completely because failure at any step requires script shutdown.

Catching Too Much: Avoid Empty except and Exception

On to the issue of handler generality. Python lets you pick and choose which exceptions to catch, but you sometimes have to be careful to not be too inclusive. For example, you’ve seen that an empty except clause catches every exception that might be raised while the code in the try block runs.

That’s easy to code, and sometimes desirable, but you may also wind up intercepting an error that’s expected by a try handler higher up in the exception nesting structure. For example, an exception handler such as the following catches and stops every exception that reaches it, regardless of whether another handler is waiting for it:

def func():
    try:
        ...                      # IndexError is raised in here
    except:
        ...                      # But everything comes here and dies!
try:
    func()
except IndexError:               # Exception should be processed here
    ...

Perhaps worse, such code might also catch unrelated system exceptions. Even things like memory errors, genuine programming mistakes, iteration stops, keyboard interrupts, and system exits raise exceptions in Python. Such exceptions should not usually be intercepted.

For example, scripts normally exit when control falls off the end of the top-level file. However, Python also provides a built-in sys.exit(statuscode) call to allow early terminations. This actually works by raising a built-in SystemExit exception to end the program, so that try/finally handlers run on the way out and special types of programs can intercept the event.[79] Because of this, a try with an empty except might unknowingly prevent a crucial exit, as in the following file (exiter.py):

import sys
def bye():
    sys.exit(40)                 # Crucial error: abort now!
try:
    bye()
except:
    print('got it')              # Oops--we ignored the exit
print('continuing...')

% python exiter.py
got it
continuing...

You simply might not expect all the kinds of exceptions that could occur during an operation. Using the built-in exception classes of the prior chapter can help in this particular case, because the Exception superclass is not a superclass of SystemExit:

try:
    bye()
except Exception:                # Won't catch exits, but _will_ catch many others
    ...

In other cases, though, this scheme is no better than an empty except clause—because Exception is a superclass above all built-in exceptions except system-exit events, it still has the potential to catch exceptions meant for elsewhere in the program.

Probably worst of all, both an empty except and catching the Exception class will also catch genuine programming errors, which should be allowed to pass most of the time. In fact, these two techniques can effectively turn off Python’s error-reporting machinery, making it difficult to notice mistakes in your code. Consider this code, for example:

mydictionary = {...}
...
try:
    x = myditctionary['spam']    # Oops: misspelled
except:
    x = None                     # Assume we got KeyError
...continue here with x...

The coder here assumes that the only sort of error that can happen when indexing a dictionary is a missing key error. But because the name myditctionary is misspelled (it should say mydictionary), Python raises a NameError instead for the undefined name reference, which the handler will silently catch and ignore. The event handler will incorrectly fill in a default for the dictionary access, masking the program error. Moreover, catching Exception here would have the exact same effect as an empty except. If this happens in code that is far removed from the place where the fetched values are used, it might make for a very interesting debugging task!

As a rule of thumb, be as specific in your handlers as you can be—empty except clauses and Exception catchers are handy, but potentially error-prone. In the last example, for instance, you would be better off saying except KeyError: to make your intentions explicit and avoid intercepting unrelated events. In simpler scripts, the potential for problems might not be significant enough to outweigh the convenience of a catchall, but in general, general handlers are generally trouble.

Catching Too Little: Use Class-Based Categories

On the other hand, neither should handlers be too specific. When you list specific exceptions in a try, you catch only what you actually list. This isn’t necessarily a bad thing, but if a system evolves to raise other exceptions in the future, you may need to go back and add them to exception lists elsewhere in your code.

We saw this phenomenon at work in the prior chapter. For instance, the following handler is written to treat MyExcept1 and MyExcept2 as normal cases and everything else as an error. Therefore, if you add a MyExcept3 in the future, it will be processed as an error unless you update the exception list:

try:
    ...
except (MyExcept1, MyExcept2):   # Breaks if you add a MyExcept3
    ...                          # Non-errors
else:
    ...                          # Assumed to be an error

Luckily, careful use of the class-based exceptions we discussed in Chapter 33 can make this trap go away completely. As we saw, if you catch a general superclass, you can add and raise more specific subclasses in the future without having to extend except clause lists manually—the superclass becomes an extendible exceptions category:

try:
    ...
except SuccessCategoryName:      # OK if I add a myerror3 subclass
    ...                          # Non-errors
else:
    ...                          # Assumed to be an error

In other words, a little design goes a long way. The moral of the story is to be careful to be neither too general nor too specific in exception handlers, and to pick the granularity of your try statement wrappings wisely. Especially in larger systems, exception policies should be a part of the overall design.

Core Language Summary

Congratulations! This concludes your look at the core Python programming language. If you’ve gotten this far, you may consider yourself an Official Python Programmer (and should feel free to add Python to your résumé the next time you dig it out). You’ve already seen just about everything there is to see in the language itself, and all in much more depth than many practicing Python programmers initially do. You’ve studied built-in types, statements, and exceptions, as well as tools used to build up larger program units (functions, modules, and classes); you’ve even explored important design issues, OOP, program architecture, and more.

The Python Toolset

From this point forward, your future Python career will largely consist of becoming proficient with the toolset available for application-level Python programming. You’ll find this to be an ongoing task. The standard library, for example, contains hundreds of modules, and the public domain offers still more tools. It’s possible to spend a decade or more seeking proficiency with all these tools, especially as new ones are constantly appearing (trust me on this!).

Speaking generally, Python provides a hierarchy of toolsets:

Built-ins

Built-in types like strings, lists, and dictionaries make it easy to write simple programs fast.

Python extensions

For more demanding tasks, you can extend Python by writing your own functions, modules, and classes.

Compiled extensions

Although we don’t cover this topic in this book, Python can also be extended with modules written in an external language like C or C++.

Because Python layers its toolsets, you can decide how deeply your programs need to delve into this hierarchy for any given task—you can use built-ins for simple scripts, add Python-coded extensions for larger systems, and code compiled extensions for advanced work. We’ve only covered the first two of these categories in this book, and that’s plenty to get you started doing substantial programming in Python.

Table 35-1 summarizes some of the sources of built-in or existing functionality available to Python programmers, and some topics you’ll probably be busy exploring for the remainder of your Python career. Up until now, most of our examples have been very small and self-contained. They were written that way on purpose, to help you master the basics. But now that you know all about the core language, it’s time to start learning how to use Python’s built-in interfaces to do real work. You’ll find that with a simple language like Python, common tasks are often much easier than you might expect.

Table 35-1. Python’s toolbox categories

Category

|

Examples

Object types

|

Lists, dictionaries, files, strings

Functions

|

len, range, open

Exceptions

|

IndexError, KeyError

Modules

|

os, tkinter, pickle, re

Attributes

|

__dict__, __name__, __class__

Peripheral tools

|

NumPy, SWIG, Jython, IronPython, Django, etc.

Development Tools for Larger Projects

Once you’ve mastered the basics, you’ll find your Python programs becoming substantially larger than the examples you’ve experimented with so far. For developing larger systems, a set of development tools is available in Python and the public domain. You’ve seen some of these in action, and I’ve mentioned a few others. To help you on your way, here is a summary of some of the most commonly used tools in this domain:

PyDoc and docstrings

PyDoc’s help function and HTML interfaces were introduced in Chapter 15. PyDoc provides a documentation system for your modules and objects and integrates with Python’s docstrings feature. It is a standard part of the Python system—see the library manual for more details. Be sure to also refer back to the documentation source hints listed in Chapter 4 for information on other Python information resources.

PyChecker and PyLint

Because Python is such a dynamic language, some programming errors are not reported until your program runs (e.g., syntax errors are caught when a file is run or imported). This isn’t a big drawback—as with most languages, it just means that you have to test your Python code before shipping it. At worst, with Python you essentially trade a compile phase for an initial testing phase. Furthermore, Python’s dynamic nature, automatic error messages, and exception model make it easier and quicker to find and fix errors in Python than it is in some other languages (unlike C, for example, Python does not crash on errors).

The PyChecker and PyLint systems provide support for catching a large set of common errors ahead of time, before your script runs. They serve similar roles to the lint program in C development. Some Python groups run their code through PyChecker prior to testing or delivery, to catch any lurking potential problems. In fact, the Python standard library is regularly run through PyChecker before release. PyChecker and PyLint are third-party open source packages; you can find them at http://www.python.org or the PyPI website, or via your friendly neighborhood web search engine.

PyUnit (a.k.a. unittest)

In Chapter 24, we learned how to add self-test code to a Python file by using the __name__ == '__main__' trick at the bottom of the file. For more advanced testing purposes, Python comes with two testing support tools. The first, PyUnit (called unittest in the library manual), provides an object-oriented class framework for specifying and customizing test cases and expected results. It mimics the JUnit framework for Java. This is a sophisticated class-based unit testing system; see the Python library manual for details.

doctest

The doctest standard library module provides a second and simpler approach to regression testing, based upon Python’s docstrings feature. Roughly, to use doctest, you cut and paste a log of an interactive testing session into the docstrings of your source files. doctest then extracts your docstrings, parses out the test cases and results, and reruns the tests to verify the expected results. doctest’s operation can be tailored in a variety of ways; see the library manual for more details.

IDEs

We discussed IDEs for Python in Chapter 3. IDEs such as IDLE provide a graphical environment for editing, running, debugging, and browsing your Python programs. Some advanced IDEs (such as Eclipse, Komodo, NetBeans, and Wing IDE) may support additional development tasks, including source control integration, code refactoring, project management tools, and more. See Chapter 3, the text editors page at http://www.python.org, and your favorite web search engine for more on available IDEs and GUI builders for Python.

Profilers

Because Python is so high-level and dynamic, intuitions about performance gleaned from experience with other languages usually don’t apply to Python code. To truly isolate performance bottlenecks in your code, you need to add timing logic with clock tools in the time or timeit modules, or run your code under the profile module. We saw an example of the timing modules at work when comparing iteration tools’ speeds in Chapter 20. Profiling is usually your first optimization step—profile to isolate bottlenecks, then time alternative codings of them.

profile is a standard library module that implements a source code profiler for Python; it runs a string of code you provide (e.g., a script file import, or a call to a function) and then, by default, prints a report to the standard output stream that gives performance statistics—number of calls to each function, time spent in each function, and more.

The profile module can be run as a script or imported, and it may be customized in various ways; for example, it can save run statistics to a file to be analyzed later with the pstats module. To profile interactively, import the profile module and call profile.run('code'), passing in the code you wish to profile as a string (e.g., a call to a function, or an import of an entire file). To profile from a system shell command line, use a command of the form python -m profile main.py args... (see Appendix A for more on this format). Also see Python’s standard library manuals for other profiling options; the cProfile module, for example, has identical interfaces to profile but runs with less overhead, so it may be better suited to profiling long-running programs.

Debuggers

We also discussed debugging options in Chapter 3 (see its sidebar Debugging Python Code). As a review, most development IDEs for Python support GUI-based debugging, and the Python standard library also includes a source code debugger module called pdb. This module provides a command-line interface and works much like common C language debuggers (e.g., dbx, gdb).

Much like the profiler, the pdb debugger can be run either interactively or from a command line and can be imported and called from a Python program. To use it interactively, import the module, start running code by calling a pdb function (e.g., pdb.run("main()")), and then type debugging commands from pdb’s interactive prompt. To launch pdb from a system shell command line, use a command of the form python -m pdb main.py args... (see Appendix A for more on this format). pdb also includes a useful postmortem analysis call, pdb.pm(), which starts the debugger after an exception has been encountered.

Because IDEs such as IDLE also include point-and-click debugging interfaces, pdb isn’t a critical a tool today, except when a GUI isn’t available or when more control is desired. See Chapter 3 for tips on using IDLE’s debugging GUI interfaces. Really, neither pdb nor IDEs seem to be used much in practice—as noted in Chapter 3, most programmers either insert print statements or simply read Python’s error messages (not the most high-tech of approaches, but the practical tends to win the day in the Python world!).

Shipping options

In Chapter 2, we introduced common tools for packaging Python programs. py2exe, PyInstaller, and freeze can package byte code and the Python Virtual Machine into “frozen binary” standalone executables, which don’t require that Python be installed on the target machine and fully hide your system’s code. In addition, we learned in Chapter 2 that Python programs may be shipped in their source (.py) or byte code (.pyc) forms, and that import hooks support special packaging techniques such as automatic extraction of .zip files and byte code encryption.

We also briefly met the standard library’s distutils modules, which provide packaging options for Python modules and packages, and C-coded extensions; see the Python manuals for more details. The emerging Python “eggs” third-party packaging system provides another alternative that also accounts for dependencies; search the Web for more details.

Optimization options

There are a couple of options for optimizing your programs. The Psyco system described in Chapter 2 provides a just-in-time compiler for translating Python byte code to binary machine code, and Shedskin offers a Python-to-C++ translator. You may also occasionally see .pyo optimized byte code files, generated and run with the -O Python command-line flag (discussed in Chapters 21 and 33); because this provides a very modest performance boost, however, it is not commonly used.

As a last resort, you can also move parts of your program to a compiled language such as C to boost performance; see the book Programming Python and the Python standard manuals for more on C extensions. In general, Python’s speed also improves over time, so be sure to upgrade to the faster releases when possible.

Other hints for larger projects

We’ve met a variety of language features in this text that will tend to become more useful once you start coding larger projects. These include module packages (Chapter 23), class-based exceptions (Chapter 33), class pseudoprivate attributes (Chapter 30), documentation strings (Chapter 15), module path configuration files (Chapter 21), hiding names from from * with __all__ lists and _X-style names (Chapter 24), adding self-test code with the __name__ == '__main__' trick (Chapter 24), using common design rules for functions and modules (Chapters 17, 19, and 24), using object-oriented design patterns (Chapter 30 and others), and so on.

To learn about other large-scale Python development tools available in the public domain, be sure to browse the pages at the PyPI website at http://www.python.org, and the Web at large.

Chapter Summary

This chapter wrapped up the exceptions part of the book with a survey of related statements, a look at common exception use cases, and a brief summary of commonly used development tools.

This chapter also wrapped up the core material of this book. At this point, you’ve been exposed to the full subset of Python that most programmers use. In fact, if you have read this far, you should feel free to consider yourself an official Python programmer. Be sure to pick up a t-shirt the next time you’re online.

The next and final part of this book is a collection of chapters dealing with topics that are advanced, but still in the core language category. These chapters are all optional reading, because not every Python programmer must delve into their subjects; indeed, most of you can stop here and begin exploring Python’s roles in your application domains. Frankly, application libraries tend to be more important in practice than advanced (and to some, esoteric) language features.

On the other hand, if you do need to care about things like Unicode or binary data, have to deal with API-building tools such as descriptors, decorators, and metaclasses, or just want to dig a bit further in general, the next part of the book will help you get started. The larger examples in the final part will also give you a chance to see the concepts you’ve already learned being applied in more realistic ways.

As this is the end of the core material of this book, you get a break on the chapter quiz—just one question this time. As always, though, be sure to work through this part’s closing exercises to cement what you’ve learned in the past few chapters; because the next part is optional reading, this is the final end-of-part exercises session. If you want to see some examples of how what you’ve learned comes together in real scripts drawn from common applications, check out the “solution” to exercise 4 in Appendix B.

Test Your Knowledge: Part VII Exercises

As we’ve reached the end of this part of the book, it’s time for a few exception exercises to give you a chance to practice the basics. Exceptions really are simple tools; if you get these, you’ve probably mastered exceptions.

See Part VII, Exceptions and Tools in Appendix B for the solutions.

try/ except. Write a function called oops that explicitly raises an IndexError exception when called. Then write another function that calls oops inside a try/except statement to catch the error. What happens if you change oops to raise a KeyError instead of an IndexError? Where do the names KeyError and IndexError come from? (Hint: recall that all unqualified names come from one of four scopes.)

Exception objects and lists. Change the oops function you just wrote to raise an exception you define yourself, called MyError. Identify your exception with a class. Then, extend the try statement in the catcher function to catch this exception and its instance in addition to IndexError, and print the instance you catch.

Error handling. Write a function called safe(func, *args) that runs any function with any number of arguments by using the *name arbitrary arguments call syntax, catches any exception raised while the function runs, and prints the exception using the exc_info call in the sys module. Then use your safe function to run your oops function from exercise 1 or 2. Put safe in a module file called tools.py, and pass it the oops function interactively. What kind of error messages do you get? Finally, expand safe to also print a Python stack trace when an error occurs by calling the built-in print_exc function in the standard traceback module (see the Python library reference manual for details).

Self-study examples. At the end of Appendix B, I’ve included a handful of example scripts developed as group exercises in live Python classes for you to study and run on your own in conjunction with Python’s standard manual set. These are not described, and they use tools in the Python standard library that you’ll have to research on your own. Still, for many readers, it helps to see how the concepts we’ve discussed in this book come together in real programs. If these whet your appetite for more, you can find a wealth of larger and more realistic application-level Python program examples in follow-up books like Programming Python and on the Web.

[79] A related call, os._exit, also ends a program, but via an immediate termination—it skips cleanup actions and cannot be intercepted with try/except or try/finally blocks. It is usually only used in spawned child processes, a topic beyond this book’s scope. See the library manual or follow-up texts for details.

Chapter 36. Unicode and Byte Strings

In the strings chapter in the core types part of this book (Chapter 7), I deliberately limited the scope to the subset of string topics that most Python programmers need to know about. Because the vast majority of programmers deal with simple forms of text like ASCII, they can happily work with Python’s basic str string type and its associated operations and don’t need to come to grips with more advanced string concepts. In fact, such programmers can largely ignore the string changes in Python 3.0 and continue to use strings as they may have in the past.

On the other hand, some programmers deal with more specialized types of data: non-ASCII character sets, image file contents, and so on. For those programmers (and others who may join them some day), in this chapter we’re going to fill in the rest of the Python string story and look at some more advanced concepts in Python’s string model.

Specifically, we’ll explore the basics of Python’s support for Unicode text—wide-character strings used in internationalized applications—as well as binary data—strings that represent absolute byte values. As we’ll see, the advanced string representation story has diverged in recent versions of Python:

Python 3.0 provides an alternative string type for binary data and supports Unicode text in its normal string type (ASCII is treated as a simple type of Unicode).

Python 2.6 provides an alternative string type for non-ASCII Unicode text and supports both simple text and binary data in its normal string type.

In addition, because Python’s string model has a direct impact on how you process non-ASCII files, we’ll explore the fundamentals of that related topic here as well. Finally, we’ll take a brief look at some advanced string and binary tools, such as pattern matching, object pickling, binary data packing, and XML parsing, and the ways in which they are impacted by 3.0’s string changes.

This is officially an advanced topics chapter, because not all programmers will need to delve into the worlds of Unicode encodings or binary data. If you ever need to care about processing either of these, though, you’ll find that Python’s string models provide the support you need.

String Changes in 3.0

One of the most noticeable changes in 3.0 is the mutation of string object types. In a nutshell, 2.X’s str and unicode types have morphed into 3.0’s str and bytes types, and a new mutable bytearray type has been added. The bytearray type is technically available in Python 2.6 too (though not earlier), but it’s a back-port from 3.0 and does not as clearly distinguish between text and binary content in 2.6.

Especially if you process data that is either Unicode or binary in nature, these changes can have substantial impacts on your code. In fact, as a general rule of thumb, how much you need to care about this topic depends in large part upon which of the following categories you fall into:

If you deal with non-ASCII Unicode text—for instance, in the context of internationalized applications and the results of some XML parsers—you will find support for text encodings to be different in 3.0, but also probably more direct, accessible, and seamless than in 2.6.

If you deal with binary data—for example, in the form of image or audio files or packed data processed with the struct module—you will need to understand 3.0’s new bytes object and 3.0’s different and sharper distinction between text and binary data and files.

If you fall into neither of the prior two categories, you can generally use strings in 3.0 much as you would in 2.6: with the general str string type, text files, and all the familiar string operations we studied earlier. Your strings will be encoded and decoded using your platform’s default encoding (e.g., ASCII, or UTF-8 on Windows in the U.S.—sys.getdefaultencoding() gives your default if you care to check), but you probably won’t notice.

In other words, if your text is always ASCII, you can get by with normal string objects and text files and can avoid most of the following story. As we’ll see in a moment, ASCII is a simple kind of Unicode and a subset of other encodings, so string operations and files “just work” if your programs process ASCII text.

Even if you fall into the last of the three categories just mentioned, though, a basic understanding of 3.0’s string model can help both to demystify some of the underlying behavior now, and to make mastering Unicode or binary data issues easier if they impact you in the future. Though applications are beyond our scope here, especially if you work with the Internet, files, directories, network interfaces, databases, pipes, and even GUIs, Unicode may no longer be an optional topic for you in Python 3.X.

Python 3.0’s support for Unicode and binary data is also available in 2.6, albeit in different forms. Although our main focus in this chapter is on string types in 3.0, we’ll explore some 2.6 differences along the way too. Regardless of which version you use, the tools we’ll explore here can become important in many types of programs.

String Basics

Before we look at any code, let’s begin with a general overview of Python’s string model. To understand why 3.0 changed the way it did on this front, we have to start with a brief look at how characters are actually represented in computers.

Character Encoding Schemes

Most programmers think of strings as series of characters used to represent textual data. The way characters are stored in a computer’s memory can vary, though, depending on what sort of character set must be recorded.

The ASCII standard was created in the U.S., and it defines many U.S. programmers’ notion of text strings. ASCII defines character codes from 0 through 127 and allows each character to be stored in one 8-bit byte (only 7 bits of which are actually used). For example, the ASCII standard maps the character 'a' to the integer value 97 (0x61 in hex), which is stored in a single byte in memory and files. If you wish to see how this works, Python’s ord built-in function gives the binary value for a character, and chr returns the character for a given integer code value:

>>> ord('a')         # 'a' is a byte with binary value 97 in ASCII
97
>>> hex(97)
'0x61'
>>> chr(97)          # Binary value 97 stands for character 'a'
'a'

Sometimes one byte per character isn’t enough, though. Various symbols and accented characters, for instance, do not fit into the range of possible characters defined by ASCII. To accommodate special characters, some standards allow all possible values in an 8-bit byte, 0 through 255, to represent characters, and assign the values 128 through 255 (outside ASCII’s range) to special characters. One such standard, known as Latin-1, is widely used in Western Europe. In Latin-1, character codes above 127 are assigned to accented and otherwise special characters. The character assigned to byte value 196, for example, is a specially marked non-ASCII character:

>>> 0xC4
196
>>> chr(196)
'Ä'

This standard allows for a wide array of extra special characters. Still, some alphabets define so many characters that it is impossible to represent each of them as one byte. Unicode allows more flexibility. Unicode text is commonly referred to as “wide-character” strings, because each character may be represented with multiple bytes. Unicode is typically used in internationalized programs, to represent European and Asian character sets that have more characters than 8-bit bytes can represent.

To store such rich text in computer memory, we say that characters are translated to and from raw bytes using an encoding—the rules for translating a string of Unicode characters into a sequence of bytes, and extracting a string from a sequence of bytes. More procedurally, this translation back and forth between bytes and strings is defined by two terms:

Encoding is the process of translating a string of characters into its raw bytes form, according to a desired encoding name.

Decoding is the process of translating a raw string of bytes into its character string form, according to its encoding name.

That is, we encode from string to raw bytes, and decode from raw bytes to string. For some encodings, the translation process is trivial—ASCII and Latin-1, for instance, map each character to a single byte, so no translation work is required. For other encodings, the mapping can be more complex and yield multiple bytes per character.

The widely used UTF-8 encoding, for example, allows a wide range of characters to be represented by employing a variable number of bytes scheme. Character codes less than 128 are represented as a single byte; codes between 128 and 0x7ff (2047) are turned into two bytes, where each byte has a value between 128 and 255; and codes above 0x7ff are turned into three- or four-byte sequences having values between 128 and 255. This keeps simple ASCII strings compact, sidesteps byte ordering issues, and avoids null (zero) bytes that can cause problems for C libraries and networking.

Because encodings’ character maps assign characters to the same codes for compatibility, ASCII is a subset of both Latin-1 and UTF-8; that is, a valid ASCII character string is also a valid Latin-1- and UTF-8-encoded string. This is also true when the data is stored in files: every ASCII file is a valid UTF-8 file, because ASCII is a 7-bit subset of UTF-8.

Conversely, the UTF-8 encoding is binary compatible with ASCII for all character codes less than 128. Latin-1 and UTF-8 simply allow for additional characters: Latin-1 for characters mapped to values 128 through 255 within a byte, and UTF-8 for characters that may be represented with multiple bytes. Other encodings allow wider character sets in similar ways (e.g., UTF-16 and UTF-32 format strings with 2 and 4 bytes per each character, respectively), but all of these—ASCII, Latin-1, UTF-8, and many others—are considered to be Unicode.

To Python programmers, encodings are specified as strings containing the encoding’s name. Python comes with roughly 100 different encodings; see the Python library reference for a complete list. Importing the module encodings and running help(encodings) shows you many encoding names as well; some are implemented in Python, and some in C. Some encodings have multiple names, too; for example, latin-1, iso_8859_1, and 8859 are all synonyms for the same encoding, Latin-1. We’ll revisit encodings later in this chapter, when we study techniques for writing Unicode strings in a script.

For more on the Unicode story, see the Python standard manual set. It includes a “Unicode HOWTO” in its “Python HOWTOs” section, which provides additional background that we will skip here in the interest of space.

Python’s String Types

At a more concrete level, the Python language provides string data types to represent character text in your scripts. The string types you will use in your scripts depend upon the version of Python you’re using. Python 2.X has a general string type for representing binary data and simple 8-bit text like ASCII, along with a specific type for representing multibyte Unicode text:

str for representing 8-bit text and binary data

unicode for representing wide-character Unicode text

Python 2.X’s two string types are different (unicode allows for the extra size of characters and has extra support for encoding and decoding), but their operation sets largely overlap. The str string type in 2.X is used for text that can be represented with 8-bit bytes, as well as binary data that represents absolute byte values.

By contrast, Python 3.X comes with three string object types—one for textual data and two for binary data:

str for representing Unicode text (both 8-bit and wider)

bytes for representing binary data (including encoded text)

bytearray, a mutable flavor of the bytes type

As mentioned earlier, bytearray is also available in Python 2.6, but it’s simply a back-port from 3.0 with less content-specific behavior and is generally considered a 3.0 type.

All three string types in 3.0 support similar operation sets, but they have different roles. The main goal behind this change in 3.X was to merge the normal and Unicode string types of 2.X into a single string type that supports both normal and Unicode text: developers wanted to remove the 2.X string dichotomy and make Unicode processing more natural. Given that ASCII and other 8-bit text is really a simple kind of Unicode, this convergence seems logically sound.

To achieve this, the 3.0 str type is defined as an immutable sequence of characters (not necessarily bytes), which may be either normal text such as ASCII with one byte per character, or richer character set text such as UTF-8 Unicode that may include multibyte characters. Strings processed by your script with this type are encoded per the platform default, but explicit encoding names may be provided to translate str objects to and from different schemes, both in memory and when transferring to and from files.

While 3.0’s new str type does achieve the desired string/unicode merging, many programs still need to process raw binary data that is not encoded per any text format. Image and audio files, as well as packed data used to interface with devices or C programs you might process with Python’s struct module, fall into this category. To support processing of truly binary data, therefore, a new type, bytes, also was introduced.

In 2.X, the general str type filled this binary data role, because strings were just sequences of bytes (the separate unicode type handles wide-character strings). In 3.0, the bytes type is defined as an immutable sequence of 8-bit integers representing absolute byte values. Moreover, the 3.0 bytes type supports almost all the same operations that the str type does; this includes string methods, sequence operations, and even re module pattern matching, but not string formatting.

A 3.0 bytes object really is a sequence of small integers, each of which is in the range 0 through 255; indexing a bytes returns an int, slicing one returns another bytes, and running the list built-in on one returns a list of integers, not characters. When processed with operations that assume characters, though, the contents of bytes objects are assumed to be ASCII-encoded bytes (e.g., the isalpha method assumes each byte is an ASCII character code). Further, bytes objects are printed as character strings instead of integers for convenience.

While they were at it, Python developers also added a bytearray type in 3.0. bytearray is a variant of bytes that is mutable and so supports in-place changes. It supports the usual string operations that str and bytes do, as well as many of the same in-place change operations as lists (e.g., the append and extend methods, and assignment to indexes). Assuming your strings can be treated as raw bytes, bytearray finally adds direct in-place mutability for string data—something not possible without conversion to a mutable type in Python 2, and not supported by Python 3.0’s str or bytes.

Although Python 2.6 and 3.0 offer much the same functionality, they package it differently. In fact, the mapping from 2.6 to 3.0 string types is not direct—2.6’s str equates to both str and bytes in 3.0, and 3.0’s str equates to both str and unicode in 2.6. Moreover, the mutability of 3.0’s bytearray is unique.

In practice, though, this asymmetry is not as daunting as it might sound. It boils down to the following: in 2.6, you will use str for simple text and binary data and unicode for more advanced forms of text; in 3.0, you’ll use str for any kind of text (simple and Unicode) and bytes or bytearray for binary data. In practice, the choice is often made for you by the tools you use—especially in the case of file processing tools, the topic of the next section.[80]

Text and Binary Files

File I/O (input and output) has also been revamped in 3.0 to reflect the str/bytes distinction and automatically support encoding Unicode text. Python now makes a sharp platform-independent distinction between text files and binary files:

Text files

When a file is opened in text mode, reading its data automatically decodes its content and returns it as a str; writing takes a str and automatically encodes it before transferring it to the file. Both reads and writes translate per a platform default or a provided encoding name. Text-mode files also support universal end-of-line translation and additional encoding specification arguments. Depending on the encoding name, text files may also automatically process the byte order mark sequence at the start of a file (more on this momentarily).

Binary files

When a file is opened in binary mode by adding a b (lowercase only) to the mode string argument in the built-in open call, reading its data does not decode it in any way but simply returns its content raw and unchanged, as a bytes object; writing similarly takes a bytes object and transfers it to the file unchanged. Binary-mode files also accept a bytearray object for the content to be written to the file.

Because the language sharply differentiates between str and bytes, you must decide whether your data is text or binary in nature and use either str or bytes objects to represent its content in your script, as appropriate. Ultimately, the mode in which you open a file will dictate which type of object your script will use to represent its content:

If you are processing image files, packed data created by other programs whose content you must extract, or some device data streams, chances are good that you will want to deal with it using bytes and binary-mode files. You might also opt for bytearray if you wish to update the data without making copies of it in memory.

If instead you are processing something that is textual in nature, such as program output, HTML, internationalized text, or CSV or XML files, you’ll probably want to use str and text-mode files.

Notice that the mode string argument to built-in function open (its second argument) becomes fairly crucial in Python 3.0—its content not only specifies a file processing mode, but also implies a Python object type. By adding a b to the mode string, you specify binary mode and will receive, or must provide, a bytes object to represent the file’s content when reading or writing. Without the b, your file is processed in text mode, and you’ll use str objects to represent its content in your script. For example, the modes rb, wb, and rb+ imply bytes; r, w+, and rt (the default) imply str.

Text-mode files also handle the byte order marker (BOM) sequence that may appear at the start of files under certain encoding schemes. In the UTF-16 and UTF-32 encodings, for example, the BOM specifies big- or little-endian format (essentially, which end of a bitstring is most significant). A UTF-8 text file may also include a BOM to declare that it is UTF-8 in general, but this isn’t guaranteed. When reading and writing data using these encoding schemes, Python automatically skips or writes the BOM if it is implied by a general encoding name or if you provide a more specific encoding name to force the issue. For example, the BOM is always processed for “utf-16,” the more specific encoding name “utf-16-le” species little-endian UTF-16 format, and the more specific encoding name “utf-8-sig” forces Python to both skip and write a BOM on input and output, respectively, for UTF-8 text (the general name “utf-8” does not).

We’ll learn more about BOMs and files in general in the section Handling the BOM in 3.0. First, let’s explore the implications of Python’s new Unicode string model.

Using Text and Binary Files

This section expands on the impact of Python 3.0’s string model on the file processing basics introduced earlier in the book. As mentioned earlier, the mode in which you open a file is crucial—it determines which object type you will use to represent the file’s content in your script. Text mode implies str objects, and binary mode implies bytes objects:

Text-mode files interpret file contents according to a Unicode encoding—either the default for your platform, or one whose name you pass in. By passing in an encoding name to open, you can force conversions for various types of Unicode files. Text-mode files also perform universal line-end translations: by default, all line-end forms map to the single '\n' character in your script, regardless of the platform on which you run it. As described earlier, text files also handle reading and writing the byte order mark (BOM) stored at the start-of-file in some Unicode encoding schemes.

Binary-mode files instead return file content to you raw, as a sequence of integers representing byte values, with no encoding or decoding and no line-end translations.

The second argument to open determines whether you want text or binary processing, just as it does in 2.X Python—adding a “b” to this string implies binary mode (e.g., "rb" to read binary data files). The default mode is "rt"; this is the same as "r", which means text input (just as in 2.X).

In 3.0, though, this mode argument to open also implies an object type for file content representation, regardless of the underlying platform—text files return a str for reads and expect one for writes, but binary files return a bytes for reads and expect one (or a bytearray) for writes.

Text File Basics

To demonstrate, let’s begin with basic file I/O. As long as you’re processing basic text files (e.g., ASCII) and don’t care about circumventing the platform-default encoding of strings, files in 3.0 look and feel much as they do in 2.X (for that matter, so do strings in general). The following, for instance, writes one line of text to a file and reads it back in 3.0, exactly as it would in 2.6 (note that file is no longer a built-in name in 3.0, so it’s perfectly OK to use it as a variable here):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python

# Basic text files (and strings) work the same as in 2.X

>>> file = open('temp', 'w')
>>> size = file.write('abc\n')       # Returns number of bytes written
>>> file.close()                     # Manual close to flush output buffer

>>> file = open('temp')              # Default mode is "r" (== "rt"): text input
>>> text = file.read()
>>> text
'abc\n'
>>> print(text)
abc

Text and Binary Modes in 3.0

In Python 2.6, there is no major distinction between text and binary files—both accept and return content as str strings. The only major difference is that text files automatically map \n end-of-line characters to and from \r\n on Windows, while binary files do not (I’m stringing operations together into one-liners here just for brevity):

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> open('temp', 'w').write('abd\n')         # Write in text mode: adds \r
>>> open('temp', 'r').read()                 # Read in text mode: drops \r
'abd\n'
>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()                # Read in binary mode: verbatim
'abd\r\n'

>>> open('temp', 'wb').write('abc\n')        # Write in binary mode
>>> open('temp', 'r').read()                 # \n not expanded to \r\n
'abc\n'
>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()
'abc\n'

In Python 3.0, things are bit more complex because of the distinction between str for text data and bytes for binary data. To demonstrate, let’s write a text file and read it back in both modes in 3.0. Notice that we are required to provide a str for writing, but reading gives us a str or a bytes, depending on the open mode:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python

# Write and read a text file

>>> open('temp', 'w').write('abc\n')         # Text mode output, provide a str
4

>>> open('temp', 'r').read()                 # Text mode input, returns a str
'abc\n'

>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()                # Binary mode input, returns a bytes
b'abc\r\n'

Notice how on Windows text-mode files translate the \n end-of-line character to \r\n on output; on input, text mode translates the \r\n back to \n, but binary mode does not. This is the same in 2.6, and it’s what we want for binary data (no translations should occur), although you can control this behavior with extra open arguments in 3.0 if desired.

Now let’s do the same again, but with a binary file. We provide a bytes to write in this case, and we still get back a str or a bytes, depending on the input mode:

# Write and read a binary file

>>> open('temp', 'wb').write(b'abc\n')       # Binary mode output, provide a bytes
4

>>> open('temp', 'r').read()                 # Text mode input, returns a str
'abc\n'

>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()                # Binary mode input, returns a bytes
b'abc\n'

Note that the \n end-of-line character is not expanded to \r\n in binary-mode output—again, a desired result for binary data. Type requirements and file behavior are the same even if the data we’re writing to the binary file is truly binary in nature. In the following, for example, the "\x00" is a binary zero byte and not a printable character:

# Write and read truly binary data

>>> open('temp', 'wb').write(b'a\x00c')      # Provide a bytes
3

>>> open('temp', 'r').read()                 # Receive a str
'a\x00c'

>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()                # Receive a bytes
b'a\x00c'

Binary-mode files always return contents as a bytes object, but accept either a bytes or bytearray object for writing; this naturally follows, given that bytearray is basically just a mutable variant of bytes. In fact, most APIs in Python 3.0 that accept a bytes also allow a bytearray:

# bytearrays work too

>>> BA = bytearray(b'\x01\x02\x03')

>>> open('temp', 'wb').write(BA)
3

>>> open('temp', 'r').read()
'\x01\x02\x03'

>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()
b'\x01\x02\x03'

Type and Content Mismatches

Notice that you cannot get away with violating Python’s str/bytes type distinction when it comes to files. As the following examples illustrate, we get errors (shortened here) if we try to write a bytes to a text file or a str to a binary file:

# Types are not flexible for file content

>>> open('temp', 'w').write('abc\n')         # Text mode makes and requires str
4
>>> open('temp', 'w').write(b'abc\n')
TypeError: can't write bytes to text stream

>>> open('temp', 'wb').write(b'abc\n')       # Binary mode makes and requires bytes
4
>>> open('temp', 'wb').write('abc\n')
TypeError: can't write str to binary stream

This makes sense: text has no meaning in binary terms, before it is encoded. Although it is often possible to convert between the types by encoding str and decoding bytes, as described earlier in this chapter, you will usually want to stick to either str for text data or bytes for binary data. Because the str and bytes operation sets largely intersect, the choice won’t be much of a dilemma for most programs (see the string tools coverage in the final section of this chapter for some prime examples of this).

In addition to type constraints, file content can matter in 3.0. Text-mode output files require a str instead of a bytes for content, so there is no way in 3.0 to write truly binary data to a text-mode file. Depending on the encoding rules, bytes outside the default character set can sometimes be embedded in a normal string, and they can always be written in binary mode. However, because text-mode input files in 3.0 must be able to decode content per a Unicode encoding, there is no way to read truly binary data in text mode:

# Can't read truly binary data in text mode

>>> chr(0xFF)                                   # FF is a valid char, FE is not
'ÿ'
>>> chr(0xFE)
UnicodeEncodeError: 'charmap' codec can't encode character '\xfe' in position 1...

>>> open('temp', 'w').write(b'\xFF\xFE\xFD')    # Can't use arbitrary bytes!
TypeError: can't write bytes to text stream

>>> open('temp', 'w').write('\xFF\xFE\xFD')     # Can write if embeddable in str
3
>>> open('temp', 'wb').write(b'\xFF\xFE\xFD')   # Can also write in binary mode
3

>>> open('temp', 'rb').read()                   # Can always read as binary bytes
b'\xff\xfe\xfd'

>>> open('temp', 'r').read()                    # Can't read text unless decodable!
UnicodeEncodeError: 'charmap' codec can't encode characters in position 2-3: ...

This last error stems from the fact that all text files in 3.0 are really Unicode text files, as the next section describes.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Python 3.0 has three string types: str (for Unicode text, including ASCII), bytes (for binary data with absolute byte values), and bytearray (a mutable flavor of bytes). The str type usually represents content stored on a text file, and the other two types generally represent content stored on binary files.

Python 2.6 has two main string types: str (for 8-bit text and binary data) and unicode (for wide-character text). The str type is used for both text and binary file content; unicode is used for text file content that is generally more complex than 8 bits. Python 2.6 (but not earlier) also has 3.0’s bytearray type, but it’s mostly a back-port and doesn’t exhibit the sharp text/binary distinction that it does in 3.0.

The mapping from 2.6 to 3.0 string types is not direct, because 2.6’s str equates to both str and bytes in 3.0, and 3.0’s str equates to both str and unicode in 2.6. The mutability of bytearray in 3.0 is also unique.

Python 3.0’s string types share almost all the same operations: method calls, sequence operations, and even larger tools like pattern matching work the same way. On the other hand, only str supports string formatting operations, and bytearray has an additional set of operations that perform in-place changes. The str and bytes types also have methods for encoding and decoding text, respectively.

Non-ASCII Unicode characters can be coded in a string with both hex (\xNN) and Unicode (\uNNNN, \UNNNNNNNN) escapes. On some keyboards, some non-ASCII characters—certain Latin-1 characters, for example—can also be typed directly.

In 3.0, text-mode files assume their file content is Unicode text (even if it’s ASCII) and automatically decode when reading and encode when writing. With binary-mode files, bytes are transferred to and from the file unchanged. The contents of text-mode files are usually represented as str objects in your script, and the contents of binary files are represented as bytes (or bytearray) objects. Text-mode files also handle the BOM for certain encoding types and automatically translate end-of-line sequences to and from the single \n character on input and output unless this is explicitly disabled; binary-mode files do not perform either of these steps.

To read files encoded in a different encoding than the default for your platform, simply pass the name of the file’s encoding to the open built-in in 3.0 (codecs.open() in 2.6); data will be decoded per the specified encoding when it is read from the file. You can also read in binary mode and manually decode the bytes to a string by giving an encoding name, but this involves extra work and is somewhat error-prone for multibyte characters (you may accidentally read a partial character sequence).

To create a Unicode text file in a specific encoding format, pass the desired encoding name to open in 3.0 (codecs.open() in 2.6); strings will be encoded per the desired encoding when they are written to the file. You can also manually encode a string to bytes and write it in binary mode, but this is usually extra work.

ASCII text is considered to be a kind of Unicode text, because its 7-bit range of values is a subset of most Unicode encodings. For example, valid ASCII text is also valid Latin-1 text (Latin-1 simply assigns the remaining possible values in an 8-bit byte to additional characters) and valid UTF-8 text (UTF-8 defines a variable-byte scheme for representing more characters, but ASCII characters are still represented with the same codes, in a single byte).

The impact of Python 3.0’s string types change depends upon the types of strings you use. For scripts that use simple ASCII text, there is probably no impact at all: the str string type works the same in 2.6 and 3.0 in this case. Moreover, although string-related tools in the standard library such as re, struct, pickle, and xml may technically use different types in 3.0 than in 2.6, the changes are largely irrelevant to most programs because 3.0’s str and bytes and 2.6’s str support almost identical interfaces. If you process Unicode data, the toolset you need has simply moved from 2.6’s unicode and codecs.open() to 3.0’s str and open. If you deal with binary data files, you’ll need to deal with content as bytes objects; since they have a similar interface to 2.6 strings, though, the impact should again be minimal.

[80] It may help to know that Python always stores decoded text strings in a encoding-neutral, multi-byte format in memory. All text processing occurs in this uniform internal format. Text is translated to and from an encoding-specific format only when it is transferred to or from byte strings, external text files, or APIs with specific ecoding requirements. Through Python 3.2, strings are stored internally in UTF-16 (roughly, UCS-2) format with 2 bytes per character, unless Python is configured to use 4 bytes/character. Python 3.3 and later will instead use a variable-length scheme with 1, 2, or 4 bytes per character, depending on a string's content. Either way, encoding pertains mostly to files and transfers; once loaded into a Python string, text in memory has no notion of encoding, and is simply a sequence of Unicode characters (a.k.a. "code points") stored generically.

Why Manage Attributes?

Object attributes are central to most Python programs—they are where we often store information about the entities our scripts process. Normally, attributes are simply names for objects; a person’s name attribute, for example, might be a simple string, fetched and set with basic attribute syntax:

person.name                 # Fetch attribute value
person.name = value         # Change attribute value

In most cases, the attribute lives in the object itself, or is inherited from a class from which it derives. That basic model suffices for most programs you will write in your Python career.

Sometimes, though, more flexibility is required. Suppose you’ve written a program to use a name attribute directly, but then your requirements change—for example, you decide that names should be validated with logic when set or mutated in some way when fetched. It’s straightforward to code methods to manage access to the attribute’s value (valid and transform are abstract here):

class Person:
    def getName(self):
        if not valid():
            raise TypeError('cannot fetch name')
        else:
            return self.name.transform()
    def setName(self, value):
         if not valid(value):
            raise TypeError('cannot change name')
        else:
            self.name = transform(value)

person = Person()
person.getName()
person.setName('value')

However, this also requires changing all the places where names are used in the entire program—a possibly nontrivial task. Moreover, this approach requires the program to be aware of how values are exported: as simple names or called methods. If you begin with a method-based interface to data, clients are immune to changes; if you do not, they can become problematic.

This issue can crop up more often than you might expect. The value of a cell in a spreadsheet-like program, for instance, might begin its life as a simple discrete value, but later mutate into an arbitrary calculation. Since an object’s interface should be flexible enough to support such future changes without breaking existing code, switching to methods later is less than ideal.

Inserting Code to Run on Attribute Access

A better solution would allow you to run code automatically on attribute access, if needed. At various points in this book, we’ve met Python tools that allow our scripts to dynamically compute attribute values when fetching them and validate or change attribute values when storing them. In this chapter, were going to expand on the tools already introduced, explore other available tools, and study some larger use-case examples in this domain. Specifically, this chapter presents:

The __getattr__ and __setattr__ methods, for routing undefined attribute fetches and all attribute assignments to generic handler methods.

The __getattribute__ method, for routing all attribute fetches to a generic handler method in new-style classes in 2.6 and all classes in 3.0.

The property built-in, for routing specific attribute access to get and set handler functions, known as properties.

The descriptor protocol, for routing specific attribute accesses to instances of classes with arbitrary get and set handler methods.

The first and third of these were briefly introduced in Part VI; the others are new topics introduced and covered here.

As we’ll see, all four techniques share goals to some degree, and it’s usually possible to code a given problem using any one of them. They do differ in some important ways, though. For example, the last two techniques listed here apply to specific attributes, whereas the first two are generic enough to be used by delegation-based classes that must route arbitrary attributes to wrapped objects. As we’ll see, all four schemes also differ in both complexity and aesthetics, in ways you must see in action to judge for yourself.

Besides studying the specifics behind the four attribute interception techniques listed in this section, this chapter also presents an opportunity to explore larger programs than we’ve seen elsewhere in this book. The CardHolder case study at the end, for example, should serve as a self-study example of larger classes in action. We’ll also be using some of the techniques outlined here in the next chapter to code decorators, so be sure you have at least a general understanding of these topics before you move on.

Properties

The property protocol allows us to route a specific attribute’s get and set operations to functions or methods we provide, enabling us to insert code to be run automatically on attribute access, intercept attribute deletions, and provide documentation for the attributes if desired.

Properties are created with the property built-in and are assigned to class attributes, just like method functions. As such, they are inherited by subclasses and instances, like any other class attributes. Their access-interception functions are provided with the self instance argument, which grants access to state information and class attributes available on the subject instance.

A property manages a single, specific attribute; although it can’t catch all attribute accesses generically, it allows us to control both fetch and assignment accesses and enables us to change an attribute from simple data to a computation freely, without breaking existing code. As we’ll see, properties are strongly related to descriptors; they are essentially a restricted form of them.

The Basics

A property is created by assigning the result of a built-in function to a class attribute:

attribute = property(fget, fset, fdel, doc)

None of this built-in’s arguments are required, and all default to None if not passed; such operations are not supported, and attempting them will raise an exception. When using them, we pass fget a function for intercepting attribute fetches, fset a function for assignments, and fdel a function for attribute deletions; the doc argument receives a documentation string for the attribute, if desired (otherwise the property copies the docstring of fget, if provided, which defaults to None). fget returns the computed attribute value, and fset and fdel return nothing (really, None).

This built-in call returns a property object, which we assign to the name of the attribute to be managed in the class scope, where it will be inherited by every instance.

A First Example

To demonstrate how this translates to working code, the following class uses a property to trace access to an attribute named name; the actual stored data is named _name so it does not clash with the property:

class Person:                       # Use (object) in 2.6
    def __init__(self, name):
        self._name = name
    def getName(self):
        print('fetch...')
        return self._name
    def setName(self, value):
        print('change...')
        self._name = value
    def delName(self):
        print('remove...')
        del self._name
    name = property(getName, setName, delName, "name property docs")

bob = Person('Bob Smith')           # bob has a managed attribute
print(bob.name)                     # Runs getName
bob.name = 'Robert Smith'           # Runs setName
print(bob.name)
del bob.name                        # Runs delName

print('-'*20)
sue = Person('Sue Jones')           # sue inherits property too
print(sue.name)
print(Person.name.__doc__)          # Or help(Person.name)

Properties are available in both 2.6 and 3.0, but they require new-style object derivation in 2.6 to work correctly for assignments—add object as a superclass here to run this in 2.6 (you can list the superclass in 3.0 too, but it’s implied and not required).

This particular property doesn’t do much—it simply intercepts and traces an attribute—but it serves to demonstrate the protocol. When this code is run, two instances inherit the property, just as they would any other attribute attached to their class. However, their attribute accesses are caught:

fetch...
Bob Smith
change...
fetch...
Robert Smith
remove...
--------------------
fetch...
Sue Jones
name property docs

Like all class attributes, properties are inherited by both instances and lower subclasses. If we change our example as follows, for example:

class Super:
    ...the original Person class code...
    name = property(getName, setName, delName, 'name property docs')

class Person(Super):
    pass                            # Properties are inherited

bob = Person('Bob Smith')
...rest unchanged...

the output is the same—the Person subclass inherits the name property from Super, and the bob instance gets it from Person. In terms of inheritance, properties work the same as normal methods; because they have access to the self instance argument, they can access instance state information like methods, as the next section demonstrates.

Computed Attributes

The example in the prior section simply traces attribute accesses. Usually, though, properties do much more—computing the value of an attribute dynamically when fetched, for example. The following example illustrates:

class PropSquare:
    def __init__(self, start):
        self.value = start
    def getX(self):                         # On attr fetch
        return self.value ** 2
    def setX(self, value):                  # On attr assign
        self.value = value
    X = property(getX, setX)                # No delete or docs

P = PropSquare(3)       # 2 instances of class with property
Q = PropSquare(32)      # Each has different state information

print(P.X)              # 3 ** 2
P.X = 4
print(P.X)              # 4 ** 2
print(Q.X)              # 32 ** 2

This class defines an attribute X that is accessed as though it were static data, but really runs code to compute its value when fetched. The effect is much like an implicit method call. When the code is run, the value is stored in the instance as state information, but each time we fetch it via the managed attribute, its value is automatically squared:

9
16
1024

Notice that we’ve made two different instances—because property methods automatically receive a self argument, they have access to the state information stored in instances. In our case, this mean the fetch computes the square of the subject instance’s data.

Coding Properties with Decorators

Although we’re saving additional details until the next chapter, we introduced function decorator basics earlier, in Chapter 31. Recall that the function decorator syntax:

@decorator
def func(args): ...

is automatically translated to this equivalent by Python, to rebind the function name to the result of the decorator callable:

def func(args): ...
func = decorator(func)

Because of this mapping, it turns out that the property built-in can serve as a decorator, to define a function that will run automatically when an attribute is fetched:

class Person:
    @property
    def name(self): ...             # Rebinds: name = property(name)

When run, the decorated method is automatically passed to the first argument of the property built-in. This is really just alternative syntax for creating a property and rebinding the attribute name manually:

class Person:
    def name(self): ...
    name = property(name)

As of Python 2.6, property objects also have getter, setter, and deleter methods that assign the corresponding property accessor methods and return a copy of the property itself. We can use these to specify components of properties by decorating normal methods too, though the getter component is usually filled in automatically by the act of creating the property itself:

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name):
        self._name = name

    @property
    def name(self):                 # name = property(name)
        "name property docs"
        print('fetch...')
        return self._name

    @name.setter
    def name(self, value):          # name = name.setter(name)
        print('change...')
        self._name = value

    @name.deleter
    def name(self):                 # name = name.deleter(name)
        print('remove...')
        del self._name

bob = Person('Bob Smith')           # bob has a managed attribute
print(bob.name)                     # Runs name getter (name 1)
bob.name = 'Robert Smith'           # Runs name setter (name 2)
print(bob.name)
del bob.name                        # Runs name deleter (name 3)

print('-'*20)
sue = Person('Sue Jones')           # sue inherits property too
print(sue.name)
print(Person.name.__doc__)          # Or help(Person.name)

In fact, this code is equivalent to the first example in this section—decoration is just an alternative way to code properties in this case. When it’s run, the results are the same:

fetch...
Bob Smith
change...
fetch...
Robert Smith
remove...
--------------------
fetch...
Sue Jones
name property docs

Compared to manual assignment of property results, in this case using decorators to code properties requires just three extra lines of code (a negligible difference). As is so often the case with alternative tools, the choice between the two techniques is largely subjective.

Descriptors

Descriptors provide an alternative way to intercept attribute access; they are strongly related to the properties discussed in the prior section. In fact, a property is a kind of descriptor—technically speaking, the property built-in is just a simplified way to create a specific type of descriptor that runs method functions on attribute accesses.

Functionally speaking, the descriptor protocol allows us to route a specific attribute’s get and set operations to methods of a separate class object that we provide: they provide a way to insert code to be run automatically on attribute access, and they allow us to intercept attribute deletions and provide documentation for the attributes if desired.

Descriptors are created as independent classes, and they are assigned to class attributes just like method functions. Like any other class attribute, they are inherited by subclasses and instances. Their access-interception methods are provided with both a self for the descriptor itself, and the instance of the client class. Because of this, they can retain and use state information of their own, as well as state information of the subject instance. For example, a descriptor may call methods available in the client class, as well as descriptor-specific methods it defines.

Like a property, a descriptor manages a single, specific attribute; although it can’t catch all attribute accesses generically, it provides control over both fetch and assignment accesses and allows us to change an attribute freely from simple data to a computation without breaking existing code. Properties really are just a convenient way to create a specific kind of descriptor, and as we shall see, they can be coded as descriptors directly.

Whereas properties are fairly narrow in scope, descriptors provide a more general solution. For instance, because they are coded as normal classes, descriptors have their own state, may participate in descriptor inheritance hierarchies, can use composition to aggregate objects, and provide a natural structure for coding internal methods and attribute documentation strings.

The Basics

As mentioned previously, descriptors are coded as separate classes and provide specially named accessor methods for the attribute access operations they wish to intercept—get, set, and deletion methods in the descriptor class are automatically run when the attribute assigned to the descriptor class instance is accessed in the corresponding way:

class Descriptor:
    "docstring goes here"
    def __get__(self, instance, owner): ...        # Return attr value
    def __set__(self, instance, value): ...        # Return nothing (None)
    def __delete__(self, instance): ...            # Return nothing (None)

Classes with any of these methods are considered descriptors, and their methods are special when one of their instances is assigned to another class’s attribute—when the attribute is accessed, they are automatically invoked. If any of these methods are absent, it generally means that the corresponding type of access is not supported. Unlike with properties, however, omitting a __set__ allows the name to be redefined in an instance, thereby hiding the descriptor—to make an attribute read-only, you must define __set__ to catch assignments and raise an exception.

Descriptor method arguments

Before we code anything realistic, let’s take a brief look at some fundamentals. All three descriptor methods outlined in the prior section are passed both the descriptor class instance (self) and the instance of the client class to which the descriptor instance is attached (instance).

The __get__ access method additionally receives an owner argument, specifying the class to which the descriptor instance is attached. Its instance argument is either the instance through which the attribute was accessed (for instance.attr), or None when the attribute is accessed through the owner class directly (for class.attr). The former of these generally computes a value for instance access, and the latter usually returns self if descriptor object access is supported.

For example, in the following, when X.attr is fetched, Python automatically runs the __get__ method of the Descriptor class to which the Subject.attr class attribute is assigned (as with properties, in Python 2.6 we must derive from object to use descriptors here; in 3.0 this is implied, but doesn’t hurt):

>>> class Descriptor(object):
...     def __get__(self, instance, owner):
...         print(self, instance, owner, sep='\n')
...
>>> class Subject:
...     attr = Descriptor()             # Descriptor instance is class attr
...
>>> X = Subject()

>>> X.attr
<__main__.Descriptor object at 0x0281E690>
<__main__.Subject object at 0x028289B0>
<class '__main__.Subject'>

>>> Subject.attr
<__main__.Descriptor object at 0x0281E690>
None
<class '__main__.Subject'>

Notice the arguments automatically passed in to the __get__ method in the first attribute fetch—when X.attr is fetched, it’s as though the following translation occurs (though the Subject.attr here doesn’t invoke __get__ again):

X.attr  ->  Descriptor.__get__(Subject.attr, X, Subject)

The descriptor knows it is being accessed directly when its instance argument is None.

Read-only descriptors

As mentioned earlier, unlike with properties, with descriptors simply omitting the __set__ method isn’t enough to make an attribute read-only, because the descriptor name can be assigned to an instance. In the following, the attribute assignment to X.a stores a in the instance object X, thereby hiding the descriptor stored in class C:

>>> class D:
...     def __get__(*args): print('get')
...
>>> class C:
...     a = D()
...
>>> X = C()
>>> X.a                                 # Runs inherited descriptor __get__
get
>>> C.a
get
>>> X.a = 99                            # Stored on X, hiding C.a
>>> X.a
99
>>> list(X.__dict__.keys())
['a']
>>> Y = C()
>>> Y.a                                 # Y still inherits descriptor
get
>>> C.a
get

This is the way all instance attribute assignments work in Python, and it allows classes to selectively override class-level defaults in their instances. To make a descriptor-based attribute read-only, catch the assignment in the descriptor class and raise an exception to prevent attribute assignment—when assigning an attribute that is a descriptor, Python effectively bypasses the normal instance-level assignment behavior and routes the operation to the descriptor object:

>>> class D:
...     def __get__(*args): print('get')
...     def __set__(*args): raise AttributeError('cannot set')
...
>>> class C:
...     a = D()
...
>>> X = C()
>>> X.a                                 # Routed to C.a.__get__
get
>>> X.a = 99                            # Routed to C.a.__set__
AttributeError: cannot set

Note

Also be careful not to confuse the descriptor __delete__ method with the general __del__ method. The former is called on attempts to delete the managed attribute name on an instance of the owner class; the latter is the general instance destructor method, run when an instance of any kind of class is about to be garbage collected. __delete__ is more closely related to the __delattr__ generic attribute deletion method we’ll meet later in this chapter. See Chapter 29 for more on operator overloading methods.

A First Example

To see how this all comes together in more realistic code, let’s get started with the same first example we wrote for properties. The following defines a descriptor that intercepts access to an attribute named name in its clients. Its methods use their instance argument to access state information in the subject instance, where the name string is actually stored. Like properties, descriptors work properly only for new-style classes, so be sure to derive both classes in the following from object if you’re using 2.6:

class Name:                             # Use (object) in 2.6
    "name descriptor docs"
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):
        print('fetch...')
        return instance._name
    def __set__(self, instance, value):
        print('change...')
        instance._name = value
    def __delete__(self, instance):
        print('remove...')
        del instance._name

class Person:                           # Use (object) in 2.6
    def __init__(self, name):
        self._name = name
    name = Name()                       # Assign descriptor to attr

bob = Person('Bob Smith')               # bob has a managed attribute
print(bob.name)                         # Runs Name.__get__
bob.name = 'Robert Smith'               # Runs Name.__set__
print(bob.name)
del bob.name                            # Runs Name.__delete__

print('-'*20)
sue = Person('Sue Jones')               # sue inherits descriptor too
print(sue.name)
print(Name.__doc__)                     # Or help(Name)

Notice in this code how we assign an instance of our descriptor class to a class attribute in the client class; because of this, it is inherited by all instances of the class, just like a class’s methods. Really, we must assign the descriptor to a class attribute like this—it won’t work if assigned to a self instance attribute instead. When the descriptor’s __get__ method is run, it is passed three objects to define its context:

self is the Name class instance.

instance is the Person class instance.

owner is the Person class.

When this code is run the descriptor’s methods intercept accesses to the attribute, much like the property version. In fact, the output is the same again:

fetch...
Bob Smith
change...
fetch...
Robert Smith
remove...
--------------------
fetch...
Sue Jones
name descriptor docs

Also like in the property example, our descriptor class instance is a class attribute and thus is inherited by all instances of the client class and any subclasses. If we change the Person class in our example to the following, for instance, the output of our script is the same:

...
class Super:
    def __init__(self, name):
        self._name = name
    name = Name()

class Person(Super):                            # Descriptors are inherited
   pass
...

Also note that when a descriptor class is not useful outside the client class, it’s perfectly reasonable to embed the descriptor’s definition inside its client syntactically. Here’s what our example looks like if we use a nested class:

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name):
        self._name = name

    class Name:                                 # Using a nested class
        "name descriptor docs"
        def __get__(self, instance, owner):
            print('fetch...')
            return instance._name
        def __set__(self, instance, value):
            print('change...')
            instance._name = value
        def __delete__(self, instance):
            print('remove...')
            del instance._name
    name = Name()

When coded this way, Name becomes a local variable in the scope of the Person class statement, such that it won’t clash with any names outside the class. This version works the same as the original—we’ve simply moved the descriptor class definition into the client class’s scope—but the last line of the testing code must change to fetch the docstring from its new location:

...
print(Person.Name.__doc__)     # Differs: not Name.__doc__ outside class

Computed Attributes

As was the case when using properties, our first descriptor example of the prior section didn’t do much—it simply printed trace messages for attribute accesses. In practice, descriptors can also be used to compute attribute values each time they are fetched. The following illustrates—it’s a rehash of the same example we coded for properties, which uses a descriptor to automatically square an attribute’s value each time it is fetched:

class DescSquare:
    def __init__(self, start):                  # Each desc has own state
        self.value = start
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):         # On attr fetch
        return self.value ** 2
    def __set__(self, instance, value):         # On attr assign
        self.value = value                      # No delete or docs

class Client1:
    X = DescSquare(3)          # Assign descriptor instance to class attr

class Client2:
    X = DescSquare(32)         # Another instance in another client class
                               # Could also code 2 instances in same class
c1 = Client1()
c2 = Client2()

print(c1.X)                    # 3 ** 2
c1.X = 4
print(c1.X)                    # 4 ** 2
print(c2.X)                    # 32 ** 2

When run, the output of this example is the same as that of the original property-based version, but here a descriptor class object is intercepting the attribute accesses:

9
16
1024

Using State Information in Descriptors

If you study the two descriptor examples we’ve written so far, you might notice that they get their information from different places—the first (the name attribute example) uses data stored on the client instance, and the second (the attribute squaring example) uses data attached to the descriptor object itself. In fact, descriptors can use both instance state and descriptor state, or any combination thereof:

Descriptor state is used to manage data internal to the workings of the descriptor.

Instance state records information related to and possibly created by the client class.

Descriptor methods may use either, but descriptor state often makes it unnecessary to use special naming conventions to avoid name collisions for descriptor data stored on an instance. For example, the following descriptor attaches information to its own instance, so it doesn’t clash with that on the client class’s instance:

class DescState:                           # Use descriptor state
    def __init__(self, value):
        self.value = value
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):    # On attr fetch
        print('DescState get')
        return self.value * 10
    def __set__(self, instance, value):    # On attr assign
        print('DescState set')
        self.value = value

# Client class

class CalcAttrs:
    X = DescState(2)                       # Descriptor class attr
    Y = 3                                  # Class attr
    def __init__(self):
        self.Z = 4                         # Instance attr

obj = CalcAttrs()
print(obj.X, obj.Y, obj.Z)                 # X is computed, others are not
obj.X = 5                                  # X assignment is intercepted
obj.Y = 6
obj.Z = 7
print(obj.X, obj.Y, obj.Z)

This code’s value information lives only in the descriptor, so there won’t be a collision if the same name is used in the client’s instance. Notice that only the descriptor attribute is managed here—get and set accesses to X are intercepted, but accesses to Y and Z are not (Y is attached to the client class and Z to the instance). When this code is run, X is computed when fetched:

DescState get
20 3 4
DescState set
DescState get
50 6 7

It’s also feasible for a descriptor to store or use an attribute attached to the client class’s instance, instead of itself. Unlike data stored in the descriptor itself, this allows for data that can vary per client class instance. The descriptor in the following example assumes the instance has an attribute _Y attached by the client class, and uses it to compute the value of the attribute it represents:

class InstState:                           # Using instance state
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):
        print('InstState get')             # Assume set by client class
        return instance._Y * 100
    def __set__(self, instance, value):
        print('InstState set')
        instance._Y = value

# Client class

class CalcAttrs:
    X = DescState(2)                       # Descriptor class attr
    Y = InstState()                        # Descriptor class attr
    def __init__(self):
        self._Y = 3                        # Instance attr
        self.Z  = 4                        # Instance attr

obj = CalcAttrs()
print(obj.X, obj.Y, obj.Z)                 # X and Y are computed, Z is not
obj.X = 5                                  # X and Y assignments intercepted
obj.Y = 6
obj.Z = 7
print(obj.X, obj.Y, obj.Z)

This time, X and Y are both assigned to descriptors and computed when fetched (X is assigned the descriptor of the prior example). The new descriptor here has no information itself, but it uses an attribute assumed to exist in the instance—that attribute is named _Y, to avoid collisions with the name of the descriptor itself. When this version is run the results are similar, but a second attribute is managed, using state that lives in the instance instead of the descriptor:

DescState get
InstState get
20 300 4
DescState set
InstState set
DescState get
InstState get
50 600 7

Both descriptor and instance state have roles. In fact, this is a general advantage that descriptors have over properties—because they have state of their own, they can easily retain data internally, without adding it to the namespace of the client instance object.

How Properties and Descriptors Relate

As mentioned earlier, properties and descriptors are strongly related—the property built-in is just a convenient way to create a descriptor. Now that you know how both work, you should also be able to see that it’s possible to simulate the property built-in with a descriptor class like the following:

class Property:
    def __init__(self, fget=None, fset=None, fdel=None, doc=None):
        self.fget = fget
        self.fset = fset
        self.fdel = fdel                                  # Save unbound methods
        self.__doc__ = doc                                # or other callables

    def __get__(self, instance, instancetype=None):
        if instance is None:
            return self
        if self.fget is None:
            raise AttributeError("can't get attribute")
        return self.fget(instance)                        # Pass instance to self
                                                          # in property accessors
    def __set__(self, instance, value):
        if self.fset is None:
            raise AttributeError("can't set attribute")
        self.fset(instance, value)

    def __delete__(self, instance):
        if self.fdel is None:
            raise AttributeError("can't delete attribute")
        self.fdel(instance)

class Person:
    def getName(self): ...
    def setName(self, value): ...
    name = Property(getName, setName)                     # Use like property()

This Property class catches attribute accesses with the descriptor protocol and routes requests to functions or methods passed in and saved in descriptor state when the class is created. Attribute fetches, for example, are routed from the Person class, to the Property class’s __get__ method, and back to the Person class’s getName. With descriptors, this “just works.”

Note that this descriptor class equivalent only handles basic property usage, though; to use @ decorator syntax to also specify set and delete operations, our Property class would also have to be extended with setter and deleter methods, which would save the decorated accessor function and return the property object (self should suffice). Since the property built-in already does this, we’ll omit a formal coding of this extension here.

Also note that descriptors are used to implement Python’s __slots__; instance attribute dictionaries are avoided by intercepting slot names with descriptors stored at the class level. See Chapter 31 for more on slots.

Note

In Chapter 38, we’ll also make use of descriptors to implement function decorators that apply to both functions and methods. As you’ll see there, because descriptors receive both descriptor and subject class instances they work well in this role, though nested functions are usually a simpler solution.

__getattr__ and __getattribute__

So far, we’ve studied properties and descriptors—tools for managing specific attributes. The __getattr__ and __getattribute__ operator overloading methods provide still other ways to intercept attribute fetches for class instances. Like properties and descriptors, they allow us to insert code to be run automatically when attributes are accessed; as we’ll see, though, these two methods can be used in more general ways.

Attribute fetch interception comes in two flavors, coded with two different methods:

__getattr__ is run for undefined attributes—that is, attributes not stored on an instance or inherited from one of its classes.

__getattribute__ is run for every attribute, so when using it you must be cautious to avoid recursive loops by passing attribute accesses to a superclass.

We met the former of these in Chapter 29; it’s available for all Python versions. The latter of these is available for new-style classes in 2.6, and for all (implicitly new-style) classes in 3.0. These two methods are representatives of a set of attribute interception methods that also includes __setattr__ and __delattr__. Because these methods have similar roles, we will generally treat them as a single topic here.

Unlike properties and descriptors, these methods are part of Python’s operator overloading protocol—specially named methods of a class, inherited by subclasses, and run automatically when instances are used in the implied built-in operation. Like all methods of a class, they each receive a first self argument when called, giving access to any required instance state information or other methods of the class.

The __getattr__ and __getattribute__ methods are also more generic than properties and descriptors—they can be used to intercept access to any (or even all) instance attribute fetches, not just the specific name to which they are assigned. Because of this, these two methods are well suited to general delegation-based coding patterns—they can be used to implement wrapper objects that manage all attribute accesses for an embedded object. By contrast, we must define one property or descriptor for every attribute we wish to intercept.

Finally, these two methods are more narrowly focused than the alternatives we considered earlier: they intercept attribute fetches only, not assignments. To also catch attribute changes by assignment, we must code a __setattr__ method—an operator overloading method run for every attribute fetch, which must take care to avoid recursive loops by routing attribute assignments through the instance namespace dictionary.

Although much less common, we can also code a __delattr__ overloading method (which must avoid looping in the same way) to intercept attribute deletions. By contrast, properties and descriptors catch get, set, and delete operations by design.

Most of these operator overloading methods were introduced earlier in the book; here, we’ll expand on their usage and study their roles in larger contexts.

The Basics

__getattr__ and __setattr__ were introduced in Chapters 29 and 31, and __getattribute__ was mentioned briefly in Chapter 31. In short, if a class defines or inherits the following methods, they will be run automatically when an instance is used in the context described by the comments to the right:

def __getattr__(self, name):        # On undefined attribute fetch [obj.name]
def __getattribute__(self, name):   # On all attribute fetch [obj.name]
def __setattr__(self, name, value): # On all attribute assignment [obj.name=value]
def __delattr__(self, name):        # On all attribute deletion [del obj.name]

In all of these, self is the subject instance object as usual, name is the string name of the attribute being accessed, and value is the object being assigned to the attribute. The two get methods normally return an attribute’s value, and the other two return nothing (None). For example, to catch every attribute fetch, we can use either of the first two methods above, and to catch every attribute assignment we can use the third:

class Catcher:
    def __getattr__(self, name):
        print('Get:', name)
    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        print('Set:', name, value)

X = Catcher()
X.job                               # Prints "Get: job"
X.pay                               # Prints "Get: pay"
X.pay = 99                          # Prints "Set: pay 99"

Such a coding structure can be used to implement the delegation design pattern we met earlier, in Chapter 30. Because all attribute are routed to our interception methods generically, we can validate and pass them along to embedded, managed objects. The following class (borrowed from Chapter 30), for example, traces every attribute fetch made to another object passed to the wrapper class:

class Wrapper:
    def __init__(self, object):
        self.wrapped = object                    # Save object
    def __getattr__(self, attrname):
        print('Trace:', attrname)                # Trace fetch
        return getattr(self.wrapped, attrname)   # Delegate fetch

There is no such analog for properties and descriptors, short of coding accessors for every possible attribute in every possibly wrapped object.

Avoiding loops in attribute interception methods

These methods are generally straightforward to use; their only complex part is the potential for looping (a.k.a. recursing). Because __getattr__ is called for undefined attributes only, it can freely fetch other attributes within its own code. However, because __getattribute__ and __setattr__ are run for all attributes, their code needs to be careful when accessing other attributes to avoid calling themselves again and triggering a recursive loop.

For example, another attribute fetch run inside a __getattribute__ method’s code will trigger __getattribute__ again, and the code will loop until memory is exhausted:

    def __getattribute__(self, name):
        x = self.other                                # LOOPS!

To work around this, route the fetch through a higher superclass instead to skip this level’s version—the object class is always a superclass, and it serves well in this role:

    def __getattribute__(self, name):
        x = object.__getattribute__(self, 'other')    # Force higher to avoid me

For __setattr__, the situation is similar; assigning any attribute inside this method triggers __setattr__ again and creates a similar loop:

    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        self.other = value                            # LOOPS!

To work around this problem, assign the attribute as a key in the instance’s __dict__ namespace dictionary instead. This avoids direct attribute assignment:

    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        self.__dict__['other'] = value                # Use atttr dict to avoid me

Although it’s a less common approach, __setattr__ can also pass its own attribute assignments to a higher superclass to avoid looping, just like __getattribute__:

    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        object.__setattr__(self, 'other', value)      # Force higher to avoid me

By contrast, though, we cannot use the __dict__ trick to avoid loops in __getattribute__:

    def __getattribute__(self, name):
        x = self.__dict__['other']                    # LOOPS!

Fetching the __dict__ attribute itself triggers __getattribute__ again, causing a recursive loop. Strange but true!

The __delattr__ method is rarely used in practice, but when it is, it is called for every attribute deletion (just as __setattr__ is called for every attribute assignment). Therefore, you must take care to avoid loops when deleting attributes, by using the same techniques: namespace dictionaries or superclass method calls.

A First Example

All this is not nearly as complicated as the prior section may have implied. To see how to put these ideas to work, here is the same first example we used for properties and descriptors in action again, this time implemented with attribute operator overloading methods. Because these methods are so generic, we test attribute names here to know when a managed attribute is being accessed; others are allowed to pass normally:

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name):               # On [Person()]
        self._name = name                   # Triggers __setattr__!

    def __getattr__(self, attr):            # On [obj.undefined]
        if attr == 'name':                  # Intercept name: not stored
            print('fetch...')
            return self._name               # Does not loop: real attr
        else:                               # Others are errors
            raise AttributeError(attr)

    def __setattr__(self, attr, value):     # On [obj.any = value]
        if attr == 'name':
            print('change...')
            attr = '_name'                  # Set internal name
        self.__dict__[attr] = value         # Avoid looping here

    def __delattr__(self, attr):            # On [del obj.any]
        if attr == 'name':
            print('remove...')
            attr = '_name'                  # Avoid looping here too
        del self.__dict__[attr]             # but much less common

bob = Person('Bob Smith')           # bob has a managed attribute
print(bob.name)                     # Runs __getattr__
bob.name = 'Robert Smith'           # Runs __setattr__
print(bob.name)
del bob.name                        # Runs __delattr__

print('-'*20)
sue = Person('Sue Jones')           # sue inherits property too
print(sue.name)
#print(Person.name.__doc__)         # No equivalent here

Notice that the attribute assignment in the __init__ constructor triggers __setattr__ too—this method catches every attribute assignment, even those within the class itself. When this code is run, the same output is produced, but this time it’s the result of Python’s normal operator overloading mechanism and our attribute interception methods:

fetch...
Bob Smith
change...
fetch...
Robert Smith
remove...
--------------------
fetch...
Sue Jones

Also note that, unlike with properties and descriptors, there’s no direct notion of specifying documentation for our attribute here; managed attributes exist within the code of our interception methods, not as distinct objects.

To achieve exactly the same results with __getattribute__, replace __getattr__ in the example with the following; because it catches all attribute fetches, this version must be careful to avoid looping by passing new fetches to a superclass, and it can’t generally assume unknown names are errors:

# Replace __getattr__ with this

    def __getattribute__(self, attr):                 # On [obj.any]
        if attr == 'name':                            # Intercept all names
            print('fetch...')
            attr = '_name'                            # Map to internal name
        return object.__getattribute__(self, attr)    # Avoid looping here

This example is equivalent to that coded for properties and descriptors, but it’s a bit artificial, and it doesn’t really highlight these tools in practice. Because they are generic, __getattr__ and __getattribute__ are probably more commonly used in delegation-base code (as sketched earlier), where attribute access is validated and routed to an embedded object. Where just a single attribute must be managed, properties and descriptors might do as well or better.

Computed Attributes

As before, our prior example doesn’t really do anything but trace attribute fetches; it’s not much more work to compute an attribute’s value when fetched. As for properties and descriptors, the following creates a virtual attribute X that runs a calculation when fetched:

class AttrSquare:
    def __init__(self, start):
        self.value = start                            # Triggers __setattr__!

    def __getattr__(self, attr):                      # On undefined attr fetch
        if attr == 'X':
            return self.value ** 2                    # value is not undefined
        else:
            raise AttributeError(attr)

    def __setattr__(self, attr, value):               # On all attr assignments
        if attr == 'X':
            attr = 'value'
        self.__dict__[attr] = value

A = AttrSquare(3)       # 2 instances of class with overloading
B = AttrSquare(32)      # Each has different state information

print(A.X)              # 3 ** 2
A.X = 4
print(A.X)              # 4 ** 2
print(B.X)              # 32 ** 2

Running this code results in the same output that we got earlier when using properties and descriptors, but this script’s mechanics are based on generic attribute interception methods:

9
16
1024

As before, we can achieve the same effect with __getattribute__ instead of __getattr__; the following replaces the fetch method with a __getattribute__ and changes the __setattr__ assignment method to avoid looping by using direct superclass method calls instead of __dict__ keys:

class AttrSquare:
    def __init__(self, start):
        self.value = start                  # Triggers __setattr__!

    def __getattribute__(self, attr):       # On all attr fetches
        if attr == 'X':
            return self.value ** 2          # Triggers __getattribute__ again!
        else:
            return object.__getattribute__(self, attr)

    def __setattr__(self, attr, value):     # On all attr assignments
        if attr == 'X':
            attr = 'value'
        object.__setattr__(self, attr, value)

When this version is run, the results are the same again. Notice the implicit routing going on in inside this class’s methods:

self.value=start inside the constructor triggers __setattr__

self.value inside __getattribute__ triggers __getattribute__ again

In fact, __getattribute__ is run twice each time we fetch attribute X. This doesn’t happen in the __getattr__ version, because the value attribute is not undefined. If you care about speed and want to avoid this, change __getattribute__ to use the superclass to fetch value as well:

    def __getattribute__(self, attr):
        if attr == 'X':
            return object.__getattribute__(self, 'value') ** 2

Of course, this still incurs a call to the superclass method, but not an additional recursive call before we get there. Add print calls to these methods to trace how and when they run.

__getattr__ and __getattribute__ Compared

To summarize the coding differences between __getattr__ and __getattribute__, the following example uses both to implement three attributes—attr1 is a class attribute, attr2 is an instance attribute, and attr3 is a virtual managed attribute computed when fetched:

class GetAttr:
    attr1 = 1
    def __init__(self):
        self.attr2 = 2
    def __getattr__(self, attr):            # On undefined attrs only
        print('get: ' + attr)               # Not attr1: inherited from class
        return 3                            # Not attr2: stored on instance

X = GetAttr()
print(X.attr1)
print(X.attr2)
print(X.attr3)

print('-'*40)

class GetAttribute(object):                 # (object) needed in 2.6 only
    attr1 = 1
    def __init__(self):
        self.attr2 = 2
    def __getattribute__(self, attr):       # On all attr fetches
        print('get: ' + attr)               # Use superclass to avoid looping here
        if attr == 'attr3':
            return 3
        else:
            return object.__getattribute__(self, attr)

X = GetAttribute()
print(X.attr1)
print(X.attr2)
print(X.attr3)

When run, the __getattr__ version intercepts only attr3 accesses, because it is undefined. The __getattribute__ version, on the other hand, intercepts all attribute fetches and must route those it does not manage to the superclass fetcher to avoid loops:

1
2
get: attr3
3
----------------------------------------
get: attr1
1
get: attr2
2
get: attr3
3

Although __getattribute__ can catch more attribute fetches than __getattr__, in practice they are often just variations on a theme—if attributes are not physically stored, the two have the same effect.

Management Techniques Compared

To summarize the coding differences in all four attribute management schemes we’ve seen in this chapter, let’s quickly step through a more comprehensive computed-attribute example using each technique. The following version uses properties to intercept and calculate attributes named square and cube. Notice how their base values are stored in names that begin with an underscore, so they don’t clash with the names of the properties themselves:

# 2 dynamically computed attributes with properties

class Powers:
    def __init__(self, square, cube):
        self._square = square                      # _square is the base value
        self._cube   = cube                        # square is the property name

    def getSquare(self):
        return self._square ** 2
    def setSquare(self, value):
        self._square = value
    square = property(getSquare, setSquare)

    def getCube(self):
        return self._cube ** 3
    cube = property(getCube)

X = Powers(3, 4)
print(X.square)      # 3 ** 2 = 9
print(X.cube)        # 4 ** 3 = 64
X.square = 5
print(X.square)      # 5 ** 2 = 25

To do the same with descriptors, we define the attributes with complete classes. Note that these descriptors store base values as instance state, so they must use leading underscores again so as not to clash with the names of descriptors (as we’ll see in the final example of this chapter, we could avoid this renaming requirement by storing base values as descriptor state instead):

# Same, but with descriptors

class DescSquare:
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):
        return instance._square ** 2
    def __set__(self, instance, value):
        instance._square = value

class DescCube:
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):
        return instance._cube ** 3

class Powers:                                  # Use (object) in 2.6
    square = DescSquare()
    cube   = DescCube()
    def __init__(self, square, cube):
        self._square = square                  # "self.square = square" works too,
        self._cube   = cube                    # because it triggers desc __set__!

X = Powers(3, 4)
print(X.square)      # 3 ** 2 = 9
print(X.cube)        # 4 ** 3 = 64
X.square = 5
print(X.square)      # 5 ** 2 = 25

To achieve the same result with __getattr__ fetch interception, we again store base values with underscore-prefixed names so that accesses to managed names are undefined and thus invoke our method; we also need to code a __setattrr__ to intercept assignments, and take care to avoid its potential for looping:

# Same, but with generic __getattr__ undefined attribute interception

class Powers:
    def __init__(self, square, cube):
        self._square = square
        self._cube   = cube

    def __getattr__(self, name):
        if name == 'square':
            return self._square ** 2
        elif name == 'cube':
            return self._cube ** 3
        else:
            raise TypeError('unknown attr:' + name)

    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        if name == 'square':
            self.__dict__['_square'] = value
        else:
            self.__dict__[name] = value

X = Powers(3, 4)
print(X.square)      # 3 ** 2 = 9
print(X.cube)        # 4 ** 3 = 64
X.square = 5
print(X.square)      # 5 ** 2 = 25

The final option, coding this with __getattribute__, is similar to the prior version. Because we catch every attribute now, though, we must route base value fetches to a superclass to avoid looping:

# Same, but with generic __getattribute__ all attribute interception

class Powers:
    def __init__(self, square, cube):
        self._square = square
        self._cube   = cube
    def __getattribute__(self, name):
        if name == 'square':
            return object.__getattribute__(self, '_square') ** 2
        elif name == 'cube':
            return object.__getattribute__(self, '_cube') ** 3
        else:
            return object.__getattribute__(self, name)
    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        if name == 'square':
            self.__dict__['_square'] = value
        else:
            self.__dict__[name] = value

X = Powers(3, 4)
print(X.square)      # 3 ** 2 = 9
print(X.cube)        # 4 ** 3 = 64
X.square = 5
print(X.square)      # 5 ** 2 = 25

As you can see, each technique takes a different form in code, but all four produce the same result when run:

9
64
25

For more on how these alternatives compare, and other coding options, stay tuned for a more realistic application of them in the attribute validation example in the section Example: Attribute Validations. First, though, we need to study a pitfall associated with two of these tools.

Intercepting Built-in Operation Attributes

When I introduced __getattr__ and __getattribute__, I stated that they intercept undefined and all attribute fetches, respectively, which makes them ideal for delegation-based coding patterns. While this is true for normally named attributes, their behavior needs some additional clarification: for method-name attributes implicitly fetched by built-in operations, these methods may not be run at all. This means that operator overloading method calls cannot be delegated to wrapped objects unless wrapper classes somehow redefine these methods themselves.

For example, attribute fetches for the __str__, __add__, and __getitem__ methods run implicitly by printing, + expressions, and indexing, respectively, are not routed to the generic attribute interception methods in 3.0. Specifically:

In Python 3.0, neither __getattr__ nor __getattribute__ is run for such attributes.

In Python 2.6, __getattr__ is run for such attributes if they are undefined in the class.

In Python 2.6, __getattribute__ is available for new-style classes only and works as it does in 3.0.

In other words, in Python 3.0 classes (and 2.6 new-style classes), there is no direct way to generically intercept built-in operations like printing and addition. In Python 2.X, the methods such operations invoke are looked up at runtime in instances, like all other attributes; in Python 3.0 such methods are looked up in classes instead.

This change makes delegation-based coding patterns more complex in 3.0, since they cannot generically intercept operator overloading method calls and route them to an embedded object. This is not a showstopper—wrapper classes can work around this constraint by redefining all relevant operator overloading methods in the wrapper itself, in order to delegate calls. These extra methods can be added either manually, with tools, or by definition in and inheritance from common superclasses. This does, however, make wrappers more work than they used to be when operator overloading methods are a part of a wrapped object’s interface.

Keep in mind that this issue applies only to __getattr__ and __getattribute__. Because properties and descriptors are defined for specific attributes only, they don’t really apply to delegation-based classes at all—a single property or descriptor cannot be used to intercept arbitrary attributes. Moreover, a class that defines both operator overloading methods and attribute interception will work correctly, regardless of the type of attribute interception defined. Our concern here is only with classes that do not have operator overloading methods defined, but try to intercept them generically.

Consider the following example, the file getattr.py, which tests various attribute types and built-in operations on instances of classes containing __getattr__ and __getattribute__ methods:

class GetAttr:
    eggs = 88             # eggs stored on class, spam on instance
    def __init__(self):
       self.spam = 77
    def __len__(self):    # len here, else __getattr__ called with __len__
        print('__len__: 42')
        return 42
    def __getattr__(self, attr):     # Provide __str__ if asked, else dummy func
        print('getattr: ' + attr)
        if attr == '__str__':
            return lambda *args: '[Getattr str]'
        else:
            return lambda *args: None

class GetAttribute(object):          # object required in 2.6, implied in 3.0
    eggs = 88                        # In 2.6 all are isinstance(object) auto
    def __init__(self):              # But must derive to get new-style tools,
        self.spam = 77               # incl __getattribute__, some __X__ defaults
    def __len__(self):
        print('__len__: 42')
        return 42
    def __getattribute__(self, attr):
        print('getattribute: ' + attr)
        if attr == '__str__':
            return lambda *args: '[GetAttribute str]'
        else:
            return lambda *args: None

for Class in GetAttr, GetAttribute:
    print('\n' + Class.__name__.ljust(50, '='))

    X = Class()
    X.eggs               # Class attr
    X.spam               # Instance attr
    X.other              # Missing attr
    len(X)               # __len__ defined explicitly

    try:                 # New-styles must support [], +, call directly: redefine
        X[0]             # __getitem__?
    except:
        print('fail []')

    try:
        X + 99           # __add__?
    except:
        print('fail +')

    try:
        X()              # __call__?  (implicit via built-in)
    except:
        print('fail ()')
    X.__call__()         # __call__?  (explicit, not inherited)

    print(X.__str__())   # __str__?   (explicit, inherited from type)
    print(X)             # __str__?   (implicit via built-in)

When run under Python 2.6, __getattr__ does receive a variety of implicit attribute fetches for built-in operations, because Python looks up such attributes in instances normally. Conversely, __getattribute__ is not run for any of the operator overloading names, because such names are looked up in classes only:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python getattr.py

GetAttr===========================================
getattr: other
__len__: 42
getattr: __getitem__
getattr: __coerce__
getattr: __add__
getattr: __call__
getattr: __call__
getattr: __str__
[Getattr str]
getattr: __str__
[Getattr str]

GetAttribute======================================
getattribute: eggs
getattribute: spam
getattribute: other
__len__: 42
fail []
fail +
fail ()
getattribute: __call__
getattribute: __str__
[GetAttribute str]
<__main__.GetAttribute object at 0x025EA1D0>

Note how __getattr__ intercepts both implicit and explicit fetches of __call__ and __str__ in 2.6 here. By contrast, __getattribute__ fails to catch implicit fetches of either attribute name for built-in operations.

Really, the __getattribute__ case is the same in 2.6 as it is in 3.0, because in 2.6 classes must be made new-style by deriving from object to use this method. This code’s object derivation is optional in 3.0 because all classes are new-style.

When run under Python 3.0, though, results for __getattr__ differ—none of the implicitly run operator overloading methods trigger either attribute interception method when their attributes are fetched by built-in operations. Python 3.0 skips the normal instance lookup mechanism when resolving such names:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python getattr.py

GetAttr===========================================
getattr: other
__len__: 42
fail []
fail +
fail ()
getattr: __call__
<__main__.GetAttr object at 0x025D17F0>
<__main__.GetAttr object at 0x025D17F0>

GetAttribute======================================
getattribute: eggs
getattribute: spam
getattribute: other
__len__: 42
fail []
fail +
fail ()
getattribute: __call__
getattribute: __str__
[GetAttribute str]
<__main__.GetAttribute object at 0x025D1870>

We can trace these outputs back to prints in the script to see how this works:

__str__ access fails to be caught twice by __getattr__ in 3.0: once for the built-in print, and once for explicit fetches because a default is inherited from the class (really, from the built-in object, which is a superclass to every class).

__str__ fails to be caught only once by the __getattribute__ catchall, during the built-in print operation; explicit fetches bypass the inherited version.

__call__ fails to be caught in both schemes in 3.0 for built-in call expressions, but it is intercepted by both when fetched explicitly; unlike with __str__, there is no inherited __call__ default to defeat __getattr__.

__len__ is caught by both classes, simply because it is an explicitly defined method in the classes themselves—its name it is not routed to either __getattr__ or __getattribute__ in 3.0 if we delete the class’s __len__ methods.

All other built-in operations fail to be intercepted by both schemes in 3.0.

Again, the net effect is that operator overloading methods implicitly run by built-in operations are never routed through either attribute interception method in 3.0: Python 3.0 searches for such attributes in classes and skips instance lookup entirely.

This makes delegation-based wrapper classes more difficult to code in 3.0—if wrapped classes may contain operator overloading methods, those methods must be redefined redundantly in the wrapper class in order to delegate to the wrapped object. In general delegation tools, this can add many extra methods.

Of course, the addition of such methods can be partly automated by tools that augment classes with new methods (the class decorators and metaclasses of the next two chapters might help here). Moreover, a superclass might be able to define all these extra methods once, for inheritance in delegation-based classes. Still, delegation coding patterns require extra work in 3.0.

For a more realistic illustration of this phenomenon as well as its workaround, see the Private decorator example in the following chapter. There, we’ll see that it’s also possible to insert a __getattribute__ in the client class to retain its original type, although this method still won’t be called for operator overloading methods; printing still runs a __str__ defined in such a class directly, for example, instead of routing the request through __getattribute__.

As another example, the next section resurrects our class tutorial example. Now that you understand how attribute interception works, I’ll be able to explain one of its stranger bits.

Note

For an example of this 3.0 change at work in Python itself, see the discussion of the 3.0 os.popen object in Chapter 14. Because it is implemented with a wrapper that uses __getattr__ to delegate attribute fetches to an embedded object, it does not intercept the next(X) built-in iterator function in Python 3.0, which is defined to run __next__. It does, however, intercept and delegate explicit X.__next__() calls, because these are not routed through the built-in and are not inherited from a superclass like __str__ is.

This is equivalent to __call__ in our example—implicit calls for built-ins do not trigger __getattr__, but explicit calls to names not inherited from the class type do. In other words, this change impacts not only our delegators, but also those in the Python standard library! Given the scope of this change, it’s possible that this behavior may evolve in the future, so be sure to verify this issue in later releases.

Delegation-Based Managers Revisited

The object-oriented tutorial of Chapter 27 presented a Manager class that used object embedding and method delegation to customize its superclass, rather than inheritance. Here is the code again for reference, with some irrelevant testing removed:

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, job=None, pay=0):
        self.name = name
        self.job  = job
        self.pay  = pay
    def lastName(self):
        return self.name.split()[-1]
    def giveRaise(self, percent):
        self.pay = int(self.pay * (1 + percent))
    def __str__(self):
        return '[Person: %s, %s]' % (self.name, self.pay)

class Manager:
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.person = Person(name, 'mgr', pay)      # Embed a Person object
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        self.person.giveRaise(percent + bonus)      # Intercept and delegate
    def __getattr__(self, attr):
        return getattr(self.person, attr)           # Delegate all other attrs
    def __str__(self):
        return str(self.person)                     # Must overload again (in 3.0)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    sue = Person('Sue Jones', job='dev', pay=100000)
    print(sue.lastName())
    sue.giveRaise(.10)
    print(sue)
    tom = Manager('Tom Jones', 50000)    # Manager.__init__
    print(tom.lastName())                # Manager.__getattr__ -> Person.lastName
    tom.giveRaise(.10)                   # Manager.giveRaise -> Person.giveRaise
    print(tom)                           # Manager.__str__ -> Person.__str__

Comments at the end of this file show which methods are invoked for a line’s operation. In particular, notice how lastName calls are undefined in Manager, and thus are routed into the generic __getattr__ and from there on to the embedded Person object. Here is the script’s output—Sue receives a 10% raise from Person, but Tom gets 20% because giveRaise is customized in Manager:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python person.py
Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
Jones
[Person: Tom Jones, 60000]

By contrast, though, notice what occurs when we print a Manager at the end of the script: the wrapper class’s __str__ is invoked, and it delegates to the embedded Person object’s __str__. With that in mind, watch what happens if we delete the Manager.__str__ method in this code:

# Delete the Manager __str__ method

class Manager:
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.person = Person(name, 'mgr', pay)      # Embed a Person object
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        self.person.giveRaise(percent + bonus)      # Intercept and delegate
    def __getattr__(self, attr):
        return getattr(self.person, attr)           # Delegate all other attrs

Now printing does not route its attribute fetch through the generic __getattr__ interceptor under Python 3.0 for Manager objects. Instead, a default __str__ display method inherited from the class’s implicit object superclass is looked up and run (sue still prints correctly, because Person has an explicit __str__):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python person.py
Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
Jones
<__main__.Manager object at 0x02A5AE30>

Curiously, running without a __str__ like this does trigger __getattr__ in Python 2.6, because operator overloading attributes are routed through this method, and classes do not inherit a default for __str__:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python person.py
Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
Jones
[Person: Tom Jones, 60000]

Switching to __getattribute__ won’t help 3.0 here either—like __getattr__, it is not run for operator overloading attributes implied by built-in operations in either Python 2.6 or 3.0:

# Replace __getattr_ with __getattribute__

class Manager:                                           # Use (object) in 2.6
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.person = Person(name, 'mgr', pay)           # Embed a Person object
    def giveRaise(self, percent, bonus=.10):
        self.person.giveRaise(percent + bonus)           # Intercept and delegate
    def __getattribute__(self, attr):
        print('**', attr)
        if attr in ['person', 'giveRaise']:
            return object.__getattribute__(self, attr)   # Fetch my attrs
        else:
            return getattr(self.person, attr)            # Delegate all others

Regardless of which attribute interception method is used in 3.0, we still must include a redefined __str__ in Manager (as shown above) in order to intercept printing operations and route them to the embedded Person object:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python person.py
Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
** lastName
** person
Jones
** giveRaise
** person
<__main__.Manager object at 0x028E0590>

Notice that __getattribute__ gets called twice here for methods—once for the method name, and again for the self.person embedded object fetch. We could avoid that with a different coding, but we would still have to redefine __str__ to catch printing, albeit differently here (self.person would cause this __getattribute__ to fail):

# Code __getattribute__ differently to minimize extra calls

class Manager:
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.person = Person(name, 'mgr', pay)
    def __getattribute__(self, attr):
        print('**', attr)
        person = object.__getattribute__(self, 'person')
        if attr == 'giveRaise':
            return lambda percent: person.giveRaise(percent+.10)
        else:
            return getattr(person, attr)
    def __str__(self):
        person = object.__getattribute__(self, 'person')
        return str(person)

When this alternative runs, our object prints properly, but only because we’ve added an explicit __str__ in the wrapper—this attribute is still not routed to our generic attribute interception method:

Jones
[Person: Sue Jones, 110000]
** lastName
Jones
** giveRaise
[Person: Tom Jones, 60000]

That short story here is that delegation-based classes like Manager must redefine some operator overloading methods (like __str__) to route them to embedded objects in Python 3.0, but not in Python 2.6 unless new-style classes are used. Our only direct options seem to be using __getattr__ and Python 2.6, or redefining operator overloading methods in wrapper classes redundantly in 3.0.

Again, this isn’t an impossible task; many wrappers can predict the set of operator overloading methods required, and tools and superclasses can automate part of this task. Moreover, not all classes use operator overloading methods (indeed, most application classes usually should not). It is, however, something to keep in mind for delegation coding models used in Python 3.0; when operator overloading methods are part of an object’s interface, wrappers must accommodate them portably by redefining them locally.

Example: Attribute Validations

To close out this chapter, let’s turn to a more realistic example, coded in all four of our attribute management schemes. The example we will use defines a CardHolder object with four attributes, three of which are managed. The managed attributes validate or transform values when fetched or stored. All four versions produce the same results for the same test code, but they implement their attributes in very different ways. The examples are included largely for self-study; although I won’t go through their code in detail, they all use concepts we’ve already explored in this chapter.

Using Properties to Validate

Our first coding uses properties to manage three attributes. As usual, we could use simple methods instead of managed attributes, but properties help if we have been using attributes in existing code already. Properties run code automatically on attribute access, but are focused on a specific set of attributes; they cannot be used to intercept all attributes generically.

To understand this code, it’s crucial to notice that the attribute assignments inside the __init__ constructor method trigger property setter methods too. When this method assigns to self.name, for example, it automatically invokes the setName method, which transforms the value and assigns it to an instance attribute called __name so it won’t clash with the property’s name.

This renaming (sometimes called name mangling) is necessary because properties use common instance state and have none of their own. Data is stored in an attribute called __name, and the attribute called name is always a property, not data.

In the end, this class manages attributes called name, age, and acct; allows the attribute addr to be accessed directly; and provides a read-only attribute called remain that is entirely virtual and computed on demand. For comparison purposes, this property-based coding weighs in at 39 lines of code:

class CardHolder:
    acctlen = 8                                # Class data
    retireage = 59.5

    def __init__(self, acct, name, age, addr):
        self.acct = acct                       # Instance data
        self.name = name                       # These trigger prop setters too
        self.age  = age                        # __X mangled to have class name
        self.addr = addr                       # addr is not managed
                                               # remain has no data
    def getName(self):
        return self.__name
    def setName(self, value):
        value = value.lower().replace(' ', '_')
        self.__name = value
    name = property(getName, setName)

    def getAge(self):
        return self.__age
    def setAge(self, value):
        if value < 0 or value > 150:
            raise ValueError('invalid age')
        else:
            self.__age = value
    age = property(getAge, setAge)

    def getAcct(self):
        return self.__acct[:-3] + '***'
    def setAcct(self, value):
        value = value.replace('-', '')
        if len(value) != self.acctlen:
            raise TypeError('invald acct number')
        else:
            self.__acct = value
    acct = property(getAcct, setAcct)

    def remainGet(self):                       # Could be a method, not attr
        return self.retireage - self.age       # Unless already using as attr
    remain = property(remainGet)

Self-test code

The following code tests our class; add this to the bottom of your file, or place the class in a module and import it first. We’ll use this same testing code for all four versions of this example. When it runs, we make two instances of our managed-attribute class and fetch and change its various attributes. Operations expected to fail are wrapped in try statements:

bob = CardHolder('1234-5678', 'Bob Smith', 40, '123 main st')
print(bob.acct, bob.name, bob.age, bob.remain, bob.addr, sep=' / ')
bob.name = 'Bob Q. Smith'
bob.age  = 50
bob.acct = '23-45-67-89'
print(bob.acct, bob.name, bob.age, bob.remain, bob.addr, sep=' / ')

sue = CardHolder('5678-12-34', 'Sue Jones', 35, '124 main st')
print(sue.acct, sue.name, sue.age, sue.remain, sue.addr, sep=' / ')
try:
    sue.age = 200
except:
    print('Bad age for Sue')

try:
    sue.remain = 5
except:
    print("Can't set sue.remain")

try:
    sue.acct = '1234567'
except:
    print('Bad acct for Sue')

Here is the output of our self-test code; again, this is the same for all versions of this example. Trace through this code to see how the class’s methods are invoked; accounts are displayed with some digits hidden, names are converted to a standard format, and time remaining until retirement is computed when fetched using a class attribute cutoff:

12345*** / bob_smith / 40 / 19.5 / 123 main st
23456*** / bob_q._smith / 50 / 9.5 / 123 main st
56781*** / sue_jones / 35 / 24.5 / 124 main st
Bad age for Sue
Can't set sue.remain
Bad acct for Sue

Using Descriptors to Validate

Now, let’s recode our example using descriptors instead of properties. As we’ve seen, descriptors are very similar to properties in terms of functionality and roles; in fact, properties are basically a restricted form of descriptor. Like properties, descriptors are designed to handle specific attributes, not generic attribute access. Unlike properties, descriptors have their own state, and they’re a more general scheme.

To understand this code, it’s again important to notice that the attribute assignments inside the __init__ constructor method trigger descriptor __set__ methods. When the constructor method assigns to self.name, for example, it automatically invokes the Name.__set__() method, which transforms the value and assigns it to a descriptor attribute called name.

Unlike in the prior property-based variant, though, in this case the actual name value is attached to the descriptor object, not the client class instance. Although we could store this value in either instance or descriptor state, the latter avoids the need to mangle names with underscores to avoid collisions. In the CardHolder client class, the attribute called name is always a descriptor object, not data. The downside of this scheme is that state stored inside a descriptor itself is class-level data which is effectively shared by all client class instances, and so cannot vary between them.

In the end, this class implements the same attributes as the prior version: it manages attributes called name, age, and acct; allows the attribute addr to be accessed directly; and provides a read-only attribute called remain that is entirely virtual and computed on demand. Notice how we must catch assignments to the remain name in its descriptor and raise an exception; as we learned earlier, if we did not do this, assigning to this attribute of an instance would silently create an instance attribute that hides the class attribute descriptor. For comparison purposes, this descriptor-based coding takes 45 lines of code:

class CardHolder:
    acctlen = 8                                  # Class data
    retireage = 59.5

    def __init__(self, acct, name, age, addr):
        self.acct = acct                         # Instance data
        self.name = name                         # These trigger __set__ calls too
        self.age  = age                          # __X not needed: in descriptor
        self.addr = addr                         # addr is not managed
                                                 # remain has no data
    class Name:
        def __get__(self, instance, owner):      # Class names: CardHolder locals
            return self.name
        def __set__(self, instance, value):
            value = value.lower().replace(' ', '_')
            self.name = value
    name = Name()

    class Age:
        def __get__(self, instance, owner):
            return self.age                             # Use descriptor data
        def __set__(self, instance, value):
            if value < 0 or value > 150:
                raise ValueError('invalid age')
            else:
                self.age = value
    age = Age()

    class Acct:
        def __get__(self, instance, owner):
            return self.acct[:-3] + '***'
        def __set__(self, instance, value):
            value = value.replace('-', '')
            if len(value) != instance.acctlen:          # Use instance class data
                raise TypeError('invald acct number')
            else:
                self.acct = value
    acct = Acct()

    class Remain:
        def __get__(self, instance, owner):
            return instance.retireage - instance.age    # Triggers Age.__get__
        def __set__(self, instance, value):
            raise TypeError('cannot set remain')        # Else set allowed here
    remain = Remain()

Using __getattr__ to Validate

As we’ve seen, the __getattr__ method intercepts all undefined attributes, so it can be more generic than using properties or descriptors. For our example, we simply test the attribute name to know when a managed attribute is being fetched; others are stored physically on the instance and so never reach __getattr__. Although this approach is more general than using properties or descriptors, extra work may be required to imitate the specific-attribute focus of other tools. We need to check names at runtime, and we must code a __setattr__ in order to intercept and validate attribute assignments.

As for the property and descriptor versions of this example, it’s critical to notice that the attribute assignments inside the __init__ constructor method trigger the class’s __setattr__ method too. When this method assigns to self.name, for example, it automatically invokes the __setattr__ method, which transforms the value and assigns it to an instance attribute called name. By storing name on the instance, it ensures that future accesses will not trigger __getattr__. In contrast, acct is stored as _acct, so that later accesses to acct do invoke __getattr__.

In the end, this class, like the prior two, manages attributes called name, age, and acct; allows the attribute addr to be accessed directly; and provides a read-only attribute called remain that is entirely virtual and is computed on demand.

For comparison purposes, this alternative comes in at 32 lines of code—7 fewer than the property-based version, and 13 fewer than the version using descriptors. Clarity matters more than code size, of course, but extra code can sometimes imply extra development and maintenance work. Probably more important here are roles: generic tools like __getattr__ may be better suited to generic delegation, while properties and descriptors are more directly designed to manage specific attributes.

Also note that the code here incurs extra calls when setting unmanaged attributes (e.g., addr), although no extra calls are incurred for fetching unmanaged attributes, since they are defined. Though this will likely result in negligible overhead for most programs, properties and descriptors incur an extra call only when managed attributes are accessed.

Here’s the __getattr__ version of our code:

class CardHolder:
    acctlen = 8                                  # Class data
    retireage = 59.5

    def __init__(self, acct, name, age, addr):
        self.acct = acct                         # Instance data
        self.name = name                         # These trigger __setattr__ too
        self.age  = age                          # _acct not mangled: name tested
        self.addr = addr                         # addr is not managed
                                                 # remain has no data
    def __getattr__(self, name):
        if name == 'acct':                           # On undefined attr fetches
            return self._acct[:-3] + '***'           # name, age, addr are defined
        elif name == 'remain':
            return self.retireage - self.age         # Doesn't trigger __getattr__
        else:
            raise AttributeError(name)

    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        if name == 'name':                           # On all attr assignments
            value = value.lower().replace(' ', '_')  # addr stored directly
        elif name == 'age':                          # acct mangled to _acct
            if value < 0 or value > 150:
                raise ValueError('invalid age')
        elif name == 'acct':
            name  = '_acct'
            value = value.replace('-', '')
            if len(value) != self.acctlen:
                raise TypeError('invald acct number')
        elif name == 'remain':
            raise TypeError('cannot set remain')
        self.__dict__[name] = value                  # Avoid looping

Using __getattribute__ to Validate

Our final variant uses the __getattribute__ catchall to intercept attribute fetches and manage them as needed. Every attribute fetch is caught here, so we test the attribute names to detect managed attributes and route all others to the superclass for normal fetch processing. This version uses the same __setattr__ to catch assignments as the prior version.

The code works very much like the __getattr__ version, so I won’t repeat the full description here. Note, though, that because every attribute fetch is routed to __getattribute__, we don’t need to mangle names to intercept them here (acct is stored as acct). On the other hand, this code must take care to route nonmanaged attribute fetches to a superclass to avoid looping.

Also notice that this version incurs extra calls for both setting and fetching unmanaged attributes (e.g., addr); if speed is paramount, this alternative may be the slowest of the bunch. For comparison purposes, this version amounts to 32 lines of code, just like the prior version:

class CardHolder:
    acctlen = 8                                  # Class data
    retireage = 59.5

    def __init__(self, acct, name, age, addr):
        self.acct = acct                         # Instance data
        self.name = name                         # These trigger __setattr__ too
        self.age  = age                          # acct not mangled: name tested
        self.addr = addr                         # addr is not managed
                                                 # remain has no data
    def __getattribute__(self, name):
        superget = object.__getattribute__             # Don't loop: one level up
        if name == 'acct':                             # On all attr fetches
            return superget(self, 'acct')[:-3] + '***'
        elif name == 'remain':
            return superget(self, 'retireage') - superget(self, 'age')
        else:
            return superget(self, name)                # name, age, addr: stored

    def __setattr__(self, name, value):
        if name == 'name':                             # On all attr assignments
            value = value.lower().replace(' ', '_')    # addr stored directly
        elif name == 'age':
            if value < 0 or value > 150:
                raise ValueError('invalid age')
        elif name == 'acct':
            value = value.replace('-', '')
            if len(value) != self.acctlen:
                raise TypeError('invald acct number')
        elif name == 'remain':
            raise TypeError('cannot set remain')
        self.__dict__[name] = value                     # Avoid loops, orig names

Be sure to study and run this section’s code on your own for more pointers on managed attribute coding techniques.

Test Your Knowledge: Quiz

How do __getattr__ and __getattribute__ differ?

How do properties and descriptors differ?

How are properties and decorators related?

What are the main functional differences between __getattr__ and __getattribute__ and properties and descriptors?

Isn’t all this feature comparison just a kind of argument?

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The __getattr__ method is run for fetches of undefined attributes only—i.e., those not present on an instance and not inherited from any of its classes. By contrast, the __getattribute__ method is called for every attribute fetch, whether the attribute is defined or not. Because of this, code inside a __getattr__ can freely fetch other attributes if they are defined, whereas __getattribute__ must use special code for all such attribute fetches to avoid looping (it must route fetches to a superclass to skip itself).

Properties serve a specific role, while descriptors are more general. Properties define get, set, and delete functions for a specific attribute; descriptors provide a class with methods for these actions, too, but they provide extra flexibility to support more arbitrary actions. In fact, properties are really a simple way to create a specific kind of descriptor—one that runs functions on attribute accesses. Coding differs too: a property is created with a built-in function, and a descriptor is coded with a class; as such, descriptors can leverage all the usual OOP features of classes, such as inheritance. Moreover, in addition to the instance’s state information, descriptors have local state of their own, so they can avoid name collisions in the instance.

Properties can be coded with decorator syntax. Because the property built-in accepts a single function argument, it can be used directly as a function decorator to define a fetch access property. Due to the name rebinding behavior of decorators, the name of the decorated function is assigned to a property whose get accessor is set to the original function decorated (name = property(name)). Property setter and deleter attributes allow us to further add set and delete accessors with decoration syntax—they set the accessor to the decorated function and return the augmented property.

The __getattr__ and __getattribute__ methods are more generic: they can be used to catch arbitrarily many attributes. In contrast, each property or descriptor provides access interception for only one specific attribute—we can’t catch every attribute fetch with a single property or descriptor. On the other hand, properties and descriptors handle both attribute fetch and assignment by design: __getattr__ and __getattribute__ handle fetches only; to intercept assignments as well, __setattr__ must also be coded. The implementation is also different: __getattr__ and __getattribute__ are operator overloading methods, whereas properties and descriptors are objects manually assigned to class attributes.

No it isn’t. To quote from Python namesake Monty Python’s Flying Circus:

An argument is a connected series of statements intended to establish a
proposition.
No it isn't.
Yes it is! It's not just contradiction.
Look, if I argue with you, I must take up a contrary position.
Yes, but that's not just saying "No it isn't."
Yes it is!
No it isn't!
Yes it is!
No it isn't. Argument is an intellectual process. Contradiction is just
the automatic gainsaying of any statement the other person makes.
(short pause)
No it isn't.
It is.
Not at all.
Now look...

Chapter 38. Decorators

In the advanced class topics chapter of this book (Chapter 31), we met static and class methods and took a quick look at the @ decorator syntax Python offers for declaring them. We also met function decorators briefly in the prior chapter (Chapter 37), while exploring the property built-in’s ability to serve as a decorator, and in Chapter 28 while studying the notion of abstract superclasses.

This chapter picks up where the previous decorator coverage left off. Here, we’ll dig deeper into the inner workings of decorators and study more advanced ways to code new decorators ourselves. As we’ll see, many of the concepts we studied in earlier chapters, such as state retention, show up regularly in decorators.

This is a somewhat advanced topic, and decorator construction tends to be of more interest to tool builders than to application programmers. Still, given that decorators are becoming increasingly common in popular Python frameworks, a basic understanding can help demystify their role, even if you’re just a decorator user.

Besides covering decorator construction details, this chapter serves as a more realistic case study of Python in action. Because its examples are somewhat larger than most of the others we’ve seen in this book, they better illustrate how code comes together into more complete systems and tools. As an extra perk, much of the code we’ll write here may be used as general-purpose tools in your day-to-day programs.

What’s a Decorator?

Decoration is a way to specify management code for functions and classes. Decorators themselves take the form of callable objects (e.g., functions) that process other callable objects. As we saw earlier in this book, Python decorators come in two related flavors:

Function decorators do name rebinding at function definition time, providing a layer of logic that can manage functions and methods, or later calls to them.

Class decorators do name rebinding at class definition time, providing a layer of logic that can manage classes, or the instances created by calling them later.

In short, decorators provide a way to insert automatically run code at the end of function and class definition statements—at the end of a def for function decorators, and at the end of a class for class decorators. Such code can play a variety of roles, as described in the following sections.

Managing Calls and Instances

For example, in typical use, this automatically run code may be used to augment calls to functions and classes. It arranges this by installing wrapper objects to be invoked later:

Function decorators install wrapper objects to intercept later function calls and process them as needed.

Class decorators install wrapper objects to intercept later instance creation calls and process them as required.

Decorators achieve these effects by automatically rebinding function and class names to other callables, at the end of def and class statements. When later invoked, these callables can perform tasks such as tracing and timing function calls, managing access to class instance attributes, and so on.

Managing Functions and Classes

Although most examples in this chapter deal with using wrappers to intercept later calls to functions and classes, this is not the only way decorators can be used:

Function decorators can also be used to manage function objects, instead of later calls to them—to register a function to an API, for instance. Our primary focus here, though, will be on their more commonly used call wrapper application.

Class decorators can also be used to manage class objects directly, instead of instance creation calls—to augment a class with new methods, for example. Because this role intersects strongly with that of metaclasses (indeed, both run at the end of the class creation process), we’ll see additional use cases in the next chapter.

In other words, function decorators can be used to manage both function calls and function objects, and class decorators can be used to manage both class instances and classes themselves. By returning the decorated object itself instead of a wrapper, decorators become a simple post-creation step for functions and classes.

Regardless of the role they play, decorators provide a convenient and explicit way to code tools useful both during program development and in live production systems.

Using and Defining Decorators

Depending on your job description, you might encounter decorators as a user or a provider. As we’ve seen, Python itself comes with built-in decorators that have specialized roles—static method declaration, property creation, and more. In addition, many popular Python toolkits include decorators to perform tasks such as managing database or user-interface logic. In such cases, we can get by without knowing how the decorators are coded.

For more general tasks, programmers can code arbitrary decorators of their own. For example, function decorators may be used to augment functions with code that adds call tracing, performs argument validity testing during debugging, automatically acquires and releases thread locks, times calls made to function for optimization, and so on. Any behavior you can imagine adding to a function call is a candidate for custom function decorators.

On the other hand, function decorators are designed to augment only a specific function or method call, not an entire object interface. Class decorators fill the latter role better—because they can intercept instance creation calls, they can be used to implement arbitrary object interface augmentation or management tasks. For example, custom class decorators can trace or validate every attribute reference made for an object. They can also be used to implement proxy objects, singleton classes, and other common coding patterns. In fact, we’ll find that many class decorators bear a strong resemblance to the delegation coding pattern we met in Chapter 30.

Why Decorators?

Like many advanced Python tools, decorators are never strictly required from a purely technical perspective: their functionality can often be implemented instead using simple helper function calls or other techniques (and at a base level, we can always manually code the name rebinding that decorators perform automatically).

That said, decorators provide an explicit syntax for such tasks, which makes intent clearer, can minimize augmentation code redundancy, and may help ensure correct API usage:

Decorators have a very explicit syntax, which makes them easier to spot than helper function calls that may be arbitrarily far-removed from the subject functions or classes.

Decorators are applied once, when the subject function or class is defined; it’s not necessary to add extra code (which may have to be changed in the future) at every call to the class or function.

Because of both of the prior points, decorators make it less likely that a user of an API will forget to augment a function or class according to API requirements.

In other words, beyond their technical model, decorators offer some advantages in terms of code maintenance and aesthetics. Moreover, as structuring tools, decorators naturally foster encapsulation of code, which reduces redundancy and makes future changes easier.

Decorators do have some potential drawbacks, too—when they insert wrapper logic, they can alter the types of the decorated objects, and they may incur extra calls. On the other hand, the same considerations apply to any technique that adds wrapping logic to objects.

We’ll explore these tradeoffs in the context of real code later in this chapter. Although the choice to use decorators is still somewhat subjective, their advantages are compelling enough that they are quickly becoming best practice in the Python world. To help you decide for yourself, let’s turn to the details.

The Basics

Let’s get started with a first-pass look at decoration behavior from a symbolic perspective. We’ll write real code soon, but since most of the magic of decorators boils down to an automatic rebinding operation, it’s important to understand this mapping first.

Function Decorators

Function decorators have been available in Python since version 2.5. As we saw earlier in this book, they are largely just syntactic sugar that runs one function through another at the end of a def statement, and rebinds the original function name to the result.

Usage

A function decorator is a kind of runtime declaration about the function whose definition follows. The decorator is coded on a line just before the def statement that defines a function or method, and it consists of the @ symbol followed by a reference to a metafunction—a function (or other callable object) that manages another function.

In terms of code, function decorators automatically map the following syntax:

@decorator              # Decorate function
def F(arg):
    ...

F(99)                   # Call function

into this equivalent form, where decorator is a one-argument callable object that returns a callable object with the same number of arguments as F:

def F(arg):
    ...
F = decorator(F)        # Rebind function name to decorator result

F(99)                   # Essentially calls decorator(F)(99)

This automatic name rebinding works on any def statement, whether it’s for a simple function or a method within a class. When the function F is later called, it’s actually calling the object returned by the decorator, which may be either another object that implements required wrapping logic, or the original function itself.

In other words, decoration essentially maps the first of the following into the second (though the decorator is really run only once, at decoration time):

func(6, 7)
decorator(func)(6, 7)

This automatic name rebinding accounts for the static method and property decoration syntax we met earlier in the book:

class C:
    @staticmethod
    def meth(...): ...            # meth = staticmethod(meth)

class C:
    @property
    def name(self): ...           # name = property(name)

In both cases, the method name is rebound to the result of a built-in function decorator, at the end of the def statement. Calling the original name later invokes whatever object the decorator returns.

Implementation

A decorator itself is a callable that returns a callable. That is, it returns the object to be called later when the decorated function is invoked through its original name—either a wrapper object to intercept later calls, or the original function augmented in some way. In fact, decorators can be any type of callable and return any type of callable: any combination of functions and classes may be used, though some are better suited to certain contexts.

For example, to tap into the decoration protocol in order to manage a function just after it is created, we might code a decorator of this form:

def decorator(F):
    # Process function F
    return F

@decorator
def func(): ...                  # func = decorator(func)

Because the original decorated function is assigned back to its name, this simply adds a post-creation step to function definition. Such a structure might be used to register a function to an API, assign function attributes, and so on.

In more typical use, to insert logic that intercepts later calls to a function, we might code a decorator to return a different object than the original function:

def decorator(F):
    # Save or use function F
    # Return a different callable: nested def, class with __call__, etc.

@decorator
def func(): ...                  # func = decorator(func)

This decorator is invoked at decoration time, and the callable it returns is invoked when the original function name is later called. The decorator itself receives the decorated function; the callable returned receives whatever arguments are later passed to the decorated function’s name. This works the same for class methods: the implied instance object simply shows up in the first argument of the returned callable.

In skeleton terms, here’s one common coding pattern that captures this idea—the decorator returns a wrapper that retains the original function in an enclosing scope:

def decorator(F):                     # On @ decoration
    def wrapper(*args):               # On wrapped function call
        # Use F and args
        # F(*args) calls original function
    return wrapper

@decorator                            # func = decorator(func)
def func(x, y):                       # func is passed to decorator's F
    ...

func(6, 7)                            # 6, 7 are passed to wrapper's *args

When the name func is later called, it really invokes the wrapper function returned by decorator; the wrapper function can then run the original func because it is still available in an enclosing scope. When coded this way, each decorated function produces a new scope to retain state.

To do the same with classes, we can overload the call operation and use instance attributes instead of enclosing scopes:

class decorator:
    def __init__(self, func):         # On @ decoration
        self.func = func
    def __call__(self, *args):        # On wrapped function call
        # Use self.func and args
        # self.func(*args) calls original function

@decorator
def func(x, y):                       # func = decorator(func)
    ...                               # func is passed to __init__

func(6, 7)                            # 6, 7 are passed to __call__'s *args

When the name func is later called now, it really invokes the __call__ operator overloading method of the instance created by decorator; the __call__ method can then run the original func because it is still available in an instance attribute. When coded this way, each decorated function produces a new instance to retain state.

Supporting method decoration

One subtle point about the prior class-based coding is that while it works to intercept simple function calls, it does not quite work when applied to class method functions:

class decorator:
    def __init__(self, func):           # func is method without instance
        self.func = func
    def __call__(self, *args):          # self is decorator instance
        # self.func(*args) fails!  # C instance not in args!

class C:
    @decorator
    def method(self, x, y):             # method = decorator(method)
        ...                              # Rebound to decorator instance

When coded this way, the decorated method is rebound to an instance of the decorator class, instead of a simple function.

The problem with this is that the self in the decorator’s __call__ receives the decorator class instance when the method is later run, and the instance of class C is never included in *args. This makes it impossible to dispatch the call to the original method—the decorator object retains the original method function, but it has no instance to pass to it.

To support both functions and methods, the nested function alternative works better:

def decorator(F):                       # F is func or method without instance
    def wrapper(*args):                 # class instance in args[0] for method
        # F(*args) runs func or method
    return wrapper

@decorator
def func(x, y):                         # func = decorator(func)
    ...
func(6, 7)                              # Really calls wrapper(6, 7)

class C:
    @decorator
    def method(self, x, y):             # method = decorator(method)
        ...                             # Rebound to simple function

X = C()
X.method(6, 7)                          # Really calls wrapper(X, 6, 7)

When coded this way wrapper receives the C class instance in its first argument, so it can dispatch to the original method and access state information.

Technically, this nested-function version works because Python creates a bound method object and thus passes the subject class instance to the self argument only when a method attribute references a simple function; when it references an instance of a callable class instead, the callable class’s instance is passed to self to give the callable class access to its own state information. We’ll see how this subtle difference can matter in more realistic examples later in this chapter.

Also note that nested functions are perhaps the most straightforward way to support decoration of both functions and methods, but not necessarily the only way. The prior chapter’s descriptors, for example, receive both the descriptor and subject class instance when called. Though more complex, later in this chapter we’ll see how this tool can be leveraged in this context as well.

Class Decorators

Function decorators proved so useful that the model was extended to allow class decoration in Python 2.6 and 3.0. Class decorators are strongly related to function decorators; in fact, they use the same syntax and very similar coding patterns. Rather than wrapping individual functions or methods, though, class decorators are a way to manage classes, or wrap up instance construction calls with extra logic that manages or augments instances created from a class.

Usage

Syntactically, class decorators appear just before class statements (just as function decorators appear just before function definitions). In symbolic terms, assuming that decorator is a one-argument function that returns a callable, the class decorator syntax:

@decorator                 # Decorate class
class C:
    ...

x = C(99)                  # Make an instance

is equivalent to the following—the class is automatically passed to the decorator function, and the decorator’s result is assigned back to the class name:

class C:
    ...
C = decorator(C)           # Rebind class name to decorator result

x = C(99)                  # Essentially calls decorator(C)(99)

The net effect is that calling the class name later to create an instance winds up triggering the callable returned by the decorator, instead of calling the original class itself.

Implementation

New class decorators are coded using many of the same techniques used for function decorators. Because a class decorator is also a callable that returns a callable, most combinations of functions and classes suffice.

However it’s coded, the decorator’s result is what runs when an instance is later created. For example, to simply manage a class just after it is created, return the original class itself:

def decorator(C):
    # Process class C
    return C

@decorator
class C: ...                                    # C = decorator(C)

To instead insert a wrapper layer that intercepts later instance creation calls, return a different callable object:

def decorator(C):
    # Save or use class C
    # Return a different callable: nested def, class with __call__, etc.

@decorator
class C: ...                                    # C = decorator(C)

The callable returned by such a class decorator typically creates and returns a new instance of the original class, augmented in some way to manage its interface. For example, the following inserts an object that intercepts undefined attributes of a class instance:

def decorator(cls):                             # On @ decoration
    class Wrapper:
        def __init__(self, *args):              # On instance creation
            self.wrapped = cls(*args)
        def __getattr__(self, name):            # On attribute fetch
            return getattr(self.wrapped, name)
    return Wrapper

@decorator
class C:                             # C = decorator(C)
    def __init__(self, x, y):        # Run by Wrapper.__init__
        self.attr = 'spam'

x = C(6, 7)                          # Really calls Wrapper(6, 7)
print(x.attr)                        # Runs Wrapper.__getattr__, prints "spam"

In this example, the decorator rebinds the class name to another class, which retains the original class in an enclosing scope and creates and embeds an instance of the original class when it’s called. When an attribute is later fetched from the instance, it is intercepted by the wrapper’s __getattr__ and delegated to the embedded instance of the original class. Moreover, each decorated class creates a new scope, which remembers the original class. We’ll flesh out this example into some more useful code later in this chapter.

Like function decorators, class decorators are commonly coded as either “factory” functions that create and return callables, classes that use __init__ or __call__ methods to intercept call operations, or some combination thereof. Factory functions typically retain state in enclosing scope references, and classes in attributes.

Supporting multiple instances

As with function decorators, with class decorators some callable type combinations work better than others. Consider the following invalid alternative to the class decorator of the prior example:

class Decorator:
    def __init__(self, C):                    # On @ decoration
        self.C = C
    def __call__(self, *args):                # On instance creation
        self.wrapped = self.C(*args)
        return self
    def __getattr__(self, attrname):          # On atrribute fetch
        return getattr(self.wrapped, attrname)

@Decorator
class C: ...                                  # C = Decorator(C)

x = C()
y = C()                                       # Overwrites x!

This code handles multiple decorated classes (each makes a new Decorator instance) and will intercept instance creation calls (each runs __call__). Unlike the prior version, however, this version fails to handle multiple instances of a given class—each instance creation call overwrites the prior saved instance. The original version does support multiple instances, because each instance creation call makes a new independent wrapper object. More generally, either of the following patterns supports multiple wrapped instances:

def decorator(C):                             # On @ decoration
    class Wrapper:
        def __init__(self, *args):            # On instance creation
            self.wrapped = C(*args)
    return Wrapper

class Wrapper: ...
def decorator(C):                             # On @ decoration
    def onCall(*args):                        # On instance creation
        return Wrapper(C(*args))              # Embed instance in instance
    return onCall

We’ll study this phenomenon in a more realistic context later in the chapter; in practice, though, we must be careful to combine callable types properly to support our intent.

Decorator Nesting

Sometimes one decorator isn’t enough. To support multiple steps of augmentation, decorator syntax allows you to add multiple layers of wrapper logic to a decorated function or method. When this feature is used, each decorator must appear on a line of its own. Decorator syntax of this form:

@A
@B
@C
def f(...):
    ...

runs the same as the following:

def f(...):
    ...
f = A(B(C(f)))

Here, the original function is passed through three different decorators, and the resulting callable object is assigned back to the original name. Each decorator processes the result of the prior, which may be the original function or an inserted wrapper.

If all the decorators insert wrappers, the net effect is that when the original function name is called, three different layers of wrapping object logic will be invoked, to augment the original function in three different ways. The last decorator listed is the first applied, and the most deeply nested (insert joke about “interior decorators” here...).

Just as for functions, multiple class decorators result in multiple nested function calls, and possibly multiple levels of wrapper logic around instance creation calls. For example, the following code:

@spam
@eggs
class C:
    ...

X = C()

is equivalent to the following:

class C:
    ...
C = spam(eggs(C))

X = C()

Again, each decorator is free to return either the original class or an inserted wrapper object. With wrappers, when an instance of the original C class is finally requested, the call is redirected to the wrapping layer objects provided by both the spam and eggs decorators, which may have arbitrarily different roles.

For example, the following do-nothing decorators simply return the decorated function:

def d1(F): return F
def d2(F): return F
def d3(F): return F

@d1
@d2
@d3
def func():               # func = d1(d2(d3(func)))
    print('spam')

func()                    # Prints "spam"

The same syntax works on classes, as do these same do-nothing decorators.

When decorators insert wrapper function objects, though, they may augment the original function when called—the following concatenates to its result in the decorator layers, as it runs the layers from inner to outer:

def d1(F): return lambda: 'X' + F()
def d2(F): return lambda: 'Y' + F()
def d3(F): return lambda: 'Z' + F()

@d1
@d2
@d3
def func():               # func = d1(d2(d3(func)))
    return 'spam'

print(func())             # Prints "XYZspam"

We use lambda functions to implement wrapper layers here (each retains the wrapped function in an enclosing scope); in practice, wrappers can take the form of functions, callable classes, and more. When designed well, decorator nesting allows us to combine augmentation steps in a wide variety of ways.

Decorator Arguments

Both function and class decorators can also seem to take arguments, although really these arguments are passed to a callable that in effect returns the decorator, which in turn returns a callable. The following, for instance:

@decorator(A, B)
def F(arg):
    ...

F(99)

is automatically mapped into this equivalent form, where decorator is a callable that returns the actual decorator. The returned decorator in turn returns the callable run later for calls to the original function name:

def F(arg):
    ...
F = decorator(A, B)(F)    # Rebind F to result of decorator's return value

F(99)                     # Essentially calls decorator(A, B)(F)(99)

Decorator arguments are resolved before decoration ever occurs, and they are usually used to retain state information for use in later calls. The decorator function in this example, for instance, might take a form like the following:

def decorator(A, B):
    # Save or use A, B
    def actualDecorator(F):
        # Save or use function F
        # Return a callable: nested def, class with __call__, etc.
        return callable
    return actualDecorator

The outer function in this structure generally saves the decorator arguments away as state information, for use in the actual decorator, the callable it returns, or both. This code snippet retains the state information argument in enclosing function scope references, but class attributes are commonly used as well.

In other words, decorator arguments often imply three levels of callables: a callable to accept decorator arguments, which returns a callable to serve as decorator, which returns a callable to handle calls to the original function or class. Each of the three levels may be a function or class and may retain state in the form of scopes or class attributes. We’ll see concrete examples of decorator arguments employed later in this chapter.

Decorators Manage Functions and Classes, Too

Although much of the rest of this chapter focuses on wrapping later calls to functions and classes, I should underscore that the decorator mechanism is more general than this—it is a protocol for passing functions and classes through a callable immediately after they are created. As such, it can also be used to invoke arbitrary post-creation processing:

def decorator(O):
    # Save or augment function or class O
    return O

@decorator
def F(): ...                 # F = decorator(F)

@decorator
class C: ...                 # C = decorator(C)

As long as we return the original decorated object this way instead of a wrapper, we can manage functions and classes themselves, not just later calls to them. We’ll see more realistic examples later in this chapter that use this idea to register callable objects to an API with decoration and assign attributes to functions when they are created.

Coding Function Decorators

On to the code—in the rest of this chapter, we are going to study working examples that demonstrate the decorator concepts we just explored. This section presents a handful of function decorators at work, and the next shows class decorators in action. Following that, we’ll close out with some larger case studies of class and function decorator usage.

Tracing Calls

To get started, let’s revive the call tracer example we met in Chapter 31. The following defines and applies a function decorator that counts the number of calls made to the decorated function and prints a trace message for each call:

class tracer:
    def __init__(self, func):             # On @ decoration: save original func
        self.calls = 0
        self.func = func
    def __call__(self, *args):            # On later calls: run original func
        self.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (self.calls, self.func.__name__))
        self.func(*args)

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):           # spam = tracer(spam)
    print(a + b + c)         # Wraps spam in a decorator object

Notice how each function decorated with this class will create a new instance, with its own saved function object and calls counter. Also observe how the *args argument syntax is used to pack and unpack arbitrarily many passed-in arguments. This generality enables this decorator to be used to wrap any function with any number of arguments (this version doesn’t yet work on class methods, but we’ll fix that later in this section).

Now, if we import this module’s function and test it interactively, we get the following sort of behavior—each call generates a trace message initially, because the decorator class intercepts it. This code runs under both Python 2.6 and 3.0, as does all code in this chapter unless otherwise noted:

>>> from decorator1 import spam

>>> spam(1, 2, 3)            # Really calls the tracer wrapper object
call 1 to spam
6

>>> spam('a', 'b', 'c')      # Invokes __call__ in class
call 2 to spam
abc

>>> spam.calls               # Number calls in wrapper state information
2
>>> spam
<decorator1.tracer object at 0x02D9A730>

When run, the tracer class saves away the decorated function, and intercepts later calls to it, in order to add a layer of logic that counts and prints each call. Notice how the total number of calls shows up as an attribute of the decorated function—spam is really an instance of the tracer class when decorated (a finding that may have ramifications for programs that do type checking, but is generally benign).

For function calls, the @ decoration syntax can be more convenient than modifying each call to account for the extra logic level, and it avoids accidentally calling the original function directly. Consider a nondecorator equivalent such as the following:

calls = 0
def tracer(func, *args):
    global calls
    calls += 1
    print('call %s to %s' % (calls, func.__name__))
    func(*args)

def spam(a, b, c):
    print(a, b, c)

>>> spam(1, 2, 3)            # Normal non-traced call: accidental?
1 2 3

>>> tracer(spam, 1, 2, 3)    # Special traced call without decorators
call 1 to spam
1 2 3

This alternative can be used on any function without the special @ syntax, but unlike the decorator version, it requires extra syntax at every place where the function is called in your code; furthermore, its intent may not be as obvious, and it does not ensure that the extra layer will be invoked for normal calls. Although decorators are never required (we can always rebind names manually), they are often the most convenient option.

State Information Retention Options

The last example of the prior section raises an important issue. Function decorators have a variety of options for retaining state information provided at decoration time, for use during the actual function call. They generally need to support multiple decorated objects and multiple calls, but there are a number of ways to implement these goals: instance attributes, global variables, nonlocal variables, and function attributes can all be used for retaining state.

Class instance attributes

For example, here is an augmented version of the prior example, which adds support for keyword arguments and returns the wrapped function’s result to support more use cases:

class tracer:                                # State via instance attributes
    def __init__(self, func):                # On @ decorator
        self.calls = 0                       # Save func for later call
        self.func  = func
    def __call__(self, *args, **kwargs):     # On call to original function
        self.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (self.calls, self.func.__name__))
        return self.func(*args, **kwargs)

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):          # Same as: spam = tracer(spam)
    print(a + b + c)        # Triggers tracer.__init__

@tracer
def eggs(x, y):             # Same as: eggs = tracer(eggs)
    print(x ** y)           # Wraps eggs in a tracer object

spam(1, 2, 3)               # Really calls tracer instance: runs tracer.__call__
spam(a=4, b=5, c=6)         # spam is an instance attribute

eggs(2, 16)                 # Really calls tracer instance, self.func is eggs
eggs(4, y=4)                # self.calls is per-function here (need 3.0 nonlocal)

Like the original, this uses class instance attributes to save state explicitly. Both the wrapped function and the calls counter are per-instance information—each decoration gets its own copy. When run as a script under either 2.6 or 3.0, the output of this version is as follows; notice how the spam and eggs functions each have their own calls counter, because each decoration creates a new class instance:

call 1 to spam
6
call 2 to spam
15
call 1 to eggs
65536
call 2 to eggs
256

While useful for decorating functions, this coding scheme has issues when applied to methods (more on this later).

Enclosing scopes and globals

Enclosing def scope references and nested defs can often achieve the same effect, especially for static data like the decorated original function. In this example, though, we would also need a counter in the enclosing scope that changes on each call, and that’s not possible in Python 2.6. In 2.6, we can either use classes and attributes, as we did earlier, or move the state variable out to the global scope, with global declarations:

calls = 0
def tracer(func):                         # State via enclosing scope and global
    def wrapper(*args, **kwargs):         # Instead of class attributes
        global calls                      # calls is global, not per-function
        calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (calls, func.__name__))
        return func(*args, **kwargs)
    return wrapper

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):        # Same as: spam = tracer(spam)
    print(a + b + c)

@tracer
def eggs(x, y):           # Same as: eggs = tracer(eggs)
    print(x ** y)

spam(1, 2, 3)             # Really calls wrapper, bound to func
spam(a=4, b=5, c=6)       # wrapper calls spam

eggs(2, 16)               # Really calls wrapper, bound to eggs
eggs(4, y=4)              # Global calls is not per-function here!

Unfortunately, moving the counter out to the common global scope to allow it to be changed like this also means that it will be shared by every wrapped function. Unlike class instance attributes, global counters are cross-program, not per-function—the counter is incremented for any traced function call. You can tell the difference if you compare this version’s output with the prior version’s—the single, shared global call counter is incorrectly updated by calls to every decorated function:

call 1 to spam
6
call 2 to spam
15
call 3 to eggs
65536
call 4 to eggs
256

Enclosing scopes and nonlocals

Shared global state may be what we want in some cases. If we really want a per-function counter, though, we can either use classes as before, or make use of the new nonlocal statement in Python 3.0, described in Chapter 17. Because this new statement allows enclosing function scope variables to be changed, they can serve as per-decoration and changeable data:

def tracer(func):                        # State via enclosing scope and nonlocal
    calls = 0                            # Instead of class attrs or global
    def wrapper(*args, **kwargs):        # calls is per-function, not global
        nonlocal calls
        calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (calls, func.__name__))
        return func(*args, **kwargs)
    return wrapper

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):        # Same as: spam = tracer(spam)
    print(a + b + c)

@tracer
def eggs(x, y):           # Same as: eggs = tracer(eggs)
    print(x ** y)

spam(1, 2, 3)             # Really calls wrapper, bound to func
spam(a=4, b=5, c=6)       # wrapper calls spam

eggs(2, 16)               # Really calls wrapper, bound to eggs
eggs(4, y=4)              # Nonlocal calls _is_ not per-function here

Now, because enclosing scope variables are not cross-program globals, each wrapped function gets its own counter again, just as for classes and attributes. Here’s the new output when run under 3.0:

call 1 to spam
6
call 2 to spam
15
call 1 to eggs
65536
call 2 to eggs
256

Function attributes

Finally, if you are not using Python 3.X and don’t have a nonlocal statement, you may still be able to avoid globals and classes by making use of function attributes for some changeable state instead. In recent Pythons, we can assign arbitrary attributes to functions to attach them, with func.attr=value. In our example, we can simply use wrapper.calls for state. The following works the same as the preceding nonlocal version because the counter is again per-decorated-function, but it also runs in Python 2.6:

def tracer(func):                        # State via enclosing scope and func attr
    def wrapper(*args, **kwargs):        # calls is per-function, not global
        wrapper.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (wrapper.calls, func.__name__))
        return func(*args, **kwargs)
    wrapper.calls = 0
    return wrapper

Notice that this only works because the name wrapper is retained in the enclosing tracer function’s scope. When we later increment wrapper.calls, we are not changing the name wrapper itself, so no nonlocal declaration is required.

This scheme was almost relegated to a footnote, because it is more obscure than nonlocal in 3.0 and is probably better saved for cases where other schemes don’t help. However, we will employ it in an answer to one of the end-of-chapter questions, where we’ll need to access the saved state from outside the decorator’s code; nonlocals can only be seen inside the nested function itself, but function attributes have wider visibility.

Because decorators often imply multiple levels of callables, you can combine functions with enclosing scopes and classes with attributes to achieve a variety of coding structures. As we’ll see later, though, this sometimes may be subtler than you expect—each decorated function should have its own state, and each decorated class may require state both for itself and for each generated instance.

In fact, as the next section will explain, if we want to apply function decorators to class methods, too, we also have to be careful about the distinction Python makes between decorators coded as callable class instance objects and decorators coded as functions.

Class Blunders I: Decorating Class Methods

When I wrote the first tracer function decorator above, I naively assumed that it could also be applied to any method—decorated methods should work the same, but the automatic self instance argument would simply be included at the front of *args. Unfortunately, I was wrong: when applied to a class’s method, the first version of the tracer fails, because self is the instance of the decorator class and the instance of the decorated subject class is not included in *args. This is true in both Python 3.0 and 2.6.

I introduced this phenomenon earlier in this chapter, but now we can see it in the context of realistic working code. Given the class-based tracing decorator:

class tracer:
    def __init__(self, func):                # On @ decorator
        self.calls = 0                       # Save func for later call
        self.func  = func
    def __call__(self, *args, **kwargs):     # On call to original function
        self.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (self.calls, self.func.__name__))
        return self.func(*args, **kwargs)

decoration of simple functions works as advertised earlier:

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):                           # spam = tracer(spam)
    print(a + b + c)                         # Triggers tracer.__init__

spam(1, 2, 3)                                # Runs tracer.__call__
spam(a=4, b=5, c=6)                          # spam is an instance attribute

However, decoration of class methods fails (more lucid readers might recognize this as our Person class resurrected from the object-oriented tutorial in Chapter 27):

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.name = name
        self.pay  = pay

    @tracer
    def giveRaise(self, percent):            # giveRaise = tracer(giveRaise)
        self.pay *= (1.0 + percent)

    @tracer
    def lastName(self):                      # lastName = tracer(lastName)
        return self.name.split()[-1]

bob = Person('Bob Smith', 50000)             # tracer remembers method funcs
bob.giveRaise(.25)                           # Runs tracer.__call__(???, .25)
print(bob.lastName())                        # Runs tracer.__call__(???)

The root of the problem here is in the self argument of the tracer class’s __call__ method—is it a tracer instance or a Person instance? We really need both as it’s coded: the tracer for decorator state, and the Person for routing on to the original method. Really, self must be the tracer object, to provide access to tracer’s state information; this is true whether decorating a simple function or a method.

Unfortunately, when our decorated method name is rebound to a class instance object with a __call__, Python passes only the tracer instance to self; it doesn’t pass along the Person subject in the arguments list at all. Moreover, because the tracer knows nothing about the Person instance we are trying to process with method calls, there’s no way to create a bound method with an instance, and thus no way to correctly dispatch the call.

In fact, the prior listing winds up passing too few arguments to the decorated method, and results in an error. Add a line to the decorator’s __call__ to print all its arguments to verify this; as you can see, self is the tracer, and the Person instance is entirely absent:

<__main__.tracer object at 0x02D6AD90> (0.25,) {}
call 1 to giveRaise
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "C:/misc/tracer.py", line 56, in <module>
    bob.giveRaise(.25)
  File "C:/misc/tracer.py", line 9, in __call__
    return self.func(*args, **kwargs)
TypeError: giveRaise() takes exactly 2 positional arguments (1 given)

As mentioned earlier, this happens because Python passes the implied subject instance to self when a method name is bound to a simple function only; when it is an instance of a callable class, that class’s instance is passed instead. Technically, Python only makes a bound method object containing the subject instance when the method is a simple function.

Using nested functions to decorate methods

If you want your function decorators to work on both simple functions and class methods, the most straightforward solution lies in using one of the other state retention solutions described earlier—code your function decorator as nested defs, so that you don’t depend on a single self instance argument to be both the wrapper class instance and the subject class instance.

The following alternative applies this fix using Python 3.0 nonlocals. Because decorated methods are rebound to simple functions instead of instance objects, Python correctly passes the Person object as the first argument, and the decorator propagates it on in the first item of *args to the self argument of the real, decorated methods:

# A decorator for both functions and methods

def tracer(func):                        # Use function, not class with __call__
    calls = 0                            # Else "self" is decorator instance only!
    def onCall(*args, **kwargs):
        nonlocal calls
        calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (calls, func.__name__))
        return func(*args, **kwargs)
    return onCall


# Applies to simple functions

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):                       # spam = tracer(spam)
    print(a + b + c)                     # onCall remembers spam

spam(1, 2, 3)                            # Runs onCall(1, 2, 3)
spam(a=4, b=5, c=6)


# Applies to class method functions too!

class Person:
    def __init__(self, name, pay):
        self.name = name
        self.pay  = pay

    @tracer
    def giveRaise(self, percent):        # giveRaise = tracer(giveRaise)
        self.pay *= (1.0 + percent)      # onCall remembers giveRaise

    @tracer
    def lastName(self):                  # lastName = tracer(lastName)
        return self.name.split()[-1]

print('methods...')
bob = Person('Bob Smith', 50000)
sue = Person('Sue Jones', 100000)
print(bob.name, sue.name)
sue.giveRaise(.10)                       # Runs onCall(sue, .10)
print(sue.pay)
print(bob.lastName(), sue.lastName())    # Runs onCall(bob), lastName in scopes

This version works the same on both functions and methods:

call 1 to spam
6
call 2 to spam
15
methods...
Bob Smith Sue Jones
call 1 to giveRaise
110000.0
call 1 to lastName
call 2 to lastName
Smith Jones

Using descriptors to decorate methods

Although the nested function solution illustrated in the prior section is the most straightforward way to support decorators that apply to both functions and class methods, other schemes are possible. The descriptor feature we explored in the prior chapter, for example, can help here as well.

Recall from our discussion in that chapter that a descriptor may be a class attribute assigned to objects with a __get__ method run automatically when that attribute is referenced and fetched (object derivation is required in Python 2.6, but not 3.0):

class Descriptor(object):
    def __get__(self, instance, owner): ...

class Subject:
    attr = Descriptor()

X = Subject()
X.attr         # Roughly runs Descriptor.__get__(Subject.attr, X, Subject)

Descriptors may also have __set__ and __del__ access methods, but we don’t need them here. Now, because the descriptor’s __get__ method receives both the descriptor class and subject class instances when invoked, it’s well suited to decorating methods when we need both the decorator’s state and the original class instance for dispatching calls. Consider the following alternative tracing decorator, which is also a descriptor:

class tracer(object):
    def __init__(self, func):                # On @ decorator
        self.calls = 0                       # Save func for later call
        self.func  = func
    def __call__(self, *args, **kwargs):     # On call to original func
        self.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (self.calls, self.func.__name__))
        return self.func(*args, **kwargs)
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):      # On method attribute fetch
        return wrapper(self, instance)

class wrapper:
    def __init__(self, desc, subj):          # Save both instances
        self.desc = desc                     # Route calls back to  decr
        self.subj = subj
    def __call__(self, *args, **kwargs):
        return self.desc(self.subj, *args, **kwargs)  # Runs tracer.__call__

@tracer
def spam(a, b, c):                           # spam = tracer(spam)
    ...same as prior...                      # Uses __call__ only

class Person:
    @tracer
    def giveRaise(self, percent):            # giveRaise = tracer(giverRaise)
        ...same as prior...                  # Makes giveRaise a descriptor

This works the same as the preceding nested function coding. Decorated functions invoke only its __call__, while decorated methods invoke its __get__ first to resolve the method name fetch (on instance.method); the object returned by __get__ retains the subject class instance and is then invoked to complete the call expression, thereby triggering __call__ (on (args...)). For example, the test code’s call to:

sue.giveRaise(.10)                           # Runs __get__ then __call__

run’s tracer.__get__ first, because the giveRaise attribute in the Person class has been rebound to a descriptor by the function decorator. The call expression then triggers the __call__ method of the returned wrapper object, which in turn invokes tracer.__call__.

The wrapper object retains both descriptor and subject instances, so it can route control back to the original decorator/descriptor class instance. In effect, the wrapper object saves the subject class instance available during method attribute fetch and adds it to the later call’s arguments list, which is passed to __call__. Routing the call back to the descriptor class instance this way is required in this application so that all calls to a wrapped method use the same calls counter state information in the descriptor instance object.

Alternatively, we could use a nested function and enclosing scope references to achieve the same effect—the following version works the same as the preceding one, by swapping a class and object attributes for a nested function and scope references, but it requires noticeably less code:

class tracer(object):
    def __init__(self, func):                # On @ decorator
        self.calls = 0                       # Save func for later call
        self.func  = func
    def __call__(self, *args, **kwargs):     # On call to original func
        self.calls += 1
        print('call %s to %s' % (self.calls, self.func.__name__))
        return self.func(*args, **kwargs)
    def __get__(self, instance, owner):                # On method fetch
        def wrapper(*args, **kwargs):                  # Retain both inst
            return self(instance, *args, **kwargs)     # Runs __call__
        return wrapper

Add print statements to these alternatives’ methods to trace the two-step get/call process on your own, and run them with the same test code as in the nested function alternative shown earlier. In either coding, this descriptor-based scheme is also substantially subtler than the nested function option, and so is probably a second choice here; it may be a useful coding pattern in other contexts, though.

In the rest of this chapter we’re going to be fairly casual about using classes or functions to code our function decorators, as long as they are applied only to functions. Some decorators may not require the instance of the original class, and will still work on both functions and methods if coded as a class—something like Python’s own staticmethod decorator, for example, wouldn’t require an instance of the subject class (indeed, its whole point is to remove the instance from the call).

The moral of this story, though, is that if you want your decorators to work on both simple functions and class methods, you’re better off using the nested-function-based coding pattern outlined here instead of a class with call interception.

Timing Calls

To sample the fuller flavor of what function decorators are capable of, let’s turn to a different use case. Our next decorator times calls made to a decorated function—both the time for one call, and the total time among all calls. The decorator is applied to two functions, in order to compare the time requirements of list comprehensions and the map built-in call (for comparison, also see Chapter 20 for another nondecorator example that times iteration alternatives like these):

import time

class timer:
    def __init__(self, func):
        self.func    = func
        self.alltime = 0
    def __call__(self, *args, **kargs):
        start   = time.clock()
        result  = self.func(*args, **kargs)
        elapsed = time.clock() - start
        self.alltime += elapsed
        print('%s: %.5f, %.5f' % (self.func.__name__, elapsed, self.alltime))
        return result

@timer
def listcomp(N):
    return [x * 2 for x in range(N)]

@timer
def mapcall(N):
    return map((lambda x: x * 2), range(N))

result = listcomp(5)                # Time for this call, all calls, return value
listcomp(50000)
listcomp(500000)
listcomp(1000000)
print(result)
print('allTime = %s' % listcomp.alltime)      # Total time for all listcomp calls

print('')
result = mapcall(5)
mapcall(50000)
mapcall(500000)
mapcall(1000000)
print(result)
print('allTime = %s' % mapcall.alltime)       # Total time for all mapcall calls

print('map/comp = %s' % round(mapcall.alltime / listcomp.alltime, 3))

In this case, a nondecorator approach would allow the subject functions to be used with or without timing, but it would also complicate the call signature when timing is desired (we’d need to add code at every call instead of once at the def), and there would be no direct way to guarantee that all list builder calls in a program are routed through timer logic, short of finding and potentially changing them all.

When run in Python 2.6, the output of this file’s self-test code is as follows:

listcomp: 0.00002, 0.00002
listcomp: 0.00910, 0.00912
listcomp: 0.09105, 0.10017
listcomp: 0.17605, 0.27622
[0, 2, 4, 6, 8]
allTime = 0.276223304917

mapcall: 0.00003, 0.00003
mapcall: 0.01363, 0.01366
mapcall: 0.13579, 0.14945
mapcall: 0.27648, 0.42593
[0, 2, 4, 6, 8]
allTime = 0.425933533452
map/comp = 1.542

Testing subtlety: I didn’t run this under Python 3.0 because, as described in Chapter 14, the map built-in returns an iterator in 3.0, instead of an actual list as in 2.6. Hence, 3.0’s map doesn’t quite compare directly to a list comprehension’s work (as is, the map test takes virtually no time at all in 3.0!).

If you wish to run this under 3.0, too, use list(map()) to force it to build a list like the list comprehension does, or else you’re not really comparing apples to apples. Don’t do so in 2.6, though—if you do, the map test will be charged for building two lists, not one.

The following sort of code would pick fairly for 2.6 and 3.0; note, though, that while this makes the comparison between list comprehensions and map more fair in either 2.6 or 3.0, because range is also an iterator in 3.0, the results for 2.6 and 3.0 won’t compare directly:

...
import sys

@timer
def listcomp(N):
    return [x * 2 for x in range(N)]

if sys.version_info[0] == 2:
    @timer
    def mapcall(N):
        return map((lambda x: x * 2), range(N))
else:
    @timer
    def mapcall(N):
        return list(map((lambda x: x * 2), range(N)))
    ...

Finally, as we learned in the modules part of this book if you want to be able to reuse this decorator in other modules, you should indent the self-test code at the bottom of the file under a __name__ == '__main__' test so it runs only when the file is run, not when it’s imported. We won’t do this, though, because we’re about to add another feature to our code.

Adding Decorator Arguments

The timer decorator of the prior section works, but it would be nice if it was more configurable—providing an output label and turning trace messages on and off, for instance, might be useful in a general-purpose tool like this. Decorator arguments come in handy here: when they’re coded properly, we can use them to specify configuration options that can vary for each decorated function. A label, for instance, might be added as follows:

def timer(label=''):
    def decorator(func):
        def onCall(*args):          # args passed to function
            ...                     # func retained in enclosing scope
            print(label, ...        # label retained in enclosing scope
        return onCall
    return decorator                # Returns that actual decorator

@timer('==>')                       # Like listcomp = timer('==>')(listcomp)
def listcomp(N): ...                # listcomp is rebound to decorator

listcomp(...)                       # Really calls decorator

This code adds an enclosing scope to retain a decorator argument for use on a later actual call. When the listcomp function is defined, it really invokes decorator (the result of timer, run before decoration actually occurs), with the label value available in its enclosing scope. That is, timer returns the decorator, which remembers both the decorator argument and the original function and returns a callable which invokes the original function on later calls.

We can put this structure to use in our timer to allow a label and a trace control flag to be passed in at decoration time. Here’s an example that does just that, coded in a module file named mytools.py so it can be imported as a general tool:

import time

def timer(label='', trace=True):                  # On decorator args: retain args
    class Timer:
        def __init__(self, func):                 # On @: retain decorated func
            self.func    = func
            self.alltime = 0
        def __call__(self, *args, **kargs):       # On calls: call original
            start   = time.clock()
            result  = self.func(*args, **kargs)
            elapsed = time.clock() - start
            self.alltime += elapsed
            if trace:
                format = '%s %s: %.5f, %.5f'
                values = (label, self.func.__name__, elapsed, self.alltime)
                print(format % values)
            return result
    return Timer

Mostly all we’ve done here is embed the original Timer class in an enclosing function, in order to create a scope that retains the decorator arguments. The outer timer function is called before decoration occurs, and it simply returns the Timer class to serve as the actual decorator. On decoration, an instance of Timer is made that remembers the decorated function itself, but also has access to the decorator arguments in the enclosing function scope.

This time, rather than embedding self-test code in this file, we’ll run the decorator in a different file. Here’s a client of our timer decorator, the module file testseqs.py, applying it to sequence iteration alternatives again:

from mytools import timer

@timer(label='[CCC]==>')
def listcomp(N):                           # Like listcomp = timer(...)(listcomp)
    return [x * 2 for x in range(N)]       # listcomp(...) triggers Timer.__call__

@timer(trace=True, label='[MMM]==>')
def mapcall(N):
    return map((lambda x: x * 2), range(N))

for func in (listcomp, mapcall):
    print('')
    result = func(5)        # Time for this call, all calls, return value
    func(50000)
    func(500000)
    func(1000000)
    print(result)
    print('allTime = %s' % func.alltime)   # Total time for all calls

print('map/comp = %s' % round(mapcall.alltime / listcomp.alltime, 3))

Again, if you wish to run this fairly in 3.0, wrap the map function in a list call. When run as-is in 2.6, this file prints the following output—each decorated function now has a label of its own, defined by decorator arguments:

[CCC]==> listcomp: 0.00003, 0.00003
[CCC]==> listcomp: 0.00640, 0.00643
[CCC]==> listcomp: 0.08687, 0.09330
[CCC]==> listcomp: 0.17911, 0.27241
[0, 2, 4, 6, 8]
allTime = 0.272407666337

[MMM]==> mapcall: 0.00004, 0.00004
[MMM]==> mapcall: 0.01340, 0.01343
[MMM]==> mapcall: 0.13907, 0.15250
[MMM]==> mapcall: 0.27907, 0.43157
[0, 2, 4, 6, 8]
allTime = 0.431572169089
map/comp = 1.584

As usual, we can also test this interactively to see how the configuration arguments come into play:

>>> from mytools import timer
>>> @timer(trace=False)                    # No tracing, collect total time
... def listcomp(N):
...     return [x * 2 for x in range(N)]
...
>>> x = listcomp(5000)
>>> x = listcomp(5000)
>>> x = listcomp(5000)
>>> listcomp
<mytools.Timer instance at 0x025C77B0>
>>> listcomp.alltime
0.0051938863738243413

>>> @timer(trace=True, label='\t=>')       # Turn on tracing
... def listcomp(N):
...     return [x * 2 for x in range(N)]
...
>>> x = listcomp(5000)
        => listcomp: 0.00155, 0.00155
>>> x = listcomp(5000)
        => listcomp: 0.00156, 0.00311
>>> x = listcomp(5000)
        => listcomp: 0.00174, 0.00486
>>> listcomp.alltime
0.0048562736325408196

This timing function decorator can be used for any function, both in modules and interactively. In other words, it automatically qualifies as a general-purpose tool for timing code in our scripts. Watch for another example of decorator arguments in the section Implementing Private Attributes, and again in A Basic Range-Testing Decorator for Positional Arguments.

Note

Timing methods: This section’s timer decorator works on any function, but a minor rewrite is required to be able to apply it to class methods too. In short, as our earlier section Class Blunders I: Decorating Class Methods illustrated, it must avoid using a nested class. Because this mutation will be a subject of one of our end-of-chapter quiz questions, though, I’ll avoid giving away the answer completely here.

Managing Functions and Classes Directly

Most of our examples in this chapter have been designed to intercept function and instance creation calls. Although this is typical for decorators, they are not limited to this role. Because decorators work by running new functions and classes through decorator code, they can also be used to manage function and class objects themselves, not just later calls made to them.

Imagine, for example, that you require methods or classes used by an application to be registered to an API for later processing (perhaps that API will call the objects later, in response to events). Although you could provide a registration function to be called manually after the objects are defined, decorators make your intent more explicit.

The following simple implementation of this idea defines a decorator that can be applied to both functions and classes, to add the object to a dictionary-based registry. Because it returns the object itself instead of a wrapper, it does not intercept later calls:

# Registering decorated objects to an API

registry = {}
def register(obj):                          # Both class and func decorator
    registry[obj.__name__] = obj            # Add to registry
    return obj                              # Return obj itself, not a wrapper

@register
def spam(x):
    return(x ** 2)                          # spam = register(spam)

@register
def ham(x):
    return(x ** 3)

@register
class Eggs:                                 # Eggs = register(Eggs)
    def __init__(self, x):
        self.data = x ** 4
    def __str__(self):
        return str(self.data)

print('Registry:')
for name in registry:
    print(name, '=>', registry[name], type(registry[name]))

print('\nManual calls:')
print(spam(2))                              # Invoke objects manually
print(ham(2))                               # Later calls not intercepted
X = Eggs(2)
print(X)

print('\nRegistry calls:')
for name in registry:
    print(name, '=>', registry[name](3))    # Invoke from registry

When this code is run the decorated objects are added to the registry by name, but they still work as originally coded when they’re called later, without being routed through a wrapper layer. In fact, our objects can be run both manually and from inside the registry table:

Registry:
Eggs => <class '__main__.Eggs'> <class 'type'>
ham => <function ham at 0x02CFB738> <class 'function'>
spam => <function spam at 0x02CFB6F0> <class 'function'>

Manual calls:
4
8
16

Registry calls:
Eggs => 81
ham => 27
spam => 9

A user interface might use this technique, for example, to register callback handlers for user actions. Handlers might be registered by function or class name, as done here, or decorator arguments could be used to specify the subject event; an extra def statement enclosing our decorator could be used to retain such arguments for use on decoration.

This example is artificial, but its technique is very general. For example, function decorators might also be used to process function attributes, and class decorators might insert new class attributes, or even new methods, dynamically. Consider the following function decorators—they assign function attributes to record information for later use by an API, but they do not insert a wrapper layer to intercept later calls:

# Augmenting decorated objects directly

>>> def decorate(func):
...     func.marked = True          # Assign function attribute for later use
...     return func
...
>>> @decorate
... def spam(a, b):
...     return a + b
...
>>> spam.marked
True

>>> def annotate(text):             # Same, but value is decorator argument
...     def decorate(func):
...         func.label = text
...         return func
...     return decorate
...
>>> @annotate('spam data')
... def spam(a, b):                 # spam = annotate(...)(spam)
...     return a + b
...
>>> spam(1, 2), spam.label
(3, 'spam data')

Such decorators augment functions and classes directly, without catching later calls to them. We’ll see more examples of class decorations managing classes directly in the next chapter, because this turns out to encroach on the domain of metaclasses; for the remainder of this chapter, let’s turn to two larger case studies of decorators at work.

Example: “Private” and “Public” Attributes

The final two sections of this chapter present larger examples of decorator use. Both are presented with minimal description, partly because this chapter has exceeded its size limits, but mostly because you should already understand decorator basics well enough to study these on your own. Being general-purpose tools, these examples give us a chance to see how decorator concepts come together in more useful code.

Implementing Private Attributes

The following class decorator implements a Private declaration for class instance attributes—that is, attributes stored on an instance, or inherited from one of its classes. It disallows fetch and change access to such attributes from outside the decorated class, but still allows the class itself to access those names freely within its methods. It’s not exactly C++ or Java, but it provides similar access control as an option in Python.

We saw an incomplete first-cut implementation of instance attribute privacy for changes only in Chapter 29. The version here extends this concept to validate attribute fetches too, and it uses delegation instead of inheritance to implement the model. In fact, in a sense this is just an extension to the attribute tracer class decorator we met earlier.

Although this example utilizes the new syntactic sugar of class decorators to code attribute privacy, its attribute interception is ultimately still based upon the __getattr__ and __setattr__ operator overloading methods we met in prior chapters. When a private attribute access is detected, this version uses the raise statement to raise an exception, along with an error message; the exception may be caught in a try or allowed to terminate the script.

Here is the code, along with a self test at the bottom of the file. It will work under both Python 2.6 and 3.0 because it employs 3.0 print and raise syntax, though it catches operator overloading method attributes in 2.6 only (more on this in a moment):

"""
Privacy for attributes fetched from class instances.
See self-test code at end of file for a usage example.
Decorator same as: Doubler = Private('data', 'size')(Doubler).
Private returns onDecorator, onDecorator returns onInstance,
and each onInstance instance embeds a Doubler instance.
"""

traceMe = False
def trace(*args):
    if traceMe: print('[' + ' '.join(map(str, args)) + ']')

def Private(*privates):                          # privates in enclosing scope
    def onDecorator(aClass):                     # aClass in enclosing scope
        class onInstance:                        # wrapped in instance attribute
            def __init__(self, *args, **kargs):
                self.wrapped = aClass(*args, **kargs)
            def __getattr__(self, attr):         # My attrs don't call getattr
                trace('get:', attr)              # Others assumed in wrapped
                if attr in privates:
                    raise TypeError('private attribute fetch: ' + attr)
                else:
                    return getattr(self.wrapped, attr)
            def __setattr__(self, attr, value):             # Outside accesses
                trace('set:', attr, value)                  # Others run normally
                if attr == 'wrapped':                       # Allow my attrs
                    self.__dict__[attr] = value             # Avoid looping
                elif attr in privates:
                    raise TypeError('private attribute change: ' + attr)
                else:
                    setattr(self.wrapped, attr, value)      # Wrapped obj attrs
        return onInstance                                   # Or use __dict__
    return onDecorator


if __name__ == '__main__':
    traceMe = True

    @Private('data', 'size')                   # Doubler = Private(...)(Doubler)
    class Doubler:
        def __init__(self, label, start):
            self.label = label                 # Accesses inside the subject class
            self.data  = start                 # Not intercepted: run normally
        def size(self):
            return len(self.data)              # Methods run with no checking
        def double(self):                      # Because privacy not inherited
            for i in range(self.size()):
                self.data[i] = self.data[i] * 2
        def display(self):
            print('%s => %s' % (self.label, self.data))

    X = Doubler('X is', [1, 2, 3])
    Y = Doubler('Y is', [−10, −20, −30])

    # The followng all succeed
    print(X.label)                             # Accesses outside subject class
    X.display(); X.double(); X.display()       # Intercepted: validated, delegated
    print(Y.label)
    Y.display(); Y.double()
    Y.label = 'Spam'
    Y.display()

    # The following all fail properly
    """
    print(X.size())          # prints "TypeError: private attribute fetch: size"
    print(X.data)
    X.data = [1, 1, 1]
    X.size = lambda S: 0
    print(Y.data)
    print(Y.size())
    """

When traceMe is True, the module file’s self-test code produces the following output. Notice how the decorator catches and validates both attribute fetches and assignments run outside of the wrapped class, but does not catch attribute accesses inside the class itself:

[set: wrapped <__main__.Doubler object at 0x02B2AAF0>]
[set: wrapped <__main__.Doubler object at 0x02B2AE70>]
[get: label]
X is
[get: display]
X is => [1, 2, 3]
[get: double]
[get: display]
X is => [2, 4, 6]
[get: label]
Y is
[get: display]
Y is => [−10, −20, −30]
[get: double]
[set: label Spam]
[get: display]
Spam => [−20, −40, −60]

Implementation Details I

This code is a bit complex, and you’re probably best off tracing through it on your own to see how it works. To help you study, though, here are a few highlights worth mentioning.

Inheritance versus delegation

The first-cut privacy example shown in Chapter 29 used inheritance to mix in a __setattr__ to catch accesses. Inheritance makes this difficult, however, because differentiating between accesses from inside or outside the class is not straightforward (inside access should be allowed to run normally, and outside access should be restricted). To work around this, the Chapter 29 example requires inheriting classes to use __dict__ assignments to set attributes—an incomplete solution at best.

The version here uses delegation (embedding one object inside another) instead of inheritance; this pattern is better suited to our task, as it makes it much easier to distinguish between accesses inside and outside of the subject class. Attribute accesses from outside the subject class are intercepted by the wrapper layer’s overloading methods and delegated to the class if valid; accesses inside the class itself (i.e., through self inside its methods’ code) are not intercepted and are allowed to run normally without checks, because privacy is not inherited here.

Decorator arguments

The class decorator used here accepts any number of arguments, to name private attributes. What really happens, though, is that the arguments are passed to the Private function, and Private returns the decorator function to be applied to the subject class. So, the arguments are used before decoration ever occurs; Private returns the decorator, which in turn “remembers” the privates list as an enclosing scope reference.

State retention and enclosing scopes

Speaking of enclosing scopes, there are actually three levels of state retention at work in this code:

The arguments to Private are used before decoration occurs and are retained as an enclosing scope reference for use in both onDecorator and onInstance.

The class argument to onDecorator is used at decoration time and is retained as an enclosing scope reference for use at instance construction time.

The wrapped instance object is retained as an instance attribute in onInstance, for use when attributes are later accessed from outside the class.

This all works fairly naturally, given Python’s scope and namespace rules.

Using __dict__ and __slots__

The __setattr__ in this code relies on an instance object’s __dict__ attribute namespace dictionary in order to set onInstance’s own wrapped attribute. As we learned in the prior chapter, it cannot assign an attribute directly without looping. However, it uses the setattr built-in instead of __dict__ to set attributes in the wrapped object itself. Moreover, getattr is used to fetch attributes in the wrapped object, since they may be stored in the object itself or inherited by it.

Because of that, this code will work for most classes. You may recall from Chapter 31 that new-style classes with __slots__ may not store attributes in a __dict__. However, because we only rely on a __dict__ at the onInstance level here, not in the wrapped instance, and because setattr and getattr apply to attributes based on both __dict__ and __slots__, our decorator applies to classes using either storage scheme.

Generalizing for Public Declarations, Too

Now that we have a Private implementation, it’s straightforward to generalize the code to allow for Public declarations too—they are essentially the inverse of Private declarations, so we need only negate the inner test. The example listed in this section allows a class to use decorators to define a set of either Private or Public instance attributes (attributes stored on an instance or inherited from its classes), with the following semantics:

Private declares attributes of a class’s instances that cannot be fetched or assigned, except from within the code of the class’s methods. That is, any name declared Private cannot be accessed from outside the class, while any name not declared Private can be freely fetched or assigned from outside the class.

Public declares attributes of a class’s instances that can be fetched or assigned from both outside the class and within the class’s methods. That is, any name declared Public can be freely accessed anywhere, while any name not declared Public cannot be accessed from outside the class.

Private and Public declarations are intended to be mutually exclusive: when using Private, all undeclared names are considered Public, and when using Public, all undeclared names are considered Private. They are essentially inverses, though undeclared names not created by class methods behave slightly differently—they can be assigned and thus created outside the class under Private (all undeclared names are accessible), but not under Public (all undeclared names are inaccessible).

Again, study this code on your own to get a feel for how this works. Notice that this scheme adds an additional fourth level of state retention at the top, beyond that described in the preceding section: the test functions used by the lambdas are saved in an extra enclosing scope. This example is coded to run under either Python 2.6 or 3.0, though it comes with a caveat when run under 3.0 (explained briefly in the file’s docstring and expanded on after the code):

"""
Class decorator with Private and Public attribute declarations.
Controls access to attributes stored on an instance, or inherited
by it from its classes. Private declares attribute names that
cannot be fetched or assigned outside the decorated class, and
Public declares all the names that can. Caveat: this works in
3.0 for normally named attributes only: __X__ operator overloading
methods implicitly run for built-in operations do not trigger
either __getattr__ or __getattribute__ in new-style classes.
Add __X__ methods here to intercept and delegate built-ins.
"""

traceMe = False
def trace(*args):
    if traceMe: print('[' + ' '.join(map(str, args)) + ']')

def accessControl(failIf):
    def onDecorator(aClass):
        class onInstance:
            def __init__(self, *args, **kargs):
                self.__wrapped = aClass(*args, **kargs)
            def __getattr__(self, attr):
                trace('get:', attr)
                if failIf(attr):
                    raise TypeError('private attribute fetch: ' + attr)
                else:
                    return getattr(self.__wrapped, attr)
            def __setattr__(self, attr, value):
                trace('set:', attr, value)
                if attr == '_onInstance__wrapped':
                    self.__dict__[attr] = value
                elif failIf(attr):
                    raise TypeError('private attribute change: ' + attr)
                else:
                    setattr(self.__wrapped, attr, value)
        return onInstance
    return onDecorator

def Private(*attributes):
    return accessControl(failIf=(lambda attr: attr in attributes))

def Public(*attributes):
    return accessControl(failIf=(lambda attr: attr not in attributes))

See the prior example’s self-test code for a usage example. Here’s a quick look at these class decorators in action at the interactive prompt (they work the same in 2.6 and 3.0); as advertised, non-Private or Public names can be fetched and changed from outside the subject class, but Private or non-Public names cannot:

>>> from access import Private, Public

>>> @Private('age')                             # Person = Private('age')(Person)
... class Person:                               # Person = onInstance with state
...     def __init__(self, name, age):
...         self.name = name
...         self.age  = age                     # Inside accesses run normally
...
>>> X = Person('Bob', 40)
>>> X.name                                      # Outside accesses validated
'Bob'
>>> X.name = 'Sue'
>>> X.name
'Sue'
>>> X.age
TypeError: private attribute fetch: age
>>> X.age = 'Tom'
TypeError: private attribute change: age

>>> @Public('name')
... class Person:
...     def __init__(self, name, age):
...         self.name = name
...         self.age  = age
...
>>> X = Person('bob', 40)                       # X is an onInstance
>>> X.name                                      # onInstance embeds Person
'bob'
>>> X.name = 'Sue'
>>> X.name
'Sue'
>>> X.age
TypeError: private attribute fetch: age
>>> X.age = 'Tom'
TypeError: private attribute change: age

Implementation Details II

To help you analyze the code, here are a few final notes on this version. Since this is just a generalization of the preceding section’s example, most of the notes there apply here as well.

Using __X pseudoprivate names

Besides generalizing, this version also makes use of Python’s __X pseudoprivate name mangling feature (which we met in Chapter 30) to localize the wrapped attribute to the control class, by automatically prefixing it with the class name. This avoids the prior version’s risk for collisions with a wrapped attribute that may be used by the real, wrapped class, and it’s useful in a general tool like this. It’s not quite “privacy,” though, because the mangled name can be used freely outside the class. Notice that we also have to use the fully expanded name string ('_onInstance__wrapped') in __setattr__, because that’s what Python changes it to.

Breaking privacy

Although this example does implement access controls for attributes of an instance and its classes, it is possible to subvert these controls in various ways—for instance, by going through the expanded version of the wrapped attribute explicitly (bob.pay might not work, but the fully mangled bob._onInstance__wrapped.pay could!). If you have to explicitly try to do so, though, these controls are probably sufficient for normal intended use. Of course, privacy controls can generally be subverted in any language if you try hard enough (#define private public may work in some C++ implementations, too). Although access controls can reduce accidental changes, much of this is up to programmers in any language; whenever source code may be changed, access control will always be a bit of a pipe dream.

Decorator tradeoffs

We could again achieve the same results without decorators, by using manager functions or coding the name rebinding of decorators manually; the decorator syntax, however, makes this consistent and a bit more obvious in the code. The chief potential downsides of this and any other wrapper-based approach are that attribute access incurs an extra call, and instances of decorated classes are not really instances of the original decorated class—if you test their type with X.__class__ or isinstance(X, C), for example, you’ll find that they are instances of the wrapper class. Unless you plan to do introspection on objects’ types, though, the type issue is probably irrelevant.

Open Issues

As is, this example works as planned under Python 2.6 and 3.0 (provided operator overloading methods to be delegated are redefined in the wrapper). As with most software, though, there is always room for improvement.

Caveat: operator overloading methods fail to delegate under 3.0

Like all delegation-based classes that use __getattr__, this decorator works cross-version for normally named attributes only; operator overloading methods like __str__ and __add__ work differently for new-style classes and so fail to reach the embedded object if defined there when this runs under 3.0.

As we learned in the prior chapter, classic classes look up operator overloading names in instances at runtime normally, but new-style classes do not—they skip the instance entirely and look up such methods in classes. Hence, the __X__ operator overloading methods implicitly run for built-in operations do not trigger either __getattr__ or __getattribute__ in new-style classes in 2.6 and all classes in 3.0; such attribute fetches skip our onInstance.__getattr__ altogether, so they cannot be validated or delegated.

Our decorator’s class is not coded as new-style (by deriving from object), so it will catch operator overloading methods if run under 2.6. Since all classes are new-style automatically in 3.0, though, such methods will fail if they are coded on the embedded object. The simplest workaround in 3.0 is to redefine redundantly in onInstance all the operator overloading methods that can possibly be used in wrapped objects. Such extra methods can be added by hand, by tools that partly automate the task (e.g., with class decorators or the metaclasses discussed in the next chapter), or by definition in superclasses.

To see the difference yourself, try applying the decorator to a class that uses operator overloading methods under 2.6; validations work as before, and both the __str__ method used by printing and the __add__ method run for + invoke the decorator’s __getattr__ and hence wind up being validated and delegated to the subject Person object correctly:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> from access import Private
>>> @Private('age')
... class Person:
...     def __init__(self):
...         self.age = 42
...     def __str__(self):
...         return 'Person: ' + str(self.age)
...     def __add__(self, yrs):
...         self.age += yrs
...
>>> X = Person()
>>> X.age                                   # Name validations fail correctly
TypeError: private attribute fetch: age
>>> print(X)                                # __getattr__ => runs Person.__str__
Person: 42
>>> X + 10                                  # __getattr__ => runs Person.__add__
>>> print(X)                                # __getattr__ => runs Person.__str__
Person: 52

When the same code is run under Python 3.0, though, the implicitly invoked __str__ and __add__ skip the decorator’s __getattr__ and look for definitions in or above the decorator class itself; print winds up finding the default display inherited from the class type (technically, from the implied object superclass in 3.0), and + generates an error because no default is inherited:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> from access import Private
>>> @Private('age')
... class Person:
...     def __init__(self):
...         self.age = 42
...     def __str__(self):
...         return 'Person: ' + str(self.age)
...     def __add__(self, yrs):
...         self.age += yrs
...
>>> X = Person()                            # Name validations still work
>>> X.age                                   # But 3.0 fails to delegate built-ins!
TypeError: private attribute fetch: age
>>> print(X)
<access.onInstance object at 0x025E0790>
>>> X + 10
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for +: 'onInstance' and 'int'
>>> print(X)
<access.onInstance object at 0x025E0790>

Using the alternative __getattribute__ method won’t help here—although it is defined to catch every attribute reference (not just undefined names), it is also not run by built-in operations. Python’s property feature, which we met in Chapter 37, won’t help here either; recall that properties are automatically run code associated with specific attributes defined when a class is written, and are not designed to handle arbitrary attributes in wrapped objects.

As mentioned earlier, the most straightforward solution under 3.0 is to redundantly redefine operator overloading names that may appear in embedded objects in delegation-based classes like our decorator. This isn’t ideal because it creates some code redundancy, especially compared to 2.6 solutions. However, it isn’t too major a coding effort, can be automated to some extent with tools or superclasses, suffices to make our decorator work in 3.0, and allows operator overloading names to be declared Private or Public too (assuming each overloading method runs the failIf test internally):

def accessControl(failIf):
    def onDecorator(aClass):
        class onInstance:
            def __init__(self, *args, **kargs):
                self.__wrapped = aClass(*args, **kargs)

            # Intercept and delegate operator overloading methods
            def __str__(self):
                return str(self.__wrapped)
            def __add__(self, other):
                return self.__wrapped + other
            def __getitem__(self, index):
                return self.__wrapped[index]         # If needed
            def __call__(self, *args, **kargs):
                return self.__wrapped(*arg, *kargs)  # If needed
            ...plus any others needed...

            # Intercept and delegate named attributes
            def __getattr__(self, attr):
                ...
            def __setattr__(self, attr, value):
                ...
        return onInstance
    return onDecorator

With such operator overloading methods added, the prior example with __str__ and __add__ works the same under 2.6 and 3.0, although a substantial amount of extra code may be required to accommodate 3.0—in principle, every operator overloading method that is not run automatically will need to be defined redundantly for 3.0 in a general tool class like this (which is why this extension is omitted in our code). Since every class is new-style in 3.0, delegation-based code is more difficult (though not impossible) in this release.

On the other hand, delegation wrappers could simply inherit from a common superclass that redefines operator overloading methods once, with standard delegation code. Moreover, tools such as additional class decorators or metaclasses might automate some of the work of adding such methods to delegation classes (see the class augmentation examples in Chapter 39 for details). Though still not as simple as the 2.6 solution, such techniques might help make 3.0 delegation classes more general.

Implementation alternatives: __getattribute__ inserts, call stack inspection

Although redundantly defining operator overloading methods in wrappers is probably the most straightforward workaround to Python 3.0 dilemma outlined in the prior section, it’s not necessarily the only one. We don’t have space to explore this issue much further here, so investigating other potential solutions is relegated to a suggested exercise. Because one dead-end alternative underscores class concepts well, though, it merits a brief mention.

One downside of this example is that instance objects are not truly instances of the original class—they are instances of the wrapper instead. In some programs that rely on type testing, this might matter. To support such cases, we might try to achieve similar effects by inserting a __getattribute__ method into the original class, to catch every attribute reference made on its instances. This inserted method would pass valid requests up to its superclass to avoid loops, using the techniques we studied in the prior chapter. Here is the potential change to our class decorator’s code:

# trace support as before

def accessControl(failIf):
    def onDecorator(aClass):
        def getattributes(self, attr):
            trace('get:', attr)
            if failIf(attr):
                raise TypeError('private attribute fetch: ' + attr)
            else:
                return object.__getattribute__(self, attr)
        aClass.__getattribute__ = getattributes
        return aClass
    return onDecorator

def Private(*attributes):
    return accessControl(failIf=(lambda attr: attr in attributes))

def Public(*attributes):
    return accessControl(failIf=(lambda attr: attr not in attributes))

This alternative addresses the type-testing issue but suffers from others. For example, it handles only attribute fetches—as is, this version allows private names to be assigned freely. Intercepting assignments would still have to use __setattr__, and either an instance wrapper object or another class method insertion. Adding an instance wrapper to catch assignments would change the type again, and inserting methods fails if the original class is using a __setattr__ of its own (or a __getattribute__, for that matter!). An inserted __setattr__ would also have to allow for a __slots__ in the client class.

In addition, this scheme does not address the built-in operation attributes issue described in the prior section, since __getattribute__ is not run in these contexts, either. In our case, if Person had a __str__ it would be run by print operations, but only because it was actually present in that class. As before, the __str__ attribute would not be routed to the inserted __getattribute__ method generically—printing would bypass this method altogether and call the class’s __str__ directly.

Although this is probably better than not supporting operator overloading methods in a wrapped object at all (barring redefinition, at least), this scheme still cannot intercept and validate __X__ methods, making it impossible for any of them to be Private. Although most operator overloading methods are meant to be public, some might not be.

Much worse, because this nonwrapper approach works by adding a __getattribute__ to the decorated class, it also intercepts attribute accesses made by the class itself and validates them the same as accesses made from outside—this means the class’s method won’t be able to use Private names, either!

In fact, inserting methods this way is functionally equivalent to inheriting them, and implies the same constraints as our original Chapter 29 privacy code. To know whether an attribute access originated inside or outside the class, our method might need to inspect frame objects on the Python call stack. This might ultimately yield a solution (replace private attributes with properties or descriptors that check the stack, for example), but it would slow access further and is far too dark a magic for us to explore here.

While interesting, and possibly relevant for some other use cases, this method insertion technique doesn’t meet our goals. We won’t explore this option’s coding pattern further here because we will study class augmentation techniques in the next chapter, in conjunction with metaclasses. As we’ll see there, metaclasses are not strictly required for changing classes this way, because class decorators can often serve the same role.

Python Isn’t About Control

Now that I’ve gone to such great lengths to add Private and Public attribute declarations for Python code, I must again remind you that it is not entirely Pythonic to add access controls to your classes like this. In fact, most Python programmers will probably find this example to be largely or totally irrelevant, apart from serving as a demonstration of decorators in action. Most large Python programs get by successfully without any such controls at all. If you do wish to regulate attribute access in order to eliminate coding mistakes, though, or happen to be a soon-to-be-ex-C++-or-Java programmer, most things are possible with Python’s operator overloading and introspection tools.

Chapter Summary

In this chapter, we explored decorators—both the function and class varieties. As we learned, decorators are a way to insert code to be run automatically when a function or class is defined. When a decorator is used, Python rebinds a function or class name to the callable object it returns. This hook allows us to add a layer of wrapper logic to function calls and class instance creation calls, in order to manage functions and instances. As we also saw, manager functions and manual name rebinding can achieve the same effect, but decorators provide a more explicit and uniform solution.

As we’ll see in the next chapter, class decorators can also be used to manage classes themselves, rather than just their instances. Because this functionality overlaps with metaclasses, the topic of the next chapter, you’ll have to read ahead for the rest of this story. First, though, work through the following quiz. Because this chapter was mostly focused on its larger examples, its quiz will ask you to modify some of its code in order to review.

Chapter 39. Metaclasses

In the prior chapter, we explored decorators and studied various examples of their use. In this final chapter of the book, we’re going continue our tool-builders focus and investigate another advanced topic: metaclasses.

In a sense, metaclasses simply extend the code-insertion model of decorators. As we learned in the prior chapter, function and class decorators allow us to intercept and augment function calls and class instance creation calls. In a similar sprit, metaclasses allow us to intercept and augment class creation—they provide an API for inserting extra logic to be run at the conclusion of a class statement, albeit in different ways than decorators. As such, they provide a general protocol for managing class objects in a program.

Like all the subjects dealt with in this part of the book, this is an advanced topic that can be investigated on an as-needed basis. In practice, metaclasses allow us to gain a high level of control over how a set of classes work. This is a powerful concept, and metaclasses are not intended for most application programmers (nor, frankly, the faint of heart!).

On the other hand, metaclasses open the door to a variety of coding patterns that may be difficult or impossible to achieve otherwise, and they are especially of interest to programmers seeking to write flexible APIs or programming tools for others to use. Even if you don’t fall into that category, metaclasses can teach you much about Python’s class model in general.

As in the prior chapter, part of our goal here is also to show more realistic code examples than we did earlier in this book. Although metaclasses are a core language topic and not themselves an application domain, part of this chapter’s goal is to spark your interest in exploring larger application-programming examples after you finish this book.

To Metaclass or Not to Metaclass

Metaclasses are perhaps the most advanced topic in this book, if not the Python language as a whole. To borrow a quote from the comp.lang.python newsgroup by veteran Python core developer Tim Peters (who is also the author of the famous “import this” Python motto):

[Metaclasses] are deeper magic than 99% of users should ever worry about. If you wonder whether you need them, you don’t (the people who actually need them know with certainty that they need them, and don’t need an explanation about why).

In other words, metaclasses are primarily intended for programmers building APIs and tools for others to use. In many (if not most) cases, they are probably not the best choice in applications work. This is especially true if you’re developing code that other people will use in the future. Coding something “because it seems cool” is not generally a reasonable justification, unless you are experimenting or learning.

Still, metaclasses have a wide variety of potential roles, and it’s important to know when they can be useful. For example, they can be used to enhance classes with features like tracing, object persistence, exception logging, and more. They can also be used to construct portions of a class at runtime based upon configuration files, apply function decorators to every method of a class generically, verify conformance to expected interfaces, and so on.

In their more grandiose incarnations, metaclasses can even be used to implement alternative coding patterns such as aspect-oriented programming, object/relational mappers (ORMs) for databases, and more. Although there are often alternative ways to achieve such results (as we’ll see, the roles of class decorators and metaclasses often intersect), metaclasses provide a formal model tailored to those tasks. We don’t have space to explore all such applications first-hand in this chapter but you should feel free to search the Web for additional use cases after studying the basics here.

Probably the reason for studying metaclasses most relevant to this book is that this topic can help demystify Python’s class mechanics in general. Although you may or may not code or reuse them in your work, a cursory understanding of metaclasses can impart a deeper understanding of Python at large.

Increasing Levels of Magic

Most of this book has focused on straightforward application-coding techniques, as most programmers spend their time writing modules, functions, and classes to achieve real-world goals. They may use classes and make instances, and might even do a bit of operator overloading, but they probably won’t get too deep into the details of how their classes actually work.

However, in this book we’ve also seen a variety of tools that allow us to control Python’s behavior in generic ways, and that often have more to do with Python internals or tool building than with application-programming domains:

Introspection attributes

Special attributes like __class__ and __dict__ allow us to inspect internal implementation aspects of Python objects, in order to process them generically—to list all attributes of an object, display a class’s name, and so on.

Operator overloading methods

Specially named methods such as __str__ and __add__ coded in classes intercept and provide behavior for built-in operations applied to class instances, such as printing, expression operators, and so on. They are run automatically in response to built-in operations and allow classes to conform to expected interfaces.

Attribute interception methods

A special category of operator overloading methods provide a way to intercept attribute accesses on instances generically: __getattr__, __setattr__, and __getattribute__ allow wrapper classes to insert automatically run code that may validate attribute requests and delegate them to embedded objects. They allow any number of attributes of an object—either selected attributes, or all of them—to be computed when accessed.

Class properties

The property built-in allows us to associate code with a specific class attribute that is automatically run when the attribute is fetched, assigned, or deleted. Though not as generic as the prior paragraph’s tools, properties allow for automatic code invocation on access to specific attributes.

Class attribute descriptors

Really, property is a succinct way to define an attribute descriptor that runs functions on access automatically. Descriptors allow us to code in a separate class __get__, __set__, and __delete__ handler methods that are run automatically when an attribute assigned to an instance of that class is accessed. They provide a general way to insert automatically run code when a specific attribute is accessed, and they are triggered after an attribute is looked up normally.

Function and class decorators

As we saw in Chapter 38, the special @callable syntax for decorators allows us to add logic to be automatically run when a function is called or a class instance is created. This wrapper logic can trace or time calls, validate arguments, manage all instances of a class, augment instances with extra behavior such as attribute fetch validation, and more. Decorator syntax inserts name-rebinding logic to be run at the end of function and class definition statements—decorated function and class names are rebound to callable objects that intercept later calls.

As mentioned in this chapter’s introduction, metaclasses are a continuation of this story—they allow us to insert logic to be run automatically when a class object is created, at the end of a class statement. This logic doesn’t rebind the class name to a decorator callable, but rather routes creation of the class itself to specialized logic.

In other words, metaclasses are ultimately just another way to define automatically run code. Via metaclasses and the other tools just listed, Python provides ways for us to interject logic in a variety of contexts—at operator evaluation, attribute access, function calls, class instance creation, and now class object creation.

Unlike class decorators, which usually add logic to be run at instance creation time, metaclasses run at class creation time; as such, they are hooks generally used for managing or augmenting classes, instead of their instances.

For example, metaclasses can be used to add decoration to all methods of classes automatically, register all classes in use to an API, add user-interface logic to classes automatically, create or extend classes from simplified specifications in text files, and so on. Because we can control how classes are made (and by proxy the behavior their instances acquire), their applicability is potentially very wide.

As we’ve also seen, many of these advanced Python tools have intersecting roles. For example, attributes can often be managed with properties, descriptors, or attribute interception methods. As we’ll see in this chapter, class decorators and metaclasses can often be used interchangeably as well. Although class decorators are often used to manage instances, they can be used to manage classes instead; similarly, while metaclasses are designed to augment class construction, they can often insert code to manage instances, too. Since the choice of which technique to use is sometimes purely subjective, knowledge of the alternatives can help you pick the right tool for a given task.

The Downside of “Helper” Functions

Also like the decorators of the prior chapter, metaclasses are often optional, from a theoretical perspective. We can usually achieve the same effect by passing class objects through manager functions (sometimes known as “helper” functions), much as we can achieve the goals of decorators by passing functions and instances through manager code. Just like decorators, though, metaclasses:

Provide a more formal and explicit structure

Help ensure that application programmers won’t forget to augment their classes according to an API’s requirements

Avoid code redundancy and its associated maintenance costs by factoring class customization logic into a single location, the metaclass

To illustrate, suppose we want to automatically insert a method into a set of classes. Of course, we could do this with simple inheritance, if the subject method is known when we code the classes. In that case, we can simply code the method in a superclass and have all the classes in question inherit from it:

class Extras:
    def extra(self, args):              # Normal inheritance: too static
        ...

class Client1(Extras): ...              # Clients inherit extra methods
class Client2(Extras): ...
class Client3(Extras): ...

X = Client1()                           # Make an instance
X.extra()                               # Run the extra methods

Sometimes, though, it’s impossible to predict such augmentation when classes are coded. Consider the case where classes are augmented in response to choices made in a user interface at runtime, or to specifications typed in a configuration file. Although we could code every class in our imaginary set to manually check these, too, it’s a lot to ask of clients (required is abstract here—it’s something to be filled in):

def extra(self, arg): ...

class Client1: ...                      # Client augments: too distributed
if required():
    Client1.extra = extra

class Client2: ...
if required():
    Client2.extra = extra

class Client3: ...
if required():
    Client3.extra = extra

X = Client1()
X.extra()

We can add methods to a class after the class statement like this because a class method is just a function that is associated with a class and has a first argument to receive the self instance. Although this works, it puts all the burden of augmentation on client classes (and assumes they’ll remember to do this at all!).

It would be better from a maintenance perspective to isolate the choice logic in a single place. We might encapsulate some of this extra work by routing classes though a manager function—such a manager function would extend the class as required and handle all the work of runtime testing and configuration:

def extra(self, arg): ...

def extras(Class):                      # Manager function: too manual
    if required():
        Class.extra = extra

class Client1: ...
extras(Client1)

class Client2: ...
extras(Client2)

class Client3: ...
extras(Client3)

X = Client1()
X.extra()

This code runs the class through a manager function immediately after it is created. Although manager functions like this one can achieve our goal here, they still put a fairly heavy burden on class coders, who must understand the requirements and adhere to them in their code. It would be better if there were a simple way to enforce the augmentation in the subject classes, so that they don’t need to deal with and can’t forget to use the augmentation. In other words, we’d like to be able to insert some code to run automatically at the end of a class statement, to augment the class.

This is exactly what metaclasses do—by declaring a metaclass, we tell Python to route the creation of the class object to another class we provide:

def extra(self, arg): ...

class Extras(type):
    def __init__(Class, classname, superclasses, attributedict):
        if required():
            Class.extra = extra

class Client1(metaclass=Extras): ...    # Metaclass declaration only
class Client2(metaclass=Extras): ...    # Client class is instance of meta
class Client3(metaclass=Extras): ...

X = Client1()                           # X is instance of Client1
X.extra()

Because Python invokes the metaclass automatically at the end of the class statement when the new class is created, it can augment, register, or otherwise manage the class as needed. Moreover, the only requirement for the client classes is that they declare the metaclass; every class that does so will automatically acquire whatever augmentation the metaclass provides, both now and in the future if the metaclass changes. Although it may be difficult to see in this small example, metaclasses generally handle such tasks better than other approaches.

Metaclasses Versus Class Decorators: Round 1

Having said that, it’s also interesting to note that the class decorators described in the preceding chapter sometimes overlap with metaclasses in terms of functionality. Although they are typically used for managing or augmenting instances, class decorators can also augment classes, independent of any created instances.

For example, suppose we coded our manager function to return the augmented class, instead of simply modifying it in-place. This would allow a greater degree of flexibility, because the manager would be free to return any type of object that implements the class’s expected interface:

def extra(self, arg): ...

def extras(Class):
    if required():
        Class.extra = extra
    return Class

class Client1: ...
Client1 = extras(Client1)

class Client2: ...
Client2 = extras(Client2)

class Client3: ...
Client3 = extras(Client3)

X = Client1()
X.extra()

If you think this is starting to look reminiscent of class decorators, you’re right. In the prior chapter we presented class decorators as a tool for augmenting instance creation calls. Because they work by automatically rebinding a class name to the result of a function, though, there’s no reason that we can’t use them to augment the class before any instances are ever created. That is, class decorators can apply extra logic to classes, not just instances, at creation time:

def extra(self, arg): ...

def extras(Class):
    if required():
        Class.extra = extra
    return Class

@extras
class Client1: ...             # Client1 = extras(Client1)

@extras
class Client2: ...             # Rebinds class independent of instances

@extras
class Client3: ...

X = Client1()                  # Makes instance of augmented class
X.extra()                      # X is instance of original Client1

Decorators essentially automate the prior example’s manual name rebinding here. Just like with metaclasses, because the decorator returns the original class, instances are made from it, not from a wrapper object. In fact, instance creation is not intercepted at all.

In this specific case—adding methods to a class when it’s created—the choice between metaclasses and decorators is somewhat arbitrary. Decorators can be used to manage both instances and classes, and they intersect with metaclasses in the second of these roles.

However, this really addresses only one operational mode of metaclasses. As we’ll see, decorators correspond to metaclass __init__ methods in this role, but metaclasses have additional customization hooks. As we’ll also see, in addition to class initialization, metaclasses can perform arbitrary construction tasks that might be more difficult with decorators.

Moreover, although decorators can manage both instances and classes, the converse is not as direct—metaclasses are designed to manage classes, and applying them to managing instances is less straightforward. We’ll explore this difference in code later in this chapter.

Much of this section’s code has been abstract, but we’ll flesh it out into a real working example later in this chapter. To fully understand how metaclasses work, though, we first need to get a clearer picture of their underlying model.

The Metaclass Model

To really understand how metaclasses do their work, you need to understand a bit more about Python’s type model and what happens at the end of a class statement.

Classes Are Instances of type

So far in this book, we’ve done most of our work by making instances of built-in types like lists and strings, as well as instances of classes we code ourselves. As we’ve seen, instances of classes have some state information attributes of their own, but they also inherit behavioral attributes from the classes from which they are made. The same holds true for built-in types; list instances, for example, have values of their own, but they inherit methods from the list type.

While we can get a lot done with such instance objects, Python’s type model turns out to be a bit richer than I’ve formally described. Really, there’s a hole in the model we’ve seen thus far: if instances are created from classes, what is it that creates our classes? It turns out that classes are instances of something, too:

In Python 3.0, user-defined class objects are instances of the object named type, which is itself a class.

In Python 2.6, new-style classes inherit from object, which is a subclass of type; classic classes are instances of type and are not created from a class.

We explored the notion of types in Chapter 9 and the relationship of classes to types in Chapter 31, but let’s review the basics here so we can see how they apply to metaclasses.

Recall that the type built-in returns the type of any object (which is itself an object). For built-in types like lists, the type of the instance is the built-in list type, but the type of the list type is the type type itself—the type object at the top of the hierarchy creates specific types, and specific types create instances. You can see this for yourself at the interactive prompt. In Python 3.0, for example:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> type([])                     # In 3.0 list is instance of list type
<class 'list'>
>>> type(type([]))               # Type of list is type class
<class 'type'>

>>> type(list)                   # Same, but with type names
<class 'type'>
>>> type(type)                   # Type of type is type: top of hierarchy
<class 'type'>

As we learned when studying new-style class changes in Chapter 31, the same is generally true in Python 2.6 (and older), but types are not quite the same as classes—type is a unique kind of built-in object that caps the type hierarchy and is used to construct types:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> type([])                     # In 2.6, type is a bit different
<type 'list'>
>>> type(type([]))
<type 'type'>

>>> type(list)
<type 'type'>
>>> type(type)
<type 'type'>

It turns out that the type/instance relationship holds true for classes as well: instances are created from classes, and classes are created from type. In Python 3.0, though, the notion of a “type” is merged with the notion of a “class.” In fact, the two are essentially synonyms—classes are types, and types are classes. That is:

Types are defined by classes that derive from type.

User-defined classes are instances of type classes.

User-defined classes are types that generate instances of their own.

As we saw earlier, this equivalence effects code that tests the type of instances: the type of an instance is the class from which it was generated. It also has implications for the way that classes are created that turn out to be the key to this chapter’s subject. Because classes are normally created from a root type class by default, most programmers don’t need to think about this type/class equivalence. However, it opens up new possibilities for customizing both classes and their instances.

For example, classes in 3.0 (and new-style classes in 2.6) are instances of the type class, and instance objects are instances of their classes; in fact, classes now have a __class__ that links to type, just as an instance has a __class__ that links to the class from which it was made:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> class C: pass                 # 3.0 class object (new-style)
...
>>> X = C()                       # Class instance object

>>> type(X)                       # Instance is instance of class
<class '__main__.C'>
>>> X.__class__                   # Instance's class
<class '__main__.C'>

>>> type(C)                       # Class is instance of type
<class 'type'>
>>> C.__class__                   # Class's class is type
<class 'type'>

Notice especially the last two lines here—classes are instances of the type class, just as normal instances are instances of a class. This works the same for both built-ins and user-defined class types in 3.0. In fact, classes are not really a separate concept at all: they are simply user-defined types, and type itself is defined by a class.

In Python 2.6, things work similarly for new-style classes derived from object, because this enables 3.0 class behavior:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> class C(object): pass         # In 2.6 new-style classes,
...                               # classes have a class too
>>> X = C()

>>> type(X)
<class '__main__.C'>
>>> type(C)
<type 'type'>

>>> X.__class__
<class '__main__.C'>
>>> C.__class__
<type 'type'>

Classic classes in 2.6 are a bit different, though—because they reflect the class model in older Python releases, they do not have a __class__ link, and like built-in types in 2.6 they are instances of type, not a type class:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> class C: pass                 # In 2.6 classic classes,
...                               # classes have no class themselves
>>> X = C()

>>> type(X)
<type 'instance'>
>>> type(C)
<type 'classobj'>

>>> X.__class__
<class __main__.C at 0x005F85A0>
>>> C.__class__
AttributeError: class C has no attribute '__class__'

Metaclasses Are Subclasses of Type

So why do we care that classes are instances of a type class in 3.0? It turns out that this is the hook that allows us to code metaclasses. Because the notion of type is the same as class today, we can subclass type with normal object-oriented techniques and class syntax to customize it. And because classes are really instances of the type class, creating classes from customized subclasses of type allows us to implement custom kinds of classes. In full detail, this all works out quite naturally—in 3.0, and in 2.6 new-style classes:

type is a class that generates user-defined classes.

Metaclasses are subclasses of the type class.

Class objects are instances of the type class, or a subclass thereof.

Instance objects are generated from a class.

In other words, to control the way classes are created and augment their behavior, all we need to do is specify that a user-defined class be created from a user-defined metaclass instead of the normal type class.

Notice that this type instance relationship is not quite the same as inheritance: user-defined classes may also have superclasses from which they and their instances inherit attributes (inheritance superclasses are listed in parentheses in the class statement and show up in a class’s __bases__ tuple). The type from which a class is created, and of which it is an instance, is a different relationship. The next section describes the procedure Python follows to implement this instance-of type relationship.

Class Statement Protocol

Subclassing the type class to customize it is really only half of the magic behind metaclasses. We still need to somehow route a class’s creation to the metaclass, instead of the default type. To fully understand how this is arranged, we also need to know how class statements do their business.

We’ve already learned that when Python reaches a class statement, it runs its nested block of code to create its attributes—all the names assigned at the top level of the nested code block generate attributes in the resulting class object. These names are usually method functions created by nested defs, but they can also be arbitrary attributes assigned to create class data shared by all instances.

Technically speaking, Python follows a standard protocol to make this happen: at the end of a class statement, and after running all its nested code in a namespace dictionary, it calls the type object to create the class object:

class = type(classname, superclasses, attributedict)

The type object in turn defines a __call__ operator overloading method that runs two other methods when the type object is called:

type.__new__(typeclass, classname, superclasses, attributedict)
type.__init__(class, classname, superclasses, attributedict)

The __new__ method creates and returns the new class object, and then the __init__ method initializes the newly created object. As we’ll see in a moment, these are the hooks that metaclass subclasses of type generally use to customize classes.

For example, given a class definition like the following:

class Spam(Eggs):                # Inherits from Eggs
    data = 1                     # Class data attribute
    def meth(self, arg):         # Class method attribute
        pass

Python will internally run the nested code block to create two attributes of the class (data and meth), and then call the type object to generate the class object at the end of the class statement:

Spam = type('Spam', (Eggs,), {'data': 1, 'meth': meth, '__module__': '__main__'})

Because this call is made at the end of the class statement, it’s an ideal hook for augmenting or otherwise processing a class. The trick lies in replacing type with a custom subclass that will intercept this call. The next section shows how.

Chapter Summary

In this chapter, we studied metaclasses and explored examples of them in action. Metaclasses allow us to tap into the class creation protocol of Python, in order to manage or augment user-defined classes. Because they automate this process, they can provide better solutions for API writers then manual code or helper functions; because they encapsulate such code, they can minimize maintenance costs better than some other approaches.

Along the way, we also saw how the roles of class decorators and metaclasses often intersect: because both run at the conclusion of a class statement, they can sometimes be used interchangeably. Class decorators can be used to manage both class and instance objects; metaclasses can, too, although they are more directly targeted toward classes.

Since this chapter covered an advanced topic, we’ll work through just a few quiz questions to review the basics (if you’ve made it this far in a chapter on metaclasses, you probably already deserve extra credit!). Because this is the last part of the book, we’ll forego the end-of-part exercises. Be sure to see the appendixes that follow for pointers on installation steps, and the solutions to the prior parts’ exercises.

Once you finish the quiz, you’ve officially reached the end of this book. Now that you know Python inside and out, your next step, should you choose to take it, is to explore the libraries, techniques, and tools available in the application domains in which you work. Because Python is so widely used, you’ll find ample resources for using it in almost any application you can think of—from GUIs, the Web, and databases to numeric programming, robotics, and system administration.

This is where Python starts to become truly fun, but this is also where this book’s story ends, and others’ begin. For pointers on where to turn after this book, see the list of recommended follow-up texts in the Preface. Good luck with your journey. And of course, “Always look on the bright side of Life!”

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

A metaclass is a class used to create a class. Normal classes are instances of the type class by default. Metaclasses are usually subclasses of the type class, which redefines class creation protocol methods in order to customize the class creation call issued at the end of a class statement; they typically redefine the methods __new__ and __init__ to tap into the class creation protocol. Metaclasses can also be coded other ways—as simple functions, for example—but they are responsible for making and returning an object for the new class.

In Python 3.0 and later, use a keyword argument in the class header line: class C(metaclass=M). In Python 2.X, use a class attribute instead: __metaclass__ = M. In 3.0, the class header line can also name normal superclasses (a.k.a. base classes) before the metaclass keyword argument.

Because both are automatically triggered at the end of a class statement, class decorators and metaclasses can both be used to manage classes. Decorators rebind a class name to a callable’s result and metaclasses route class creation through a callable, but both hooks can be used for similar purposes. To manage classes, decorators simply augment and return the original class objects. Metaclasses augment a class after they create it.

Because both are automatically triggered at the end of a class statement, class decorators and metaclasses can both be used to manage class instances, by inserting a wrapper object to catch instance creation calls. Decorators may rebind the class name to a callable run on instance creation that retains the original class object. Metaclasses can do the same, but they must also create the class object, so their usage is somewhat more complex in this role.

Our chief weapon is decorators...decorators and metaclasses...metaclasses and decorators.... Our two weapons are metaclasses and decorators...and ruthless efficiency.... Our three weapons are metaclasses, decorators, and ruthless efficiency...and an almost fanatical devotion to Guido.... Our four...no....Amongst our weapons.... Amongst our weaponry...are such elements as metaclasses, decorators.... I’ll come in again....

Installing the Python Interpreter

Because you need the Python interpreter to run Python scripts, the first step in using Python is usually installing Python. Unless one is already available on your machine, you’ll need to fetch, install, and possibly configure a recent version of Python on your computer. You’ll only need to do this once per machine, and if you will be running a frozen binary (described in Chapter 2) or self-installing system, you may not need to do much more.

Is Python Already Present?

Before you do anything else, check whether you already have a recent Python on your machine. If you are working on Linux, Mac OS X, or some Unix systems, Python is probably already installed on your computer, though it may be one or two releases behind the cutting edge. Here’s how to check:

On Windows, check whether there is a Python entry in the Start button’s All Programs menu (at the bottom left of the screen).

On Mac OS X, open a Terminal window (Applications→Utilities→Terminal) and type python at the prompt.

On Linux and Unix, type python at a shell prompt (a.k.a. terminal window), and see what happens. Alternatively, try searching for “python” in the usual places—/usr/bin, /usr/local/bin, etc.

If you find a Python, make sure it’s a recent version. Although any recent Python will do for most of this text, this edition focuses on Python 3.0 and 2.6 specifically, so you may want to install one of these to run some of the examples in this book.

Speaking of versions, I recommend starting out with Python 3.0 or later if you’re learning Python anew and don’t need to deal with existing 2.X code; otherwise, you should generally use Python 2.6. Some popular Python-based systems still use older releases, though (2.5 is still widespread), so if you’re working with existing systems be sure to use a version relevant to your needs; the next section describes locations where you can fetch a variety of Python versions.

Where to Get Python

If there is no Python on your machine, you will need to install one yourself. The good news is that Python is an open source system that is freely available on the Web and very easy to install on most platforms.

You can always fetch the latest and greatest standard Python release from http://www.python.org, Python’s official website. Look for the Downloads link on that page, and choose a release for the platform on which you will be working. You’ll find prebuilt self-installer files for Windows (run to install), Installer Disk Images for Mac OS X (installed per Mac conventions), the full source code distribution (typically compiled on Linux, Unix, or OS X machines to generate an interpreter), and more.

Although Python is standard on Linux these days, you can also find RPMs for Linux on the Web (unpack them with rpm). Python’s website also has links to pages where versions for other platforms are maintained, either at Python.org itself or offsite. A Google web search is another great way to find Python packages. Among other platforms, you can find Python pre-built for iPods, Palm handhelds, Nokia cell phones, PlayStation and PSP, Solaris, AS/400, and Windows Mobile.

If you find yourself pining for a Unix environment on a Windows machine, you might also be interested in installing Cygwin and its version of Python (see http://www.cygwin.com). Cygwin is a GPL-licensed library and toolset that provides full Unix functionality on Windows machines, and it includes a prebuilt Python that makes use of the all the Unix tools provided.

You can also find Python on CD-ROMs supplied with Linux distributions, included with some products and computer systems, and enclosed with some other Python books. These tend to lag behind the current release somewhat, but usually not seriously so.

In addition, you can find Python in some free and commercial development bundles. For example, ActiveState distributes Python as part of its ActivePython, a package that combines standard Python with extensions for Windows development such as PyWin32, an IDE called PythonWin (described in Chapter 3), and other commonly used extensions. Python can also be had today in the Enthought Python Distribution—a package aimed at scientific computing needs—as well as in Portable Python, preconfigured to run directly from a portable device. Search the Web for details.

Finally, if you are interested in alternative Python implementations, run a web search to check out Jython (the Python port to the Java environment) and IronPython (Python for the C#/.NET world), both of which are described in Chapter 2. Installation of these systems is beyond the scope of this book.

Installation Steps

Once you’ve downloaded Python, you need to install it. Installation steps are very platform-specific, but here are a few pointers for the major Python platforms:

Windows

On Windows, Python comes as a self-installer MSI program file—simply double-click on its file icon, and answer Yes or Next at every prompt to perform a default install. The default install includes Python’s documentation set and support for tkinter (Tkinter in Python 2.6) GUIs, shelve databases, and the IDLE development GUI. Python 3.0 and 2.6 are normally installed in the directories C:\Python30 and C:\Python26, though this can be changed at install time.

For convenience, after the install Python shows up in the Start button’s All Programs menu. Python’s menu there has five entries that give quick access to common tasks: starting the IDLE user interface, reading module documentation, starting an interactive session, reading Python’s standard manuals in a web browser, and uninstalling. Most of these options involve concepts explored in detail elsewhere in this text.

When installed on Windows, Python also by default automatically registers itself to be the program that opens Python files when their icons are clicked (a program launch technique described in Chapter 3). It is also possible to build Python from its source code on Windows, but this is not commonly done.

One note for Windows Vista users: security features of the some versions of Vista change some of the rules for using MSI installer files. Although this may be a nonissue by the time you read these words, see the sidebar The Python MSI Installer on Windows Vista in this appendix for assistance if the current Python installer does not work, or does not place Python in the correct place on your machine.

Linux

On Linux, Python is available as one or more RPM files, which you unpack in the usual way (consult the RPM manpage for details). Depending on which RPMs you download, there may be one for Python itself, and another that adds support for tkinter GUIs and the IDLE environment. Because Linux is a Unix-like system, the next paragraph applies as well.

Unix

On Unix systems, Python is usually compiled from its full C source code distribution. This usually only requires you to unpack the file and run simple config and make commands; Python configures its own build procedure automatically, according to the system on which it is being compiled. However, be sure to see the package’s README file for more details on this process. Because Python is open source, its source code may be used and distributed free of charge.

On other platforms the installation details can differ widely, but they generally follow the platform’s normal conventions. Installing the “Pippy” port of Python for PalmOS, for example, requires a hotsync operation with your PDA, and Python for the Sharp Zaurus Linux-based PDA comes as one or more .ipk files, which you simply run to install it. Because additional install procedures for both executable and source forms are well documented, though, we’ll skip further details here.

The Python MSI Installer on Windows Vista

As I write this, the Python self-installer for Windows is an .msi installation file. This format works fine on Windows XP (simply double-click on the file, and it runs), but it can have issues on some versions of Windows Vista. In particular, running the MSI installer by clicking on it may cause Python to be installed at the root of the C: drive, instead of in the correct C:\PythonXX directory. Python still works in the root directory, but this is not the correct place to install it.

This is a Vista security-related issue; in short, MSI files are not true executables, so they do not correctly inherit administrator permissions, even if run by the administrator user. Instead, MSI files are run via the Windows Registry—their filenames are associated with the MSI installer program.

This problem seems to be either Python- or Vista-version specific. On a recent laptop, for example, Python 2.6 and 3.0 installed without issue. To install Python 2.5.2 on my Vista-based OQO handheld, though, I had to use a command-line approach to force the required administrator permissions.

If Python doesn’t install in the right place for you, here’s the workaround: go to your Start button, select the All Programs entry, choose Accessories, right-click on the Command Prompt entry there, choose “Run as administrator,” and select Continue in the access control dialog. Now, within the Command Prompt window, issue a cd command to change to the directory where your Python MSI installer file resides (e.g., cd C:\user\downloads), and then run the MSI installer manually by typing a command line of the form msiexec /i python-2.5.1.msi. Finally, follow the usual GUI interactions to complete the install.

Naturally, this behavior may change over time. This procedure may not be required in every version of Vista, and additional workarounds may be possible (such as disabling Vista security, if you dare). It’s also possible that the Python self-installer may eventually be provided in a different format that obviates this problem—as a true executable, for instance. Be sure to try your installer by simply clicking its icon to see if it works properly before attempting any workarounds.

Configuring Python

After you’ve installed Python, you may want to configure some system settings that impact the way Python runs your code. (If you are just getting started with the language, you can probably skip this section completely; there is usually no need to specify any system settings for basic programs.)

Generally speaking, parts of the Python interpreter’s behavior can be configured with environment variable settings and command-line options. In this section, we’ll take a brief look at both, but be sure to see other documentation sources for more details on the topics we introduce here.

Python Environment Variables

Environment variables—known to some as shell variables, or DOS variables—are system-wide settings that live outside Python and thus can be used to customize the interpreter’s behavior each time it is run on a given computer. Python recognizes a handful of environment variable settings, but only a few are used often enough to warrant explanation here. Table A-1 summarizes the main Python-related environment variable settings.

Table A-1. Important environment variables

Variable

|

Role

PATH (or path)

|

System shell search path (for finding “python”)

PYTHONPATH

|

Python module search path (for imports)

PYTHONSTARTUP

|

Path to Python interactive startup file

TCL_LIBRARY, TK_LIBRARY

|

GUI extension variables (tkinter)

These variables are straightforward to use, but here are a few pointers:

PATH

The PATH setting lists a set of directories that the operating system searches for executable programs. It should normally include the directory where your Python interpreter lives (the python program on Unix, or the python.exe file on Windows).

You don’t need to set this variable at all if you are willing to work in the directory where Python resides, or type the full path to Python in command lines. On Windows, for instance, the PATH is irrelevant if you run a cd C:\Python30 before running any code (to change to the directory where Python lives), or always type C:\Python30\python instead of just python (giving a full path). Also, note that PATH settings are mostly for launching programs from command lines; they are usually irrelevant when launching via icon clicks and IDEs.

PYTHONPATH

The PYTHONPATH setting serves a role similar to PATH: the Python interpreter consults the PYTHONPATH variable to locate module files when you import them in a program. If used, this variable is set to a platform-dependent list of directory names, separated by colons on Unix and semicolons on Windows. This list normally includes just your own source code directories. Its content is merged into the sys.path module import search path, along with the script’s directory, any path file settings, and standard library directories.

You don’t need to set this variable unless you will be performing cross-directory imports—because Python always searches the home directory of the program’s top-level file automatically, this setting is required only if a module needs to import another module that lives in a different directory. See also the discussion of .pth path files later in this appendix for an alternative to PYTHONPATH. For more on the module search path, refer to Chapter 21.

PYTHONSTARTUP

If PYTHONSTARTUP is set to the pathname of a file of Python code, Python executes the file’s code automatically whenever you start the interactive interpreter, as though you had typed it at the interactive command line. This is a rarely used but handy way to make sure you always load certain utilities when working interactively; it saves an import.

tkinter settings

If you wish to use the tkinter GUI toolkit (named Tkinter in 2.6), you might have to set the two GUI variables in the last line of Table A-1 to the names of the source library directories of the Tcl and Tk systems (much like PYTHONPATH). However, these settings are not required on Windows systems (where tkinter support is installed alongside Python), and they’re usually not required elsewhere if Tcl and Tk reside in standard directories.

Note that because these environment settings are external to Python itself, when you set them is usually irrelevant: this can be done before or after Python is installed, as long as they are set the way you require before Python is actually run.

Getting tkinter (and IDLE) GUI Support on Linux

The IDLE interface described in Chapter 2 is a Python tkinter GUI program. The tkinter module (named Tkinter in 2.6) is a GUI toolkit, and it’s a complete, standard component of Python on Windows and some other platforms. On some Linux systems, though, the underlying GUI library may not be a standard installed component. To add GUI support to your Python on Linux if needed, try running a command line of the form yum tkinter to automatically install tkinter’s underlying libraries. This should work on Linux distributions (and some other systems) on which the yum installation program is available.

How to Set Configuration Options

The way to set Python-related environment variables, and what to set them to, depends on the type of computer you’re working on. And again, remember that you won’t necessarily have to set these at all right away; especially if you’re working in IDLE (described in Chapter 3), configuration is not required up front.

But suppose, for illustration, that you have generally useful module files in directories called utilities and package1 somewhere on your machine, and you want to be able to import these modules from files located in other directories. That is, to load a file called spam.py from the utilities directory, you want to be able to say:

import spam

from another file located anywhere on your computer. To make this work, you’ll have to configure your module search path one way or another to include the directory containing spam.py. Here are a few tips on this process.

Unix/Linux shell variables

On Unix systems, the way to set environment variables depends on the shell you use. Under the csh shell, you might add a line like the following in your .cshrc or .login file to set the Python module search path:

setenv PYTHONPATH /usr/home/pycode/utilities:/usr/lib/pycode/package1

This tells Python to look for imported modules in two user-defined directories. Alternatively, if you’re using the ksh shell, the setting might instead appear in your .kshrc file and look like this:

export PYTHONPATH="/usr/home/pycode/utilities:/usr/lib/pycode/package1"

Other shells may use different (but analogous) syntax.

DOS variables (Windows)

If you are using MS-DOS, or some older flavors of Windows, you may need to add an environment variable configuration command to your C:\autoexec.bat file, and reboot your machine for the changes to take effect. The configuration command on such machines has a syntax unique to DOS:

set PYTHONPATH=c:\pycode\utilities;d:\pycode\package1

You can type such a command in a DOS console window, too, but the setting will then be active only for that one console window. Changing your .bat file makes the change permanent and global to all programs.

Windows environment variable GUI

On more recent versions of Windows, including XP and Vista, you can instead set PYTHONPATH and other variables via the system environment variable GUI without having to edit files or reboot. On XP, select the Control Panel, choose the System icon, pick the Advanced tab, and click the Environment Variables button to edit or add new variables (PYTHONPATH is usually a user variable). Use the same variable name and values syntax shown in the DOS set command earlier. The procedure is similar on Vista, but you may have to verify operations along the way.

You do not need to reboot your machine, but be sure to restart Python if it’s open so that it picks up your changes—it configures its path at startup time only. If you’re working in a Windows Command Prompt window, you’ll probably need to restart that to pick up your changes as well.

Windows registry

If you are an experienced Windows user, you may also be able to configure the module search path by using the Windows Registry Editor. Go to Start→Run... and type regedit. Assuming the typical registry tool is on your machine, you can then navigate to Python’s entries and make your changes. This is a delicate and error-prone procedure, though, so unless you’re familiar with the registry, I suggest using other options (indeed, this is akin to performing brain surgery on your computer, so be careful!).

Path files

Finally, if you choose to extend the module search path with a .pth file instead of the PYTHONPATH variable, you might instead code a text file that looks like the following on Windows (e.g., file C:\Python30\mypath.pth):

c:\pycode\utilities
d:\pycode\package1

Its contents will differ per platform, and its container directory may differ per both platform and Python release. Python locates this file automatically when it starts up.

Directory names in path files may be absolute, or relative to the directory containing the path file; multiple .pth files can be used (all their directories are added), and .pth files may appear in various automatically checked directories that are platform- and version-specific. In general, a Python release numbered Python N.M typically looks for path files in C:\PythonNM and C:\PythonNM\Lib\site-packages on Windows, and in /usr/local/lib/pythonN.M/site-packages and /usr/local/lib/site-python on Unix and Linux. See Chapter 21 for more on using path files to configure the sys.path import search path.

Because environment settings are often optional, and because this isn’t a book on operating system shells, I’ll defer to other sources for further details. Consult your system shell’s manpages or other documentation for more information, and if you have trouble figuring out what your settings should be, ask your system administrator or another local expert for help.

Python Command-Line Options

When you start Python from a system command line (a.k.a. a shell prompt), you can pass in a variety of option flags to control how Python runs. Unlike system-wide environment variables, command-line options can be different each time you run a script. The complete form of a Python command-line invocation in 3.0 looks like this (2.6 is roughly the same, with a few option differences):

python [-bBdEhiOsSuvVWx?] [-c command | -m module-name | script | - ] [args]

Most command lines only make use of the script and args parts of this format, to run a program’s source file with arguments to be used by the program itself. To illustrate, consider the following script file, main,py, which prints the command-line arguments list made available to the script as sys.argv:

# File main.py
import sys
print(sys.argv)

In the following command line, both python and main.py can also be complete directory paths, and the three arguments (a b –c) meant for the script show up in the sys.argv list. The first item in sys.argv is always the script file’s name, when it is known:

c:\Python30> python main.py a b –c            # Most common: run a script file
['main.py', 'a', 'b', '-c']

Other code format specification options allow you to specify Python code to be run on the command line itself (-c), to accept code to run from the standard input stream (a – means read from a pipe or redirected input stream file), and so on:

c:\Python30> python -c "print(2 ** 100)"      # Read code from command argument
1267650600228229401496703205376

c:\Python30> python -c "import main"          # Import a file to run its code
['-c']

c:\Python30> python - < main.py a b –c        # Read code from standard input
['-', 'a', 'b', '-c']

c:\Python30> python - a b -c < main.py        # Same effect as prior line
['-', 'a', 'b', '-c']

The –m code specification locates a module on Python’s module search path (sys.path) and runs it as a top-level script (as module __main__). Leave off the “.py” suffix here, since the filename is a module:

c:\Python30> python -m main a b –c            # Locate/run module as script
['c:\\Python30\\main.py', 'a', 'b', '-c']

The –m option also supports running modules in packages with relative import syntax, as well as modules located in .zip archives. This switch is commonly used to run the pdb debugger and profile profiler modules from a command line for a script invocation rather than interactively, though this usage mode seems to have changed somewhat in 3.0 (profile appears to have been affected by the removal of execfile in 3.0, and pdb steps into superfluous input/output code in the new 3.0 io module):

c:\Python30> python -m pdb main.py a b -c              # Debug a script
--Return--
> c:\python30\lib\io.py(762)closed()->False
-> return self.raw.closed
(Pdb) c

c:\Python30> C:\python26\python -m pdb main.py a b -c  # Better in 2.6?
> c:\python30\main.py(1)<module>()
-> import sys
(Pdb) c

c:\Python30> python -m profile main.py a b -c          # Profile a script

c:\Python30> python -m cProfile main.py a b -c         # Low-overhead profiler

Immediately after the “python” and before the designation of code to be run, Python accepts additional arguments that control its own behavior. These arguments are consumed by Python itself and are not meant for the script being run. For example, -O runs Python in optimized mode, -u forces standard streams to be unbuffered, and –i enters interactive mode after running a script:

c:\Python30> python –u main.py a b -c          # Unbuffered output streams

Python 2.6 supports additional options that promote 3.0 compatibility (−3, -Q) and detecting inconsistent tab indentation usage, which is always detected and reported in 3.0 (-t; see Chapter 12). See the Python manuals or reference texts for more details on available command-line options. Or better yet, ask Python itself—run a command-line form like this:

c:\Python30> python -?

to request Python’s help display, which documents available command-line options. If you deal with complex command lines, be sure to also check out the standard library modules getopt and optparse, which support more sophisticated command-line processing.

Part VI, Classes and OOP

See Test Your Knowledge: Part VI Exercises in Chapter 31 for the exercises.

Inheritance. Here’s the solution code for this exercise (file adder.py), along with some interactive tests. The __add__ overload has to appear only once, in the superclass, as it invokes type-specific add methods in subclasses:

class Adder:
    def add(self, x, y):
        print('not implemented!')
    def __init__(self, start=[]):
        self.data = start
    def __add__(self, other):                    # Or in subclasses?
        return self.add(self.data, other)        # Or return type?

class ListAdder(Adder):
    def add(self, x, y):
        return x + y

class DictAdder(Adder):
    def add(self, x, y):
        new = {}
        for k in x.keys(): new[k] = x[k]
        for k in y.keys(): new[k] = y[k]
        return new

% python
>>> from adder import *
>>> x = Adder()
>>> x.add(1, 2)
not implemented!
>>> x = ListAdder()
>>> x.add([1], [2])
[1, 2]
>>> x = DictAdder()
>>> x.add({1:1}, {2:2})
{1: 1, 2: 2}

>>> x = Adder([1])
>>> x + [2]
not implemented!
>>>
>>> x = ListAdder([1])
>>> x + [2]
[1, 2]
>>> [2] + x
Traceback (innermost last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
TypeError: __add__ nor __radd__ defined for these operands

Notice in the last test that you get an error for expressions where a class instance appears on the right of a +; if you want to fix this, use __radd__ methods, as described in “Operator Overloading” in Chapter 29.

If you are saving a value in the instance anyhow, you might as well rewrite the add method to take just one argument, in the spirit of other examples in this part of the book:

class Adder:
    def __init__(self, start=[]):
        self.data = start
    def __add__(self, other):              # Pass a single argument
        return self.add(other)             # The left side is in self
    def add(self, y):
        print('not implemented!')

class ListAdder(Adder):
    def add(self, y):
        return self.data + y

class DictAdder(Adder):
    def add(self, y):
        pass                               # Change to use self.data instead of x

x = ListAdder([1, 2, 3])
y = x + [4, 5, 6]
print(y)                                   # Prints [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]

Because values are attached to objects rather than passed around, this version is arguably more object-oriented. And, once you’ve gotten to this point, you’ll probably find that you can get rid of add altogether and simply define type-specific __add__ methods in the two subclasses.

Operator overloading. The solution code (file mylist.py) uses a few operator overloading methods that the text didn’t say much about, but they should be straightforward to understand. Copying the initial value in the constructor is important because it may be mutable; you don’t want to change or have a reference to an object that’s possibly shared somewhere outside the class. The __getattr__ method routes calls to the wrapped list. For hints on an easier way to code this in Python 2.2 and later, see Extending Types by Subclassing in Chapter 31:

class MyList:
    def __init__(self, start):
        #self.wrapped = start[:]       # Copy start: no side effects
        self.wrapped = []              # Make sure it's a list here
        for x in start: self.wrapped.append(x)
    def __add__(self, other):
        return MyList(self.wrapped + other)
    def __mul__(self, time):
        return MyList(self.wrapped * time)
    def __getitem__(self, offset):
        return self.wrapped[offset]
    def __len__(self):
        return len(self.wrapped)
    def __getslice__(self, low, high):
        return MyList(self.wrapped[low:high])
    def append(self, node):
        self.wrapped.append(node)
    def __getattr__(self, name):       # Other methods: sort/reverse/etc
        return getattr(self.wrapped, name)
    def __repr__(self):
        return repr(self.wrapped)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    x = MyList('spam')
    print(x)
    print(x[2])
    print(x[1:])
    print(x + ['eggs'])
    print(x * 3)
    x.append('a')
    x.sort()
    for c in x: print(c, end=' ')

% python mylist.py
['s', 'p', 'a', 'm']
a
['p', 'a', 'm']
['s', 'p', 'a', 'm', 'eggs']
['s', 'p', 'a', 'm', 's', 'p', 'a', 'm', 's', 'p', 'a', 'm']
a a m p s

Note that it’s important to copy the start value by appending instead of slicing here, because otherwise the result may not be a true list and so will not respond to expected list methods, such as append (e.g., slicing a string returns another string, not a list). You would be able to copy a MyList start value by slicing because its class overloads the slicing operation and provides the expected list interface; however, you need to avoid slice-based copying for objects such as strings.

Subclassing. My solution (mysub.py) appears below. Your solution should be similar:

from mylist import MyList

class MyListSub(MyList):
    calls = 0                                      # Shared by instances

    def __init__(self, start):
        self.adds = 0                              # Varies in each instance
        MyList.__init__(self, start)

    def __add__(self, other):
        MyListSub.calls += 1                       # Class-wide counter
        self.adds += 1                             # Per-instance counts
        return MyList.__add__(self, other)

    def stats(self):
        return self.calls, self.adds               # All adds, my adds

if __name__ == '__main__':
    x = MyListSub('spam')
    y = MyListSub('foo')
    print(x[2])
    print(x[1:])
    print(x + ['eggs'])
    print(x + ['toast'])
    print(y + ['bar'])
    print(x.stats())

% python mysub.py
a
['p', 'a', 'm']
['s', 'p', 'a', 'm', 'eggs']
['s', 'p', 'a', 'm', 'toast']
['f', 'o', 'o', 'bar']
(3, 2)

Attribute methods. I worked through this exercise as follows. Notice that in Python 2.6, operators try to fetch attributes through __getattr__, too; you need to return a value to make them work. Caveat: as noted in Chapter 30, __getattr__ is not called for built-in operations in Python 3.0, so the following expression won’t work as shown; in 3.0, a class like this must redefine __X__ operator overloading methods explicitly. More on this in Chapters 30, 37, and 38.

>>> class Meta:
...     def __getattr__(self, name):
...         print('get', name)
...     def __setattr__(self, name, value):
...         print('set', name, value)
...
>>> x = Meta()
>>> x.append
get append
>>> x.spam = "pork"
set spam pork
>>>
>>> x + 2
get __coerce__
Traceback (innermost last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
TypeError: call of non-function
>>>
>>> x[1]
get __getitem__
Traceback (innermost last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
TypeError: call of non-function

>>> x[1:5]
get __len__
Traceback (innermost last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
TypeError: call of non-function

Set objects. Here’s the sort of interaction you should get. Comments explain which methods are called. Also, note that sets are a built-in type in Python today, so this is largely just a coding exercise (see Chapter 5 for more on sets).

% python
>>> from setwrapper import Set
>>> x = Set([1, 2, 3, 4])          # Runs __init__
>>> y = Set([3, 4, 5])

>>> x & y                          # __and__, intersect, then __repr__
Set:[3, 4]
>>> x | y                          # __or__, union, then __repr__
Set:[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]

>>> z = Set("hello")               # __init__ removes duplicates
>>> z[0], z[-1]                    # __getitem__
('h', 'o')

>>> for c in z: print(c, end=' ')  # __getitem__
...
h e l o
>>> len(z), z                      # __len__, __repr__
(4, Set:['h', 'e', 'l', 'o'])

>>> z & "mello", z | "mello"
(Set:['e', 'l', 'o'], Set:['h', 'e', 'l', 'o', 'm'])

My solution to the multiple-operand extension subclass looks like the following class (file multiset.py). It only needs to replace two methods in the original set. The class’s documentation string explains how it works:

from setwrapper import Set

class MultiSet(Set):
    """
    Inherits all Set names, but extends intersect
    and union to support multiple operands; note
    that "self" is still the first argument (stored
    in the *args argument now); also note that the
    inherited & and | operators call the new methods
    here with 2 arguments, but processing more than
    2 requires a method call, not an expression:
    """

    def intersect(self, *others):
        res = []
        for x in self:                         # Scan first sequence
            for other in others:               # For all other args
                if x not in other: break       # Item in each one?
            else:                              # No: break out of loop
                res.append(x)                  # Yes: add item to end
        return Set(res)

    def union(*args):                          # self is args[0]
        res = []
        for seq in args:                       # For all args
            for x in seq:                      # For all nodes
                if not x in res:
                    res.append(x)              # Add new items to result
        return Set(res)

Your interaction with the extension will look something like the following. Note that you can intersect by using & or calling intersect, but you must call intersect for three or more operands; & is a binary (two-sided) operator. Also, note that we could have called MultiSet simply Set to make this change more transparent if we used setwrapper.Set to refer to the original within multiset:

>>> from multiset import *
>>> x = MultiSet([1,2,3,4])
>>> y = MultiSet([3,4,5])
>>> z = MultiSet([0,1,2])

>>> x & y, x | y                               # Two operands
(Set:[3, 4], Set:[1, 2, 3, 4, 5])

>>> x.intersect(y, z)                          # Three operands
Set:[]
>>> x.union(y, z)
Set:[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 0]
>>> x.intersect([1,2,3], [2,3,4], [1,2,3])     # Four operands
Set:[2, 3]
>>> x.union(range(10))                         # Non-MultiSets work, too
Set:[1, 2, 3, 4, 0, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]

Class tree links. Here is the way I changed the lister classes, and a rerun of the test to show its format. Do the same for the dir-based version, and also do this when formatting class objects in the tree climber variant:

class ListInstance:
    def __str__(self):
        return '<Instance of %s(%s), address %s:\n%s>' % (
                           self.__class__.__name__,       # My class's name
                           self.__supers(),               # My class's own supers
                           id(self),                      # My address
                           self.__attrnames()) )          # name=value list
    def __attrnames(self):
        ...unchanged...
    def __supers(self):
        names = []
        for super in self.__class__.__bases__:            # One level up from class
            names.append(super.__name__)                  # name, not str(super)
        return ', '.join(names)

C:\misc> python testmixin.py
<Instance of Sub(Super, ListInstance), address 7841200:
        name data1=spam
        name data2=eggs
        name data3=42
>

Composition. My solution is below (file lunch.py), with comments from the description mixed in with the code. This is one case where it’s probably easier to express a problem in Python than it is in English:

class Lunch:
    def __init__(self):                          # Make/embed Customer, Employee
        self.cust = Customer()
        self.empl = Employee()
    def order(self, foodName):                   # Start Customer order simulation
        self.cust.placeOrder(foodName, self.empl)
    def result(self):                            # Ask the Customer about its Food
        self.cust.printFood()

class Customer:
    def __init__(self):                          # Initialize my food to None
        self.food = None
    def placeOrder(self, foodName, employee):    # Place order with Employee
        self.food = employee.takeOrder(foodName)
    def printFood(self):                         # Print the name of my food
        print(self.food.name)

class Employee:
    def takeOrder(self, foodName):               # Return Food, with desired name
        return Food(foodName)

class Food:
    def __init__(self, name):                    # Store food name
        self.name = name

if __name__ == '__main__':
    x = Lunch()                                  # Self-test code
    x.order('burritos')                          # If run, not imported
    x.result()
    x.order('pizza')
    x.result()

% python lunch.py
burritos
pizza

Zoo animal hierarchy. Here is the way I coded the taxonomy in Python (file zoo.py); it’s artificial, but the general coding pattern applies to many real structures, from GUIs to employee databases. Notice that the self.speak reference in Animal triggers an independent inheritance search, which finds speak in a subclass. Test this interactively per the exercise description. Try extending this hierarchy with new classes, and making instances of various classes in the tree:

class Animal:
    def reply(self):   self.speak()              # Back to subclass
    def speak(self):   print('spam')             # Custom message

class Mammal(Animal):
    def speak(self):   print('huh?')

class Cat(Mammal):
    def speak(self):   print('meow')

class Dog(Mammal):
    def speak(self):   print('bark')

class Primate(Mammal):
    def speak(self):   print('Hello world!')

class Hacker(Primate): pass                      # Inherit from Primate

The Dead Parrot Sketch. Here’s how I implemented this one (file parrot.py). Notice how the line method in the Actor superclass works: by accessing self attributes twice, it sends Python back to the instance twice, and hence invokes two inheritance searches—self.name and self.says() find information in the specific subclasses:

class Actor:
    def line(self): print(self.name + ':', repr(self.says()))

class Customer(Actor):
    name = 'customer'
    def says(self): return "that's one ex-bird!"

class Clerk(Actor):
    name = 'clerk'
    def says(self): return "no it isn't..."

class Parrot(Actor):
    name = 'parrot'
    def says(self): return None

class Scene:
    def __init__(self):
        self.clerk    = Clerk()                  # Embed some instances
        self.customer = Customer()               # Scene is a composite
        self.subject  = Parrot()

    def action(self):
        self.customer.line()                     # Delegate to embedded
        self.clerk.line()
        self.subject.line()